<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Developing an E-book and Other Interactive Instructional Materials for Technician Education in Vacuum Technology]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paul Tymann</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ptymann@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922832</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project will develop an electronic textbook (E-book) to support vacuum technology education.  Vacuum technology is a critical, enabling technology for many industries, with semiconductor manufacturing being one of the largest.  According to the 2019 report from the Semiconductor Industry Association, the global semiconductor industry is a key growth sector in the global economy, with the US semiconductor industry accounting for almost half the global market share in 2018.  US-based industry semiconductor sales exceeded $200 billion in 2018 and the industry employs over 241,000 direct jobs.  Currently, a cohort of community colleges prepares manufacturing technicians for the US semiconductor industry.  Preparing technicians for this industry is a challenge for community colleges especially in complex technologies such as vacuum technology.  One of the challenges is finding technician-level textbooks and equipping learning environments that facilitate the development of industry-needed skills.  The E-book is expected to fill this need through its text and its associated animations, tutorials, video demonstrations, and interactive assessments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will convert the first four chapters of the text "Introduction to Vacuum Technology" by David M. Hata into a modern electronic book. This format will increase access to vacuum technology instructional resources for both students and incumbent workers.  In addition, the project will develop a laboratory guide to help community college instructors develop hands-on learning environments for their students.  This laboratory guide will present options for implementing vacuum training systems, along with video demonstrations of equipment set-up and operation for laboratory experiments.  All materials will be classroom-tested at Erie Community College, Normandale Community College, and other partner colleges.  Erie Community College and Normandale Community College will license the e-book and associated resources through a Creative Commons license, and disseminate it with help of The Society of Vacuum Coaters, a professional society, and Lesker, Inc., a vacuum equipment supplier. This project is funded by the Advanced Technological Education program that focuses on the education of technicians for the advanced-technology fields that drive the nation's economy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000454</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
<LastName>Louwagie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nancy Louwagie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nancy.louwagie@normandale.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000545584</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elena</FirstName>
<LastName>Brewer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elena V Brewer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[brewer@ecc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000595839</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Erie Community College</Name>
<CityName>ORCHARD PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>141272199</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7168511416</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4041 SOUTHWESTERN BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CNSNH6LM6NY7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ERIE COMMUNITY COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Erie Community College]]></Name>
<CityName>Williamsville</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142217095</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6205 Main St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Electronic components with their underlying integrated circuits enable the functions and operation of devices that people around the world use every day, such as, computers, smart phones, household appliances, automobiles, medical devices, and many others.&nbsp; Vacuum systems are a critical yet not well-known technology that enable the production of semiconductor devices.&nbsp; Vacuum systems create process conditions that make it possible to manipulate materials at the atomic level.&nbsp; Unplanned downtime of vacuum systems at these businesses can result in millions of dollars in lost revenues.&nbsp; The semiconductor industry and many other types of manufacturing and research organizations rely on qualified vacuum technicians to maintain, troubleshoot, and repair vacuum equipment systems so these systems operate as intended.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<br /> Project DUE #2000454 (Developing an E-book and Other Interactive Instructional Materials for Technician Education in Vacuum Technology) was funded by the National Science Foundation from October 2020 to September 2023. SUNY Erie Community College (Williamsville, NY) administered the award and partnered with Normandale Community College (Bloomington, MN), sub-awardee, to create online accessible open educational resources that support instruction of a vacuum technology curriculum.&nbsp; This project addressed an important need to provide &ldquo;off-the-shelf&rdquo; type resources for educators who want to develop a curriculum for instruction in vacuum technology either as a stand-alone program or as part of other educational programs such as semiconductor manufacturing, micro- and nanotechnology and other engineering technologies.&nbsp; Principal Investigator Elena Brewer (SUNY Erie ) and Co-Principal Investigator Nancy Louwagie (Normandale ) coordinated the project work completed by a team consisting of faculty, staff, subject matter experts (SMEs) from various organizations, and other academia/industry partners.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />Over the course of the project, the project team developed the free e-book &ldquo;Introduction to Vacuum Technology&rdquo;.&nbsp; The e-book introduces students to the applications of vacuum technology, the different types of components used to create vacuum systems, the important scientific principles that apply to vacuum system operations, basic sequences of vacuum system operation and approaches to troubleshooting rough vacuum systems.&nbsp; This e-book supports various functions intended to enhance the reading and user experience. &nbsp;The enhanced functions incorporated in this e-book include animations, simulations, video demonstrations, an in-line glossary, and interactive quizzes.&nbsp; The e-book is accompanied by a student laboratory manual and instructor&rsquo;s guide that showcase 10 sets of learning activities that can be delivered in different modalities.&nbsp; The instructor&rsquo;s guide provides a bill of materials to construct a rough vacuum system, system schematics, operational instructions, and video demonstrations for running the hands-on experiments.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />The educational resources developed under grant project DUE #2000454 were reviewed by ten subject matter experts from industry and academia. The educational materials developed were pilot-tested in courses by eight faculty members at five different institutions in the states of Minnesota, Pennsylvania and New York. All of the above-mentioned resources are available at no cost from Milne Open Textbook site <a href="https://milneopentextbooks.org/introduction-to-vacuum-technology/">https://milneopentextbooks.org/introduction-to-vacuum-technology/</a>.&nbsp; <br /> <br /></p> <p>A total of 117 student participants were directly impacted by the curriculum resources developed as project deliverables during pilot testing of the materials from January 2022 through September 2023. Student participants were located in the states of Minnesota, Pennsylvania, and New York. 34% of these students were already employed in the vacuum industry.&nbsp; 89% of students were non-traditional students with 49% of the total student participants identifying as veterans.</p> <p><br />This project also provided opportunities for faculty to participate in a professional development workshop that addressed instruction of rough vacuum technology.&nbsp; This workshop was attended by 12 faculty members from 7 different states.&nbsp; The faculty represented programs associated with engineering technology, microelectronics, semiconductor fabrication, physics, and computer science.&nbsp; Faculty participants were introduced to the educational resources developed under this grant.&nbsp; They had opportunities to practice the learning activities using rough vacuum systems.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />SUNY Erie and Normandale<em>&nbsp;</em>continue to support existing partnerships with vacuum-reliant businesses, research organizations, professional societies and other colleges as well as establish new partnerships. &nbsp;These partnerships are critical to providing a relevant and high-quality education in vacuum technology that supports the nation&rsquo;s demand to hire a knowledgeable and qualified workforce to work in semiconductor manufacturing and other vacuum reliant industries.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In Summary:</p> <p>Project DUE #2000454 had a national impact: open educational resources developed under this project were pilot tested by 117 students enrolled in courses at five higher education institutions located in three different states. This project also had a corresponding impact on twenty faculty members who used these open educational resources to facilitate course delivery and/or attended a professional development workshop. &nbsp;During the e-book development and review phase, ten subject matter experts representing both industry and academia provided feedback on the accuracy, quality, and suitability of the e-book resource for its intended audience.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><br />Project #2000454 continues to have an impact on vacuum technician education by providing open educational resources to support curricula and course delivery for vacuum technology, micro and nanotechnology, semiconductor fabrication, and other engineering technologies programs across the country.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 01/27/2024<br> Modified by: Elena&nbsp;V&nbsp;Brewer</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000454/2000454_10670559_1706415228717_Picture2--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000454/2000454_10670559_1706415228717_Picture2--rgov-800width.png" title="Professional Development Workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000454/2000454_10670559_1706415228717_Picture2--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Professional Development Workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Professional development workshop, June 21-23, 2023, Bloomington, MN</div> <div class="imageCredit">David M. Hata, Elena V. Brewer, Nancy J. Louwagie</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Elena&nbsp;V&nbsp;Brewer <div class="imageTitle">Professional Development Workshop</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000454/2000454_10670559_1706411799149_2024_01_27_22.14.56--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000454/2000454_10670559_1706411799149_2024_01_27_22.14.56--rgov-800width.png" title="Introduction to Vacuum Technology"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000454/2000454_10670559_1706411799149_2024_01_27_22.14.56--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Introduction to Vacuum Technology"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Introduction to Vacuum Technology Resources: E-Book, Student Laboratory Manual, and Instructor's Guide</div> <div class="imageCredit">David M. Hata, Elena V. Brewer, Nancy J. Louwagie</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Elena&nbsp;V&nbsp;Brewer <div class="imageTitle">Introduction to Vacuum Technology</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000454/2000454_10670559_1706415337978_Picture4--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000454/2000454_10670559_1706415337978_Picture4--rgov-800width.png" title="Examples of Feedback from SMEs, Students, and Faculty"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000454/2000454_10670559_1706415337978_Picture4--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Examples of Feedback from SMEs, Students, and Faculty"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Examples of feedback from subject matter experts, students, and faculty.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Bob Bailey, Outcomes Consulting Services</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Elena&nbsp;V&nbsp;Brewer <div class="imageTitle">Examples of Feedback from SMEs, Students, and Faculty</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000454/2000454_10670559_1706416995740_Picture5--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000454/2000454_10670559_1706416995740_Picture5--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="Workshop Participant Working with Rough Vacuum Trainer"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000454/2000454_10670559_1706416995740_Picture5--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="Workshop Participant Working with Rough Vacuum Trainer"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Professional Development Workshop Participant Working with Rough Vacuum Trainer on a Learning Activity from Student Laboratory Manual</div> <div class="imageCredit">David M. Hata</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Elena&nbsp;V&nbsp;Brewer <div class="imageTitle">Workshop Participant Working with Rough Vacuum Trainer</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000454/2000454_10670559_1706414992788_Picture3--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000454/2000454_10670559_1706414992788_Picture3--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="Professional Development Workshop Seagate Industry Tour"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000454/2000454_10670559_1706414992788_Picture3--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="Professional Development Workshop Seagate Industry Tour"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Professional Development Workshop Participants and Organizers during Seagate Industry Tour</div> <div class="imageCredit">David M. Hata</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Elena&nbsp;V&nbsp;Brewer <div class="imageTitle">Professional Development Workshop Seagate Industry Tour</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Electronic components with their underlying integrated circuits enable the functions and operation of devices that people around the world use every day, such as, computers, smart phones, household appliances, automobiles, medical devices, and many others. Vacuum systems are a critical yet not well-known technology that enable the production of semiconductor devices. Vacuum systems create process conditions that make it possible to manipulate materials at the atomic level. Unplanned downtime of vacuum systems at these businesses can result in millions of dollars in lost revenues. The semiconductor industry and many other types of manufacturing and research organizations rely on qualified vacuum technicians to maintain, troubleshoot, and repair vacuum equipment systems so these systems operate as intended.      Project DUE #2000454 (Developing an E-book and Other Interactive Instructional Materials for Technician Education in Vacuum Technology) was funded by the National Science Foundation from October 2020 to September 2023. SUNY Erie Community College (Williamsville, NY) administered the award and partnered with Normandale Community College (Bloomington, MN), sub-awardee, to create online accessible open educational resources that support instruction of a vacuum technology curriculum. This project addressed an important need to provide off-the-shelf type resources for educators who want to develop a curriculum for instruction in vacuum technology either as a stand-alone program or as part of other educational programs such as semiconductor manufacturing, micro- and nanotechnology and other engineering technologies. Principal Investigator Elena Brewer (SUNY Erie ) and Co-Principal Investigator Nancy Louwagie (Normandale ) coordinated the project work completed by a team consisting of faculty, staff, subject matter experts (SMEs) from various organizations, and other academia/industry partners.    Over the course of the project, the project team developed the free e-book Introduction to Vacuum Technology. The e-book introduces students to the applications of vacuum technology, the different types of components used to create vacuum systems, the important scientific principles that apply to vacuum system operations, basic sequences of vacuum system operation and approaches to troubleshooting rough vacuum systems. This e-book supports various functions intended to enhance the reading and user experience. The enhanced functions incorporated in this e-book include animations, simulations, video demonstrations, an in-line glossary, and interactive quizzes. The e-book is accompanied by a student laboratory manual and instructors guide that showcase 10 sets of learning activities that can be delivered in different modalities. The instructors guide provides a bill of materials to construct a rough vacuum system, system schematics, operational instructions, and video demonstrations for running the hands-on experiments.    The educational resources developed under grant project DUE #2000454 were reviewed by ten subject matter experts from industry and academia. The educational materials developed were pilot-tested in courses by eight faculty members at five different institutions in the states of Minnesota, Pennsylvania and New York. All of the above-mentioned resources are available at no cost from Milne Open Textbook site https://milneopentextbooks.org/introduction-to-vacuum-technology/.       A total of 117 student participants were directly impacted by the curriculum resources developed as project deliverables during pilot testing of the materials from January 2022 through September 2023. Student participants were located in the states of Minnesota, Pennsylvania, and New York. 34% of these students were already employed in the vacuum industry. 89% of students were non-traditional students with 49% of the total student participants identifying as veterans.    This project also provided opportunities for faculty to participate in a professional development workshop that addressed instruction of rough vacuum technology. This workshop was attended by 12 faculty members from 7 different states. The faculty represented programs associated with engineering technology, microelectronics, semiconductor fabrication, physics, and computer science. Faculty participants were introduced to the educational resources developed under this grant. They had opportunities to practice the learning activities using rough vacuum systems.    SUNY Erie and Normandalecontinue to support existing partnerships with vacuum-reliant businesses, research organizations, professional societies and other colleges as well as establish new partnerships. These partnerships are critical to providing a relevant and high-quality education in vacuum technology that supports the nations demand to hire a knowledgeable and qualified workforce to work in semiconductor manufacturing and other vacuum reliant industries.      In Summary:   Project DUE #2000454 had a national impact: open educational resources developed under this project were pilot tested by 117 students enrolled in courses at five higher education institutions located in three different states. This project also had a corresponding impact on twenty faculty members who used these open educational resources to facilitate course delivery and/or attended a professional development workshop. During the e-book development and review phase, ten subject matter experts representing both industry and academia provided feedback on the accuracy, quality, and suitability of the e-book resource for its intended audience.     Project #2000454 continues to have an impact on vacuum technician education by providing open educational resources to support curricula and course delivery for vacuum technology, micro and nanotechnology, semiconductor fabrication, and other engineering technologies programs across the country.     Last Modified: 01/27/2024       Submitted by: ElenaVBrewer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
