<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[New Paradigms of Quantum Criticality]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>450000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Serdar Ogut</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sogut@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924429</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[NONTECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports theoretical research aimed at describing the connection between physical properties of modern quantum materials and the nature of many-particle quantum entanglement. Conventional theories of electron motion in metals and semiconductors usually treat the motion of each electron independently, in an average environment defined by the other electrons. This independent electron picture has been quite successful in many metals and semiconductors. However, in many newly discovered materials, some of significant technological importance, the subtle quantum correlations between the electrons need to be accounted for, even for an understanding of their macroscopic properties. In particular, quantum entanglement leading to “spooky action at a distance” can be present not only between a pair of electrons, but across long distances and involving large numbers of electrons. A class of materials of particular interest in this research are the cuprate high temperature superconductors, all of which are layered materials containing layers with copper and oxygen atoms arranged in a square lattice. There is accumulating experimental evidence for a "quantum critical point" near a mobile electron density where the highest critical temperature for superconductivity is observed. This theoretical research will describe the phase transition in the electron entanglement across this critical point. New methods for describing many particle entanglement have been developed by the PI and others, and also across different fields of physics, including quantum information theory, high energy particle theory, and quantum gravity. These advances will be synthesized in new theoretical frameworks, and subjected to tests by observations on quantum materials.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will also contribute to the development of the scientific workforce by supporting the training of graduate students and postdoctoral associates in topics at the forefront of theoretical condensed matter physics. Furthermore, the PI will continue to pursue an active program of public lectures, interviews, colloquia, and lectures at schools for advanced graduate students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports theoretical research which will examine models of quantum criticality involving gauge theories coupled to finite density matter. While much is known about phase transitions of gauge theories coupled to relativistic matter in 2+1 spacetime dimensions, applications to cuprate criticality require finite density fermionic matter which, in the absence of disorder, has a sharp Fermi surface. The PI and his research team have proposed specific gauge theories for cuprate criticality which satisfy numerous phenomenological constraints imposed by observations. In some mathematical contexts, the combination of the gauge structure and the presence of a Fermi surface leads to effective quantum field theories which are bilocal in time. Currently, little is understood about such bilocal theories in 2+1 dimensions, and unraveling this mystery will be an important focus of this research. Previously, bilocal theories have appeared in models with infinite-range interactions, like the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) models, which have some attractive phenomenological features. Insights gained from the study of SYK models will be applied to the more realistic bilocal field theories appearing in this research. Another focus area of the research will be on the thermal Hall effect: In the most recent experiments, the thermal Hall effect has emerged as a powerful diagnostic probe of quantum phase transitions associated with changes in entanglement structure. The PI and his team will extend theories of the thermal Hall effect to models of the pseudogap phase of the cuprates. In addition, correlated electron superconductivity in twisted graphene bilayers will be studied, with a focus on the quantum interplay of multiple competing orders and superconductivity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will also contribute to the development of the scientific workforce by supporting the training of graduate students and postdoctoral associates in topics at the forefront of theoretical condensed matter physics. Furthermore, the PI will continue to pursue an active program of public lectures, interviews, colloquia, and lectures at schools for advanced graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002850</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Subir</FirstName>
<LastName>Sachdev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Subir Sachdev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sachdev@physics.harvard.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000102524</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385366</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE STE 3</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LN53LCFJFL45</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021385366</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1033 Massachusetts Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Superconductivity is a key modern technology, perhaps most significantly in efforts to develop green fusion energy. This project focused on the underlying quantum physics of high temperature superconductivity in the copper oxide compounds, commonly known as the cuprates, which are employed in the fusion energy effort. We also examined superconductivity in the compounds consisting only of a few layers of carbon atoms: this superconductivity appears at much lower temperature, but should be more amenable to incorporation in nanoscale devices.</p> <p>For the cuprates, we have developed a comprehensive framework for understanding the physics at temperatures above the critical temperature for superconductivity. Our framework is based upon the "ancilla" method introduced by us. We showed that ancilla quantum degrees of freedom ("qubits") allow more expressive wavefunctions and quantum field theories of the physical degrees of freedom in the copper oxide layers. We describe the three distinct regimes found above the critical temperature, the "pseudogap" found at low hole density, the "strange metal" at intermediate hole densities with the highest critical temperature for superconductivity, and the relatively well understood Fermi liquid at high doping density.</p> <p>For the pseudogap regime, the ancillas yield a theory expressed in terms of a specific "spin liquid" state of an insulator. A "spin liquid" is a reasonably well understood quantum state with long-range quantum entanglement, and we have extended this understanding to metallic states. We have successfully compared this theory to photoemission experiments (which eject electrons from the superconductor using light) measuring the energy of the electrons at all possible momenta.</p> <p>For the strange metal, we have combined the ancilla method with insights from the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model (introduced by the PI in 1993) of electrons with complex quantum entanglement. We have shown that presence of impurities are an essential ingredient in the observed properties of the strange metal. A theory of quantum entanglement in the presence of impurities was found to be in agreement with numerous properties of the strange metal, including the celebrated linear-in-temperature resistivity.</p> <p>We have also begun an examination of the onset of superconductivity from these different metallic regimes of the cuprates.</p> <p>For the carbon layer compounds (in particular "twisted bilayer graphene"), we proposed a symmetry classification of superconducting states which accounts for the complexity of the underlying band structure. We have found that one particular state is in excellent accord with numerous microsopic observations, and also with theoretically determined electron band structure.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/25/2023<br> Modified by: Subir&nbsp;Sachdev</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Superconductivity is a key modern technology, perhaps most significantly in efforts to develop green fusion energy. This project focused on the underlying quantum physics of high temperature superconductivity in the copper oxide compounds, commonly known as the cuprates, which are employed in the fusion energy effort. We also examined superconductivity in the compounds consisting only of a few layers of carbon atoms: this superconductivity appears at much lower temperature, but should be more amenable to incorporation in nanoscale devices.   For the cuprates, we have developed a comprehensive framework for understanding the physics at temperatures above the critical temperature for superconductivity. Our framework is based upon the "ancilla" method introduced by us. We showed that ancilla quantum degrees of freedom ("qubits") allow more expressive wavefunctions and quantum field theories of the physical degrees of freedom in the copper oxide layers. We describe the three distinct regimes found above the critical temperature, the "pseudogap" found at low hole density, the "strange metal" at intermediate hole densities with the highest critical temperature for superconductivity, and the relatively well understood Fermi liquid at high doping density.   For the pseudogap regime, the ancillas yield a theory expressed in terms of a specific "spin liquid" state of an insulator. A "spin liquid" is a reasonably well understood quantum state with long-range quantum entanglement, and we have extended this understanding to metallic states. We have successfully compared this theory to photoemission experiments (which eject electrons from the superconductor using light) measuring the energy of the electrons at all possible momenta.   For the strange metal, we have combined the ancilla method with insights from the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model (introduced by the PI in 1993) of electrons with complex quantum entanglement. We have shown that presence of impurities are an essential ingredient in the observed properties of the strange metal. A theory of quantum entanglement in the presence of impurities was found to be in agreement with numerous properties of the strange metal, including the celebrated linear-in-temperature resistivity.   We have also begun an examination of the onset of superconductivity from these different metallic regimes of the cuprates.   For the carbon layer compounds (in particular "twisted bilayer graphene"), we proposed a symmetry classification of superconducting states which accounts for the complexity of the underlying band structure. We have found that one particular state is in excellent accord with numerous microsopic observations, and also with theoretically determined electron band structure.        Last Modified: 12/25/2023       Submitted by: SubirSachdev]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
