<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[The 2020 MagIC Workshop: Rock and Paleomagnetism through Time and Space; March 2020; La Jolla, CA]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>33700.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>40440</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Raleigh Martin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ramartin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927199</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is for partial support to hold a 3-day open community workshop from March 16-18, 2020 at Scripps Institution of Oceanography.  The theme is "Rock and Paleomagnetism through Time and Space". The first two days of the workshop will be focused on science combined with dissemination of essential information about MagIC and paleomagnetic data. The third day of the workshop will include hands-on sessions for uploading data; accessing, manipulating and visualizing the data from both new and existing data sets; for data model discussions; and for brainstorming on new directions.  It will bring together scientists from various backgrounds, perspectives and subdisciplines using paleomagnetic databases to solve science problems across Earth sciences. The program and this support will foster the participation of young scientists, such as post docs and graduate students, and there is an outreach plan that aims to broaden participation. The meeting organizers have articulated a code of conduct for the meeting. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop has two overarching goals. First is to update the community about improvements, modifications, and new resources available for users of the MagIC paleomagnetic database. These include streamlined approaches to uploading data, discovering data contributed by others, using online tools for visualization and analysis, and progress in implementing APIs (application program interfaces).  The organizers also plan to gather feedback for enhancements to the MagIC database and for improving the interoperability of MagIC with other databases. The second goal is to engage a multi-disciplinary group of scientists in the discussion of scientific questions that require magnetic data to solve problems across fields. Four themes will be allocated a half day each, and are intimately related to MagIC's core activities, as well as linking to other areas where researchers have interests in interoperable data discovery. The research foci are "(1) Paleomagnetism and Improving the Geological Timescale; (2) Tectonic Applications of Paleomagnetism;(3) Variations of the Magnetic Field Through Earth's History; (4) Rock and Paleomagnetic Methods &amp; Instrumentation."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/17/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2003104</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Constable</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Catherine Constable</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cconstable@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000462429</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920931500</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8622 DISCOVERY WAY # 116</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QJ8HMDK7MRM3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>QJ8HMDK7MRM3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930225</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Institute of Geophysics & Planet]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1572</Code>
<Text>Tectonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7255</Code>
<Text>GEOINFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002324DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~33700</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2023~6740</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Magnetics Information Consortium (http://earthref.org/MAGIC) established more than twenty years ago is an online facility developed under three collaborative NSF proposals since 2003 and currently is in its fifth grant cycle sponsored by EAR Geoinformatics. The original goal of this project was to hold an open workshop titled, The 2020 MagIC Workshop: Rock and Paleomagnetism Magnetism through Time and Space, at Scripps Institution of Oceanography in March 2020.&nbsp; We planned to update the paleomagnetic community about improvements, modifications, and new resources available for users of the MagIC database including streamlined approaches to uploading data, discovering data contributed by others, using online tools for visualization and analysis, and progress in implementing APIs. We would also solicit feedback for providing further improvements and interoperability with other database efforts. We also intended to engage a broad group of researchers in the discussion of major scientific questions under several themes related to the workshop title.<br /><br />This workshop was repeatedly delayed due to the impacts of COVID-19. We were finally able to achieve ou goals, holding our in-person workshop under the udpated title&nbsp; "Magnetism and Earth History: Field Evolution, Environmental Change and Paleogeography" at Scripps Institution of Oceanography from February 28 - March 2, 2023.&nbsp; Around 60 participants from 9 countries across Europe, China, S. America, and USA took part, including more than 9 posters and 6 talks given by very early career (&lt;2 years post degree) attendees. Three half day oral sessions comprising 13 invited talks were complemented by a vibrant poster session covering diverse topics for a total of 32 formal abstracts.&nbsp; Working lunches provided opportunities for early career discussions (extended to include all postdocs, pre-tenure, or less than 8 years post PhD) and an extension of the poster session on the second day.<br /><br />Keynote talks highlighted cutting edge research topics, including attempts to identify the onset and rate of&nbsp; formation of Earth's inner core reflected in variations in ancient geomagnetic field strength, the influence of changing core-mantle boundary conditions on numerical dynamo simulations, new results in lunar paleomagnetism, and improving prospects for magnetic imaging using micrometer-scale imaging with the quantum diamond microscope on both terrestrial and extraterrestrial materials. Presentations on the Surface Environment&nbsp; included detailed studies of magnetic dissolution and&nbsp; formation of the mineral greigite in sediments , and of climate and environmental change recorded in European loess.&nbsp; A review of progress in understanding speleothem formation and the nature of their paleomagnetic records and how to image them with new SQUID microscopy were also a strong focus in this session. Our third major science session dealt with Paleogeography. Two talks highlighted great improvements in plate tectonic reconstructions enabled by new compilations and access to estimates of site level uncertainties in pole contributions combined with suitable propagation into the pole results. Additional presentations focused on bringing a broader interpretation to the integration of greater India with Asia, and new perspectives on tracking Rodinia across the Mesoproterozoic to Neoproterozoic geological boundary.<br /><br />The morning of day 2 featured presentations on MagIC as a Resource for the Community, highlighting new members and efforts by the MagIC team to develop websites dedicated to the specific subareas of paleomagnetic poles and rock magnetism, and followed by breakout discussions to solicit community input on future directions in these areas and for software developments. Day 3 was dedicated to hands-on tutorials about using online tools and making contributions to MagIC using both GUIs and Jupyter notebooks. This was a highly successful interactive session with about 40 participants, providing a welcome opportunity for users to experiment with multiple features and tools available within MagIC. Direct feedback to the MagIC team about ongoing developments in measurements and methods described at the meeting is enabling them to set future priorities for development.<br /><br />&nbsp;The MagIC workshop volume with complete program and abstracts can be found on the work shop website. <br />https://earthref.org/events/MagIC/2023/2023MagICVolume.pdf<br />https://earthref.org/events/MagIC/2023/<br /><br />Oral presentations were recorded and have been made available on MagIC&rsquo;s Youtube channel.<br />https://www.youtube.com/@magneticsinformationconsor5873/videos</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 01/04/2024<br> Modified by: Catherine&nbsp;Constable</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The Magnetics Information Consortium (http://earthref.org/MAGIC) established more than twenty years ago is an online facility developed under three collaborative NSF proposals since 2003 and currently is in its fifth grant cycle sponsored by EAR Geoinformatics. The original goal of this project was to hold an open workshop titled, The 2020 MagIC Workshop: Rock and Paleomagnetism Magnetism through Time and Space, at Scripps Institution of Oceanography in March 2020. We planned to update the paleomagnetic community about improvements, modifications, and new resources available for users of the MagIC database including streamlined approaches to uploading data, discovering data contributed by others, using online tools for visualization and analysis, and progress in implementing APIs. We would also solicit feedback for providing further improvements and interoperability with other database efforts. We also intended to engage a broad group of researchers in the discussion of major scientific questions under several themes related to the workshop title.  This workshop was repeatedly delayed due to the impacts of COVID-19. We were finally able to achieve ou goals, holding our in-person workshop under the udpated title "Magnetism and Earth History: Field Evolution, Environmental Change and Paleogeography" at Scripps Institution of Oceanography from February 28 - March 2, 2023. Around 60 participants from 9 countries across Europe, China, S. America, and USA took part, including more than 9 posters and 6 talks given by very early career ( Keynote talks highlighted cutting edge research topics, including attempts to identify the onset and rate of formation of Earth's inner core reflected in variations in ancient geomagnetic field strength, the influence of changing core-mantle boundary conditions on numerical dynamo simulations, new results in lunar paleomagnetism, and improving prospects for magnetic imaging using micrometer-scale imaging with the quantum diamond microscope on both terrestrial and extraterrestrial materials. Presentations on the Surface Environment included detailed studies of magnetic dissolution and formation of the mineral greigite in sediments , and of climate and environmental change recorded in European loess. A review of progress in understanding speleothem formation and the nature of their paleomagnetic records and how to image them with new SQUID microscopy were also a strong focus in this session. Our third major science session dealt with Paleogeography. Two talks highlighted great improvements in plate tectonic reconstructions enabled by new compilations and access to estimates of site level uncertainties in pole contributions combined with suitable propagation into the pole results. Additional presentations focused on bringing a broader interpretation to the integration of greater India with Asia, and new perspectives on tracking Rodinia across the Mesoproterozoic to Neoproterozoic geological boundary.  The morning of day 2 featured presentations on MagIC as a Resource for the Community, highlighting new members and efforts by the MagIC team to develop websites dedicated to the specific subareas of paleomagnetic poles and rock magnetism, and followed by breakout discussions to solicit community input on future directions in these areas and for software developments. Day 3 was dedicated to hands-on tutorials about using online tools and making contributions to MagIC using both GUIs and Jupyter notebooks. This was a highly successful interactive session with about 40 participants, providing a welcome opportunity for users to experiment with multiple features and tools available within MagIC. Direct feedback to the MagIC team about ongoing developments in measurements and methods described at the meeting is enabling them to set future priorities for development.  The MagIC workshop volume with complete program and abstracts can be found on the work shop website.  https://earthref.org/events/MagIC/2023/2023MagICVolume.pdf https://earthref.org/events/MagIC/2023/  Oral presentations were recorded and have been made available on MagICs Youtube channel. https://www.youtube.com/@magneticsinformationconsor5873/videos     Last Modified: 01/04/2024       Submitted by: CatherineConstable]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
