<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[A Vision of Our Own: Developing a Red Lake Nation College Vision and Strategic Plan for Increased STEM Capacity and Student Success]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149985.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149985</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jody Chase</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lchase@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925173</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[A goal of the Tribal Colleges and Universities Program (TCUP) is to increase the science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) instructional and research capacities of specific institutions of higher education that serve the Nation's indigenous students. Expanding the research capacity at these institutions expands the opportunities for students to pursue challenging, rewarding careers in STEM fields, provides for research studies in areas that may be locally relevant, and encourages a faculty community to look beyond the traditional classroom for intellectual and professional growth. This project aligns directly with that goal, allowing the institution's faculty and administrators to design and develop a comprehensive plan for improving and expanding STEM instruction. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Red Lake Nation College (RLNC) serves the Red Lake Reservation in Minnesota.  The project leaders will conduct deliberate assessment and exploration of needs, capacity, interests, and opportunities in the region in order to develop its own STEM vision, goals, and a strategic plan. The project will entail 3 phases: Phase 1 will consist of information gathering about RLNC, community, and regional employer capacity, needs, and interests. Phase 2 will consist of exploring TCU STEM programming success and possible collaborations with various institutions in the region and around the country. Phase 3 will consist of compiling and analyzing the data gathered in phases 1 and 2 and then developing an RLNC STEM vision, goals, and strategic plan.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011669</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mandy</FirstName>
<LastName>Schram</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mandy Schram</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mandy.schram@rlnc.education]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816490</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wendy</FirstName>
<LastName>Greenberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wendy A Greenberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wendy.greenberg@rlnc.education]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000784643</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Red Lake Nation College</Name>
<CityName>REDLAKE</CityName>
<ZipCode>56671</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2186791030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>15480 MIGIZI DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NE6EMW8KAZN6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RED LAKE NATION COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>J7LVQK71CA14</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Red Lake Nation College]]></Name>
<CityName>Red Lake</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>566710576</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[15480 Migizi Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1744</Code>
<Text>Tribal College &amp; Univers Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~149985</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The purpose of this project was to do deliberate assessment and exploration of needs, capacity, interests, and opportunities in our region in order to develop our own Red Lake Nation College STEM vision, goals, and a strategic plan. The project consisted information gathering about RLNC students and faculty, community, and regional employer capacity, needs, and interests. We also explored STEM programming successes and possible collaborations with various institutions in the region and around the country. Faculty and staff attended virtual and in person conferences. They also visited other Tribal Colleges to confer with STEM faculty about programming.</p> <p>Our employer survey indicated that many regional employers are interested in working with RLNC, our students, and our alumni. Surveys and listening sessions with RLNC faculty about their interests and concerns moving forward with STEM curriculum indicate that they are interested in course and program development as well as some research, but need time and resources. Student interests and needs were assessed through course evaluations. We compiled and analyzed the data gathered and are developing an RLNC STEM goals, strategic plan, and working towards expanding STEM programming as well as academic and career pathways at RLNC.&nbsp;</p> <p>As we work towards developing long term plans and programs, we have begun implementing short term changes. We responded to student and faculty requests to add student and alumni teaching assistants to specific math, biology, and English courses. Collaborations established with the UMN-Twin Cities for research and with Bemidji State University STEM and Math departments for transfer pathways. And, RLNC submitted its first NSF TCUP ICE-TI proposal titled, &ldquo;ICE-TI: A Decolonized Approach to an AAS in Social and Behavioral Sciences.&rdquo;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit</p> <p>The intellectual merit of this project comes from the deliberate, careful surveys and focus groups to compile and evaluate needs and interests of RLNC students, faculty, surrounding community members, and regional employers. It also involved visiting and meeting with potential collaborators and TCUs around the country with successful STEM programs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impacts</p> <p>Broader impacts include taking the results of this planning project and using them as the basis of a proposal for an Instructional Capacity Excellence at TCUP Institutions (ICE-TI) grant submitted in April 2023.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 01/29/2024<br> Modified by: Wendy&nbsp;A&nbsp;Greenberg</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The purpose of this project was to do deliberate assessment and exploration of needs, capacity, interests, and opportunities in our region in order to develop our own Red Lake Nation College STEM vision, goals, and a strategic plan. The project consisted information gathering about RLNC students and faculty, community, and regional employer capacity, needs, and interests. We also explored STEM programming successes and possible collaborations with various institutions in the region and around the country. Faculty and staff attended virtual and in person conferences. They also visited other Tribal Colleges to confer with STEM faculty about programming.   Our employer survey indicated that many regional employers are interested in working with RLNC, our students, and our alumni. Surveys and listening sessions with RLNC faculty about their interests and concerns moving forward with STEM curriculum indicate that they are interested in course and program development as well as some research, but need time and resources. Student interests and needs were assessed through course evaluations. We compiled and analyzed the data gathered and are developing an RLNC STEM goals, strategic plan, and working towards expanding STEM programming as well as academic and career pathways at RLNC.   As we work towards developing long term plans and programs, we have begun implementing short term changes. We responded to student and faculty requests to add student and alumni teaching assistants to specific math, biology, and English courses. Collaborations established with the UMN-Twin Cities for research and with Bemidji State University STEM and Math departments for transfer pathways. And, RLNC submitted its first NSF TCUP ICE-TI proposal titled, ICE-TI: A Decolonized Approach to an AAS in Social and Behavioral Sciences.      Intellectual Merit   The intellectual merit of this project comes from the deliberate, careful surveys and focus groups to compile and evaluate needs and interests of RLNC students, faculty, surrounding community members, and regional employers. It also involved visiting and meeting with potential collaborators and TCUs around the country with successful STEM programs.      Broader Impacts   Broader impacts include taking the results of this planning project and using them as the basis of a proposal for an Instructional Capacity Excellence at TCUP Institutions (ICE-TI) grant submitted in April 2023.     Last Modified: 01/29/2024       Submitted by: WendyAGreenberg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
