<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Broadening Participation Research Project: Understanding the role of culture in an intervention to increase the persistence of African American STEM students]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>349991.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>349991</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tori Rhoulac Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tosmith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922315</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The proposed project will examine the impact of contextual factors, career planning skills, confidence in career decision, mindset, social class, and social capital on career development of STEM students. Researchers will investigate the tole of these factors on African American STEM student persistence. As a translational research study, the project grounds theory in practice and demonstrates the impact of using a revised intervention focused on developing the career management skills of African American undergraduate STEM students. The researchers will produce evidence of an effective method for increasing the retention of minority STEM students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Grounded in Social Cognitive Career Theory (SCCT), the project follows a mixed methods design to answer three research questions: (1) How do SCCT-defined contextual factors such as social capital and social class affect the change in participants’ career planning abilities and intentions to obtain a graduate degree in STEM? (2) How does an increase in institutional resources designed to support STEM majors impact the efficacy of the intervention? and (3) What is the long-term impact of the intervention on STEM students who participated in the prior career management interventions?  Researchers will obtain quantitative and qualitative information on the impact of the intervention and support model building related to career development of minority students. The project is expected to fill a gap in the vocational psychology and STEM persistence literature, i.e., the integration of theory related to career development with underrepresented minorities with research on effective career intervention, growth mindset, and academic persistence for African American STEM students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is funded by the Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program, broadening participation in STEM education research track.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011931</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marie</FirstName>
<LastName>Hammond</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marie S Hammond</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mhammond1@tnstate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000331279</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elaine</FirstName>
<LastName>Martin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elaine Martin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[emartin@tnstate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000565426</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Broyles</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas Broyles</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tbroyle1@tnstate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000708286</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tennessee State University</Name>
<CityName>NASHVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>372091500</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6159637631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3500 JOHN A MERRITT BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>N63ZMY7UETA3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TENNESSEE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tennessee State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372091561</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3500 John A. Merritt Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~349991</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Summary.&nbsp; The primary goal of this project was to explore the long-term impact of interventions designed to increase the persistence of African American undergraduate students in STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering, &amp; Mathematics).&nbsp; Grounded in Social Cognitive Career Theory (SCCT), the project gathered data to explore SCCT-defined contextual factors such as social capital and social class. In addition, the project proposed to explore the impact of recent increases in programmatic activities directed at supporting STEM students. This project builds on previous awards to this research team (NSF awards #1238778 &amp; #1623145).</p> <p>The project proposed a quantitative design to gather data from STEM students actively engaged in their studies during the previous grant periods. Participants were invited to complete a set of measures that inquired about their career planning skills, experiences while enrolled in STEM courses, as well as SCCT-defined contextual factors. The appearance of COVID-19 in the U.S.A. and related sequestration procedures implemented beginning mid-March 2020 prevented us from engaging in the face-to-face participant recruitment activities. In response we adapted both our operating procedures (move to online meetings) and the data collection procedures. The adapted data collection procedures included utilizing more frequent email reminders as well as extending the data collection through the end of the grant period. The sequestration (2020-2022/3) impacted the entire grant period, including dissemination efforts, as conferences were cancelled or moved to a more limited, online format. As a result, dissemination efforts were re-focused to preparing manuscripts for publication.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit. This project builds on and extends the findings from previous studies which have been based in Social Cognitive Career Theory. Data gathered will be used to demonstrate long-term impact of interventions implemented during previous awards. We published a book chapter and three journal articles during the course of this grant.</p> <p>Broader Impacts. At least one department at the University has implemented the intervention as a standard part of their undergraduate training program. Given the success previously reported, the research team is moving forward with developing training materials to train STEM faculty to implement the intervention. Furthermore, in our first 10 years as a research project, we have demonstrated a significant record of mentoring and support for the development of Co-PIs (4 of 11 women; 7 of 11 Black, 1 of 11 Asian Indian), research assistants (20 of 29 women, 1 of 29 LGBTQ+; 23 of 29 Black; 28 of 29 doctoral-level), and research team volunteers (2 of 4 women; 2 of 4 Black, 1 of 4 Latine; 1 of 4 undergraduate level). All individuals received mentoring &amp; training in grant writing, grant management, data analysis &amp; management, intervention implementation, as well as professional skills, such as planning, time management, conflict resolution, etc. Training is provided by the PI, conference attendance, and/or National Center for Faculty Diversity &amp; Development.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/08/2023<br> Modified by: Marie&nbsp;S&nbsp;Hammond</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Summary. The primary goal of this project was to explore the long-term impact of interventions designed to increase the persistence of African American undergraduate students in STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering, & Mathematics). Grounded in Social Cognitive Career Theory (SCCT), the project gathered data to explore SCCT-defined contextual factors such as social capital and social class. In addition, the project proposed to explore the impact of recent increases in programmatic activities directed at supporting STEM students. This project builds on previous awards to this research team (NSF awards #1238778 & #1623145).   The project proposed a quantitative design to gather data from STEM students actively engaged in their studies during the previous grant periods. Participants were invited to complete a set of measures that inquired about their career planning skills, experiences while enrolled in STEM courses, as well as SCCT-defined contextual factors. The appearance of COVID-19 in the U.S.A. and related sequestration procedures implemented beginning mid-March 2020 prevented us from engaging in the face-to-face participant recruitment activities. In response we adapted both our operating procedures (move to online meetings) and the data collection procedures. The adapted data collection procedures included utilizing more frequent email reminders as well as extending the data collection through the end of the grant period. The sequestration (2020-2022/3) impacted the entire grant period, including dissemination efforts, as conferences were cancelled or moved to a more limited, online format. As a result, dissemination efforts were re-focused to preparing manuscripts for publication.   Intellectual Merit. This project builds on and extends the findings from previous studies which have been based in Social Cognitive Career Theory. Data gathered will be used to demonstrate long-term impact of interventions implemented during previous awards. We published a book chapter and three journal articles during the course of this grant.   Broader Impacts. At least one department at the University has implemented the intervention as a standard part of their undergraduate training program. Given the success previously reported, the research team is moving forward with developing training materials to train STEM faculty to implement the intervention. Furthermore, in our first 10 years as a research project, we have demonstrated a significant record of mentoring and support for the development of Co-PIs (4 of 11 women; 7 of 11 Black, 1 of 11 Asian Indian), research assistants (20 of 29 women, 1 of 29 LGBTQ+; 23 of 29 Black; 28 of 29 doctoral-level), and research team volunteers (2 of 4 women; 2 of 4 Black, 1 of 4 Latine; 1 of 4 undergraduate level). All individuals received mentoring & training in grant writing, grant management, data analysis & management, intervention implementation, as well as professional skills, such as planning, time management, conflict resolution, etc. Training is provided by the PI, conference attendance, and/or National Center for Faculty Diversity & Development.        Last Modified: 11/08/2023       Submitted by: MarieSHammond]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
