<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Targeted Infusion Project: Enhancement of Jackson State University Course-based Undergraduate Research Experience (JSU-CURE) Program in the Biological Sciences]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399958.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>399958</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carleitta Paige-Anderson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cpaigean@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922816</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP) through Targeted Infusion Projects supports the development, implementation, and study of evidence-based innovative models and approaches for improving the preparation and success of HBCU undergraduate students so that they may pursue STEM graduate programs and/or careers. This project at Jackson State University will take place in the Biology Department and course-based research will be used to increase student comprehension of foundational material. The project is expected to enhance the undergraduate STEM education for biology majors and better prepare them for the rigors and challenges of graduate school programs and STEM employment.    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will enable Jackson State University to transform traditionally taught lectures and labs into courses that actively engage students in authentic scientific inquiry through inquiry-based instruction. Course-based Undergraduate Research Experiences (CURES) will be utilized to enhance student research competency, improve the Biology curriculum, stimulate student interest in discovery and prepare students for entry into graduate school or the STEM workforce. The JSU-CURE program is expected to impact at least 500 undergraduate students. Implementation of the program will result in a significant increase of underrepresented minority students entering post-graduate education and careers in the STEM arena. The program will also establish a cohort of JSU-CURE scholars who will employ CURE knowledge to teach the next generation of STEM middle school and high school students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011511</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gloria</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gloria S Miller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gloria.s.miller@jsums.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000742634</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Turner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy Turner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[timothy.turner@jsums.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000704468</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Graham</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barbara Graham</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[barbara.e.graham@jsums.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000618562</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>LaDonnya</FirstName>
<LastName>Drummond</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>LaDonnya Drummond</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ladonnya.s.drummond@jsums.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000786767</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacqueline</FirstName>
<LastName>Stevens</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jacqueline J Stevens</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jacqueline.j.stevens@jsums.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000786773</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Jackson State University]]></Name>
<CityName>JACKSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>392170002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6019792008</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 J R LYNCH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MS02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>WFVHMSF6BU45</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JACKSON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Jackson State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>392170001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MS02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~399958</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>PROJECT OUTCOMES REPORT</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The Department of Biology comprises the largest number of majors at Jackson State University (JSU), a historically Black college/university located in Jackson, Mississippi. The science foundation of its biology majors is formed and developed through their entry-level General Biology I and General Botany courses. These respective freshman and sophomore level courses are meant to provide the strong foundation needed to adequately prepare biology majors to enroll in more advanced courses in biology. However, there were academic challenges surrounding the traditional way these classes were taught; some specific to classes in the biological sciences and others related to the large number of sections offered to diversely educated students.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Two major challenges were: 1) The current format did not foster student-centered, inquiry-based, independent investigation using the existing technology; and 2) Faculty were not able to teach complex topics effectively without the integration of modern technology. To provide more of our students the long-term benefits of a comprehensive learning experience, the Department of Biology submitted the Targeted Infusion Project: <em>Enhancement of Jackson State University Course-based Undergraduate Research Experience (JSU-CURE) Program in the Biological Sciences.</em></p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; We set out to transform traditionally taught lectures and labs into courses that actively engaged students in authentic scientific inquiry through inquiry-based instruction. The program was instrumental in creating a&nbsp; supportive and stimulating learning community that exposed our students to hands-on research and thus hypothetically helped to increase their academic confidence and motivation to venture further in biology and other STEM disciplines (data not available). The inclusive goal of JSU-CURE was to increase the number of biology baccalaureates who would enroll in graduate programs and/or enter the STEM workforce.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; JSU-CURE achieved its goal through the implementation of the following objectives: 1) Enhancing the biology curriculum through the integration of CUREs into entry-level biology laboratory courses. 2) Augmenting the biology curriculum with the introduction of a new course in Bioinformatics. 3) Increasing students' research competency in the biological sciences through &nbsp;faculty-mentored research. 4) Upgrading teaching and research infrastructure to support the curriculum redesign for student hands-on research experiences. 5) Establishing a cohort of JSU-CURE Scholars that employed the knowledge obtained in CURE classrooms to teach the next generation of STEM elementary and middle school students.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In early preparations to achieve our objectives it was necessary that &nbsp;JSU Biology faculty commit to implementing Course-based Undergraduate Research opportunities in their freshmen and sophomore biology courses, specifically General Biology&nbsp; Lecture and Laboratory (BIO 111) and General Botany Lecture and Laboratory (BIO 119).&nbsp; To accomplish this endeavor, JSU hosted a CURE Institute Spring 2019. The institute was designed to familiarize faculty about CUREs so that they would be prepared to implement plans, instructional materials, and assessment tools for integrating a science research project into their science laboratory course. The overarching goal of the CURE Institute was to build faculty capacity to design and implement CUREs based on research on learning in general and UG research experiences in particular. The training provided by the JSU-CURE Institute supported the JSU-Targeted Infusion Project (TIP) and was instrumental in building a cohesive network of CURE practices among biology faculty.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Together with faculty commitment and funding, the Biology Department was able to upgrade teaching and research infrastructure by providing research supplies and materials to research faculty who hosted CURE UG students.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 1) We enhanced our biology curriculum through the integration of CUREs into entry-level biology laboratory courses. Sections of General Biology 111 lecture were redesigned around MasteringBiology, (an online program provided by Pearson Education), using inquiry-based instructional modules that focused on problem posing, problem solving, and peer collaboration.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 2) The Bioinformatics course was approved by the third year and a total of 20 students enrolled during the first semester the course was offered.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 3) Students' research laboratory competency was severely interrupted by the Covid-19 campus shut-down and later by the water infrastructure problems.&nbsp; However, we successfully placed two students in research laboratories and were able to provide support for most of the Spring 2022, thru Fall 2022 semesters.&nbsp; These two students gave oral presentations to JSU faculty and staff and also traveled to two scientific meetings for presentations.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 4) &nbsp;We also provided provisions to research infrastructure to support student &nbsp;research laboratory research experiences.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 5) Because students were largely restricted to home studies during the COVID epidemic, 122 of our JSU-CURE Scholars were in place to provide much needed STEM tutoring and/or mentoring&nbsp; to approximately five elementary and middle schools located in and around the tri-county area. These scholars were able to employ the knowledge obtained in CURE classrooms to teach utilizing current social media venues.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Overall, JSU-CURE impacted a total of 682 students as a result of enhancing our curriculum through the integration of CUREs into entry-level biology courses.&nbsp; We were also able to reach 233 non-biology majors who were enrolled in Introductory Biology.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/06/2023<br> Modified by: Ladonnya&nbsp;Drummond</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  PROJECT OUTCOMES REPORT      The Department of Biology comprises the largest number of majors at Jackson State University (JSU), a historically Black college/university located in Jackson, Mississippi. The science foundation of its biology majors is formed and developed through their entry-level General Biology I and General Botany courses. These respective freshman and sophomore level courses are meant to provide the strong foundation needed to adequately prepare biology majors to enroll in more advanced courses in biology. However, there were academic challenges surrounding the traditional way these classes were taught; some specific to classes in the biological sciences and others related to the large number of sections offered to diversely educated students.    Two major challenges were: 1) The current format did not foster student-centered, inquiry-based, independent investigation using the existing technology; and 2) Faculty were not able to teach complex topics effectively without the integration of modern technology. To provide more of our students the long-term benefits of a comprehensive learning experience, the Department of Biology submitted the Targeted Infusion Project: Enhancement of Jackson State University Course-based Undergraduate Research Experience (JSU-CURE) Program in the Biological Sciences.    We set out to transform traditionally taught lectures and labs into courses that actively engaged students in authentic scientific inquiry through inquiry-based instruction. The program was instrumental in creating a supportive and stimulating learning community that exposed our students to hands-on research and thus hypothetically helped to increase their academic confidence and motivation to venture further in biology and other STEM disciplines (data not available). The inclusive goal of JSU-CURE was to increase the number of biology baccalaureates who would enroll in graduate programs and/or enter the STEM workforce.    JSU-CURE achieved its goal through the implementation of the following objectives: 1) Enhancing the biology curriculum through the integration of CUREs into entry-level biology laboratory courses. 2) Augmenting the biology curriculum with the introduction of a new course in Bioinformatics. 3) Increasing students' research competency in the biological sciences through faculty-mentored research. 4) Upgrading teaching and research infrastructure to support the curriculum redesign for student hands-on research experiences. 5) Establishing a cohort of JSU-CURE Scholars that employed the knowledge obtained in CURE classrooms to teach the next generation of STEM elementary and middle school students.     In early preparations to achieve our objectives it was necessary that JSU Biology faculty commit to implementing Course-based Undergraduate Research opportunities in their freshmen and sophomore biology courses, specifically General Biology Lecture and Laboratory (BIO 111) and General Botany Lecture and Laboratory (BIO 119). To accomplish this endeavor, JSU hosted a CURE Institute Spring 2019. The institute was designed to familiarize faculty about CUREs so that they would be prepared to implement plans, instructional materials, and assessment tools for integrating a science research project into their science laboratory course. The overarching goal of the CURE Institute was to build faculty capacity to design and implement CUREs based on research on learning in general and UG research experiences in particular. The training provided by the JSU-CURE Institute supported the JSU-Targeted Infusion Project (TIP) and was instrumental in building a cohesive network of CURE practices among biology faculty.    Together with faculty commitment and funding, the Biology Department was able to upgrade teaching and research infrastructure by providing research supplies and materials to research faculty who hosted CURE UG students.    1) We enhanced our biology curriculum through the integration of CUREs into entry-level biology laboratory courses. Sections of General Biology 111 lecture were redesigned around MasteringBiology, (an online program provided by Pearson Education), using inquiry-based instructional modules that focused on problem posing, problem solving, and peer collaboration.    2) The Bioinformatics course was approved by the third year and a total of 20 students enrolled during the first semester the course was offered.    3) Students' research laboratory competency was severely interrupted by the Covid-19 campus shut-down and later by the water infrastructure problems. However, we successfully placed two students in research laboratories and were able to provide support for most of the Spring 2022, thru Fall 2022 semesters. These two students gave oral presentations to JSU faculty and staff and also traveled to two scientific meetings for presentations.    4) We also provided provisions to research infrastructure to support student research laboratory research experiences.    5) Because students were largely restricted to home studies during the COVID epidemic, 122 of our JSU-CURE Scholars were in place to provide much needed STEM tutoring and/or mentoring to approximately five elementary and middle schools located in and around the tri-county area. These scholars were able to employ the knowledge obtained in CURE classrooms to teach utilizing current social media venues.    Overall, JSU-CURE impacted a total of 682 students as a result of enhancing our curriculum through the integration of CUREs into entry-level biology courses. We were also able to reach 233 non-biology majors who were enrolled in Introductory Biology.           Last Modified: 11/06/2023       Submitted by: LadonnyaDrummond]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
