<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[PFI-TT: Manipulating Mycorrhizal Fungi: Plant Symbionts in Organic Agriculture]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Debora Rodrigues</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Partnerships for Innovation - Technology Translation (PFI-TT) project will support the development of a woman-owned small business and the training of underrepresented students learning farming technologies. This project will identify plant symbionts that improve crop productivity, nutrition, and secondary metabolite production in organic agriculture and will directly influence contemporary farming practices. In preliminary trials, the team isolated  mycorrhizal fungi;  These plant root symbionts have been shown to improve crop yield by as much as 30%. This project will result in products for organic or conventional farmers to increase crop yield, either in biomass, nutritional value, or the concentration of marketable phytomedicinal compounds in their crop species.  The technology may improve the profit margins of organic and conventional farmers in the US and beyond. Beyond the commercial potential, this team will also contribute to scientific understanding of how plant symbionts such as mycorrhizal fungi influence plant secondary metabolite production and plant nutrient composition. These mycorrhizal fungal isolates could help ease soil stress and nutrient loss that occur in long-term organic agricultural soils across the world, improving the global agricultural environments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will assess the effect of mycorrhizal fungi on organic crop production. Maintaining productive soils in organic agriculture is challenging, as few options are available for farmers to improve the soil conditions of their field. This difficulty can lead to lower crop productivity and even failed crop establishment. Mycorrhizal fungi are soil organisms that symbiotically associate with plants to deliver difficult-to-acquire soil nutrients to plant hosts. In preliminary trials, the team has identified several highly beneficial mycorrhizal fungi that can be cultured in a laboratory setting to be applied in organic agriculture. This research will use field and greenhouse assays to assess more than 40 crop varieties to identify crops that demonstrate the strongest growth and nutritional improvement after inoculation with unique mycorrhizal isolates compared to commercially available mycorrhizal products. Mycorrhizal mediated abiotic stress resistance will be assessed by testing how mycorrhizal applications compare to traditional organic fertilizer application in situ with a local organic farm. This project will also help farmers understand how specific mycorrhizae can alter the concentration of plant secondary metabolites that are marketed for their medicinal, nutritional, or other dietary value for plants with large economic impact.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/21/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016549</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Koziol</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth Koziol</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lizkoziol@ku.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000817690</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/21/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Bever</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James D Bever</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jbever@ku.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000308751</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
<CityName>LAWRENCE</CityName>
<ZipCode>660457552</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KS01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SSUJB3GSH8A5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF KANSAS CENTER FOR RESEARCH INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>SSUJB3GSH8A5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Kansas Center for Research, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Lawrence</CityName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2385 Irving Hill Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KS01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PFI-Partnrships for Innovation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1491</Code>
<Text>BIOTECH, BIOCHEM &amp; BIOMASS ENG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~49999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Goals:</strong></p> <p>The project led by PIs Liz Koziol and James D. Bever aims to explore unique mycorrhizal isolates for boosting organic crop production. Mycorrhizal fungi enhance plant growth and nutrient absorption. The study systematically examines the impact of mycorrhizal fungi on organic crop growth, using field and greenhouse tests. This advances our understanding of their role in improving plant growth, nutrition, and secondary metabolites. Additionally, it contributes insights into plant ecology by studying mycorrhizal symbiosis and nutrient acquisition, benefiting ecological science. The project's interdisciplinary approach spans biology, agriculture, and entrepreneurship, fostering expertise and innovative solutions for agricultural challenges.</p> <p><strong>Research Areas and Results:</strong></p> <p><strong>Organic Vegetables </strong></p> <p>Sensitive Crop Screening:</p> <p>We assessed the growth response of more than thirty crop varieties of organic vegetables, herbs, seed crops and others to our AM fungal isolates (Figure 1). Biomass data collection revealed varying responses of different crops to mycorrhizal inoculation. Certain crops like Brandywine Tomato, Fennel, Arugula, Cilantro, Cannabis, Echinacea, Marjoram, Peppers, Parsley, and many others exhibited improved growth after inoculation with mycorrhizal isolates. Crop response also varied based on the growing media, suggesting context-dependent benefits.</p> <p>Field Trials of Organic Crops:</p> <p>Initial results from the <em>in-situ</em> field trial showed promising outcomes (Figure 2). Tomato varieties demonstrated consistently increased harvested weights across multiple harvests due to inoculation, ranging from +10% to +44% improvements in tomato biomass. For peppers, the response depended on crop variety, with the net pepper biomass being improved +1 to +8% percent across different harvest dates after native AM fungal inoculation.</p> <p>Specific Mycorrhizal Isolate Mediated Productivity and Nutrient Acquisition:</p> <p>In our study on plant nutrition, we examined three annual crops: Italian Sweet Basil, Lucullus Swiss Chard, and Mammoth Jalapeno. Fungal inoculation generally improved growth, while the mycorrhizal mixture enriched leaf concentrations of various nutrients. These enhancements in nutrient content, spanning macronutrients (such as nitrogen, phosphorus, potassium, calcium, magnesium, sulfur, and carbon) and micronutrients (including iron, copper, and manganese), collectively contributed to the overall improvement in the nutritional quality of the plants after inoculation with AM fungi (Figure 3).</p> <p><strong>Plant Secondary Compounds</strong></p> <p>Mycorrhizal Mediated Secondary Metabolite Production in Echinacea:</p> <p><em>Echinacea</em> growth depended significantly on inoculation with mycorrhizal fungal species (Figure 4). Different <em>Echinacea</em> species preferred distinct fungal isolates, suggesting the need for a diverse mix for optimal value. The presence of caffeic acid, a secondary metabolite compound known for its antioxidant and anti-inflammatory properties, showed improvement in inoculated plant tissues, potentially indicating enhanced medicinal properties resulting from AM fungal inoculation.</p> <p>Cannabigerol (CBG) Concentration in Industrial Hemp:</p> <p>Industrial hemp was grown for 21 weeks in the field to assess the effect of mycorrhizal isolates on cannabinoid content. CBG concentration was found to be significantly greater with the fungal mixture than with commercial products or controls (Figure 5). The trial indicated the potential for mycorrhizal influence on cannabinoid production, which may have significant implications for medicinal applications.</p> <p>Comparing with Commercial Inocula Products:</p> <p>We tested our lab-cultured mycorrhizal isolates against 16 commercial products using lettuce and carrots (Figure 6). The results were revealing. One product had no viable propagules. All commercial products had fewer propagules than claimed, ranging from 39% to a staggering 37,125% deficit. Nine out of 16 products performed worse with live propagules. Several products outperformed the control regardless of propagule viability, possibly due to fertilizer effects. This reveals inconsistencies between commercial products and our isolates. Furthermore, limited viability in commercial products emphasizes the need for industry quality control, ensuring precise product composition and effectiveness.</p> <p><strong>Entrepreneurial Focus:</strong></p> <p>The project also aimed to train early career scientists in entrepreneurship, collaborating with Wallace Meyer, Director of Entrepreneurship Programs at the University of Kansas. Both PIs, Liz Koziol and James Bever, have engaged in entrepreneurial activities like USDA I-FAST and NSF I-CORPS. Liz's objectives include customer discovery, research partnerships, entrepreneurial best practices, and developing her startup, MycoBloom. With successful trials and agricultural producers' interest, Koziol plans to commercialize a product for organic crops. She would partner with KU&rsquo;s Center for Technology Commercialization via MycoBloom and secure a commercial license.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <p>The project's broader impacts are multifaceted. This project resulted in the training of more than a dozen post-doctoral researchers, graduate students, and undergraduate students. &nbsp;It supports MycoBloom LLC's growth, empowering women in business by developing technology for organic farmers. By enhancing crop productivity and nutrient content, the research directly benefits modern farming practices. Addressing gaps in plant ecology, it advances knowledge of mycorrhizal fungi's effects on secondary metabolites and nutrient composition, potentially reshaping agricultural methods.</p> <p>Globally, the project mitigates soil stress and nutrient loss in organic soils, improving soil quality and nutrient retention. Collaboration with entrepreneurship experts fosters innovation in agriculture, aligning with the NSF PFI's aim to cultivate scientific entrepreneurship. Successful outcomes pave the way for product commercialization, offering crop solutions and boosting farmers' profitability.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/01/2023<br> Modified by: Elizabeth&nbsp;Koziol</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701459098719_Slide4--rgov-214x142.JPG" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701459098719_Slide4--rgov-800width.JPG" title="Echinacea's response to AM fungal isolates."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701459098719_Slide4--rgov-66x44.JPG" alt="Echinacea's response to AM fungal isolates."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">In our Echinacea study, mycorrhizal isolates (blue) boosted plant biomass (A) and caffeic acid concentration (B) relative to the control (white). The fungal mixture (black) exhibited a 60% increase in caffeic acid, showcasing mycorrhizal interactions' potential to enhance Echinacea's medicinal prope</div> <div class="imageCredit">Liz Koziol</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Elizabeth&nbsp;Koziol <div class="imageTitle">Echinacea's response to AM fungal isolates.</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701458582975_Slide1--rgov-214x142.JPG" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701458582975_Slide1--rgov-800width.JPG" title="Table of tested plant varieties and field and greenhouse photos"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701458582975_Slide1--rgov-66x44.JPG" alt="Table of tested plant varieties and field and greenhouse photos"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Table 1: Evaluated 30+ organic crop varieties for mycorrhizal response to AM fungal isolates. Tests followed USDA organic protocols in nurseries and fields, vital for on-farm propagation. Includes visuals of field tomatoes and AM fungal inoculation trials in the greenhouse.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Liz Koziol</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Elizabeth&nbsp;Koziol <div class="imageTitle">Table of tested plant varieties and field and greenhouse photos</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701459362765_Slide6--rgov-214x142.JPG" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701459362765_Slide6--rgov-800width.JPG" title="Quality Discrepancies in Commercial Mycorrhizal Products: Impact on Propagule Counts and Crop Growth"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701459362765_Slide6--rgov-66x44.JPG" alt="Quality Discrepancies in Commercial Mycorrhizal Products: Impact on Propagule Counts and Crop Growth"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(A) Commercial mycorrhizal products had propagule counts 39%-37,125% below stated values. (B) Lettuce trials showed commercial inoculants (blue) decreased growth by 7%, while lab cultures (black) increased by +37%. Industry quality control for accurate product composition and effectiveness is needed</div> <div class="imageCredit">Liz Koziol</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Elizabeth&nbsp;Koziol <div class="imageTitle">Quality Discrepancies in Commercial Mycorrhizal Products: Impact on Propagule Counts and Crop Growth</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701460423519_Slide5--rgov-214x142.JPG" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701460423519_Slide5--rgov-800width.JPG" title="AM fungi alter hemp survival and CBG concentration"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701460423519_Slide5--rgov-66x44.JPG" alt="AM fungi alter hemp survival and CBG concentration"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Industrial hemp trial: Native fungal isolates (blue) and mixture (black) outperform commercial product (grey) and control (white), elevating seedling survival (A) and CBG concentration by 24% (B). Demonstrates mycorrhizal inoculation's potential for superior hemp growth and cannabinoid content.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Liz Koziol</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Elizabeth&nbsp;Koziol <div class="imageTitle">AM fungi alter hemp survival and CBG concentration</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701459046060_Slide3--rgov-214x142.JPG" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701459046060_Slide3--rgov-800width.JPG" title="AM fungal isolates enhance Basil biomass and nutrient content for nutritionally enriched plants."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701459046060_Slide3--rgov-66x44.JPG" alt="AM fungal isolates enhance Basil biomass and nutrient content for nutritionally enriched plants."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Italian Sweet Basil: (A) Biomass responded to mycorrhizal isolates (blue); the mixture showed no increase (black). (B-K) Macronutrients and micronutrients varied, but the AM fungal mixture enhanced nutrient concentrations in leaves compared to the control (white), resulting in more nutritious plants</div> <div class="imageCredit">Liz Koziol</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Elizabeth&nbsp;Koziol <div class="imageTitle">AM fungal isolates enhance Basil biomass and nutrient content for nutritionally enriched plants.</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701458746508_Slide2--rgov-214x142.JPG" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701458746508_Slide2--rgov-800width.JPG" title="Field tomato and pepper biomass figure with and without inoculation."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016549/2016549_10706268_1701458746508_Slide2--rgov-66x44.JPG" alt="Field tomato and pepper biomass figure with and without inoculation."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Tomatoes thrived with AM fungal inoculation (black), yielding a remarkable +44% to +10% surge in biomass over seven harvests (A, B). Peppers consistently showed increased biomass (C, black) with a 1% to 8% boost depending on harvest date (D).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Liz Koziol</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Elizabeth&nbsp;Koziol <div class="imageTitle">Field tomato and pepper biomass figure with and without inoculation.</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Project Goals:   The project led by PIs Liz Koziol and James D. Bever aims to explore unique mycorrhizal isolates for boosting organic crop production. Mycorrhizal fungi enhance plant growth and nutrient absorption. The study systematically examines the impact of mycorrhizal fungi on organic crop growth, using field and greenhouse tests. This advances our understanding of their role in improving plant growth, nutrition, and secondary metabolites. Additionally, it contributes insights into plant ecology by studying mycorrhizal symbiosis and nutrient acquisition, benefiting ecological science. The project's interdisciplinary approach spans biology, agriculture, and entrepreneurship, fostering expertise and innovative solutions for agricultural challenges.   Research Areas and Results:   Organic Vegetables    Sensitive Crop Screening:   We assessed the growth response of more than thirty crop varieties of organic vegetables, herbs, seed crops and others to our AM fungal isolates (Figure 1). Biomass data collection revealed varying responses of different crops to mycorrhizal inoculation. Certain crops like Brandywine Tomato, Fennel, Arugula, Cilantro, Cannabis, Echinacea, Marjoram, Peppers, Parsley, and many others exhibited improved growth after inoculation with mycorrhizal isolates. Crop response also varied based on the growing media, suggesting context-dependent benefits.   Field Trials of Organic Crops:   Initial results from the in-situ field trial showed promising outcomes (Figure 2). Tomato varieties demonstrated consistently increased harvested weights across multiple harvests due to inoculation, ranging from +10% to +44% improvements in tomato biomass. For peppers, the response depended on crop variety, with the net pepper biomass being improved +1 to +8% percent across different harvest dates after native AM fungal inoculation.   Specific Mycorrhizal Isolate Mediated Productivity and Nutrient Acquisition:   In our study on plant nutrition, we examined three annual crops: Italian Sweet Basil, Lucullus Swiss Chard, and Mammoth Jalapeno. Fungal inoculation generally improved growth, while the mycorrhizal mixture enriched leaf concentrations of various nutrients. These enhancements in nutrient content, spanning macronutrients (such as nitrogen, phosphorus, potassium, calcium, magnesium, sulfur, and carbon) and micronutrients (including iron, copper, and manganese), collectively contributed to the overall improvement in the nutritional quality of the plants after inoculation with AM fungi (Figure 3).   Plant Secondary Compounds   Mycorrhizal Mediated Secondary Metabolite Production in Echinacea:   Echinacea growth depended significantly on inoculation with mycorrhizal fungal species (Figure 4). Different Echinacea species preferred distinct fungal isolates, suggesting the need for a diverse mix for optimal value. The presence of caffeic acid, a secondary metabolite compound known for its antioxidant and anti-inflammatory properties, showed improvement in inoculated plant tissues, potentially indicating enhanced medicinal properties resulting from AM fungal inoculation.   Cannabigerol (CBG) Concentration in Industrial Hemp:   Industrial hemp was grown for 21 weeks in the field to assess the effect of mycorrhizal isolates on cannabinoid content. CBG concentration was found to be significantly greater with the fungal mixture than with commercial products or controls (Figure 5). The trial indicated the potential for mycorrhizal influence on cannabinoid production, which may have significant implications for medicinal applications.   Comparing with Commercial Inocula Products:   We tested our lab-cultured mycorrhizal isolates against 16 commercial products using lettuce and carrots (Figure 6). The results were revealing. One product had no viable propagules. All commercial products had fewer propagules than claimed, ranging from 39% to a staggering 37,125% deficit. Nine out of 16 products performed worse with live propagules. Several products outperformed the control regardless of propagule viability, possibly due to fertilizer effects. This reveals inconsistencies between commercial products and our isolates. Furthermore, limited viability in commercial products emphasizes the need for industry quality control, ensuring precise product composition and effectiveness.   Entrepreneurial Focus:   The project also aimed to train early career scientists in entrepreneurship, collaborating with Wallace Meyer, Director of Entrepreneurship Programs at the University of Kansas. Both PIs, Liz Koziol and James Bever, have engaged in entrepreneurial activities like USDA I-FAST and NSF I-CORPS. Liz's objectives include customer discovery, research partnerships, entrepreneurial best practices, and developing her startup, MycoBloom. With successful trials and agricultural producers' interest, Koziol plans to commercialize a product for organic crops. She would partner with KUs Center for Technology Commercialization via MycoBloom and secure a commercial license.   Broader Impacts:   The project's broader impacts are multifaceted. This project resulted in the training of more than a dozen post-doctoral researchers, graduate students, and undergraduate students. It supports MycoBloom LLC's growth, empowering women in business by developing technology for organic farmers. By enhancing crop productivity and nutrient content, the research directly benefits modern farming practices. Addressing gaps in plant ecology, it advances knowledge of mycorrhizal fungi's effects on secondary metabolites and nutrient composition, potentially reshaping agricultural methods.   Globally, the project mitigates soil stress and nutrient loss in organic soils, improving soil quality and nutrient retention. Collaboration with entrepreneurship experts fosters innovation in agriculture, aligning with the NSF PFI's aim to cultivate scientific entrepreneurship. Successful outcomes pave the way for product commercialization, offering crop solutions and boosting farmers' profitability.     Last Modified: 12/01/2023       Submitted by: ElizabethKoziol]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
