<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of an Operando 500 MHz Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) Spectrometer]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>489013.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>489013</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tanya Whitmer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>twhitmer@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922912</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is supported by the Major Research Instrumentation and the Chemistry Research Instrumentation programs. The University of Wisconsin Madison is acquiring a 500 MHz nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectrometer equipped with a flow tube accessory and dedicated software that enable online monitoring of chemical reactions in real-time under actual experimental conditions. The instrumentation supports Professor Charles Fry and colleagues at the Wisconsin High-Pressure Reactor (WiHP-NNMR). This spectrometer allows research in a variety of fields such as those that accelerate chemical reactions of significant economic importance, as well as permitting study of biologically relevant species. In general, NMR spectroscopy is one of the most powerful tools available to chemists for the elucidation of the structure of molecules. It is used to identify unknown substances, to characterize specific arrangements of atoms within molecules, and to study the dynamics of interactions between molecules in solution or in the solid state. Access to state-of-the-art NMR spectrometers is essential to chemists who are carrying out frontier research. This instrument is an integral part of teaching as well as research and research training of undergraduate students in chemistry and biochemistry at this institution and nearby colleges such as Madison College, University of Wisconsin La Crosse, University of Wisconsin Rock County, University of Wisconsin Whitewater, Lawrence University, Maranatha Baptist University, Indiana State University and Valparaiso University. The Magnetic Resonance Facility plays an important role in strengthening the relationship between the University and Wisconsin citizens by working closely with departmental programs advocating the importance of science, research, and education to the public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award of the NMR spectrometer is aimed at enhancing research and education at all levels. It especially impacts discovery of metal-metal bonded catalysts and carbon-hydrogen functionalization reactions. The instrumentation is also for exploring photoredox catalysis, polymer mechanochemistry and three-dimensional (3D) printing. In addition, it provides information on operando investigations of transition metal catalyzed reactions. An operando method involves spectroscopic characterization of materials undergoing reaction which is coupled simultaneously with measurement of catalytic activity and selectivity. The spectrometer is also used to develop catalysts for aerobic oxidation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017891</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Fry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles G Fry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[fry@chem.wisc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000479890</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 N PARK ST STE 6301</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LCLSJAGTNZQ7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>Chemical Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~489013</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Chemistry Magnetic Resonance Facility in the University of Wisconsin-Madison has purchased and installed a nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectrometer with state-of-the-art 500 MHz operando and reaction monitoring capabilities. The instrument was made available to researchers starting in July 2021. NMR is a primary technique for the characterization of chemical compounds and reactions. Two key examples are: (1) Information-rich data obtained from the instrument can confirm (or not) a compound's chemical structure, guiding chemists as to whether a reaction has proceeded as expected (or not).&nbsp; (2) Data obtained during a reaction can elucidate the kinetics and chemical details or mechanisms of the reaction. It is important that the reaction is run at the correct temperatures and pressures, i.e., at operando conditions. In the past, NMR experiments were limited to a small range of temperatures and pressures with a static sample. To obtain NMR data from a reaction run at high temperature and/or pressure, aliquots from the reaction vessel would have to be extracted at multiple time points during the reaction and then measured. The drawback for this method is data points are limited by the time involved to do the sample extractions. In addition, the extracted samples are moved to a new, different environment. Our new NMR spectrometer enables operando conditions to be used covering an expanded range of temperatures and pressures via a device invented in Chemistry at UW-Madison called the WiHP-NMRR. The spectrometer is equipped with another new device -- Bruker BioSpin's InsightMR -- that allows reaction mixtures to flow through the spectrometer, enabling real-time in situ measurements to be performed. The InsightMR reaction monitoring device allows much more data to be acquired in a much simpler manner.</p> <p>These new operando and reaction monitoring capabilities have produced significant impacts on chemical research in a variety of areas. Data from the NMR spectrometer enabled chemists to achieve the following: (1) Alkene polymerization forms a major class of chemical manufacturing of plastics. The formation of "dormant" chemical sites that disrupt the desired alkene polymerization process has been identified using operando NMR. (2) Reaction monitoring by NMR provides significant insights into reactions that depend on light (photochemical reactions utilizing LED light).&nbsp; LED-NMR has provided detailed new information in the field of photochemical synthesis, proving to be enabling for such studies, and will be used in the design of new chemical processes in the area of asymmetric photoreactions. (3) Most chemical reactions involve multiple steps: e.g., compound A is added to B, their product is extracted and then further reacts with compound C, and so on. The reaction monitoring capability of the new NMR spectrometer assisted in the development of a one-step diamination (removal of amine, often as ammonia) reaction by providing data for key mechanistic insights. This one-step reaction is particularly useful for researchers that do not have access to electrochemical equipment.</p> <p>In the next year or two, a few examples where the new NMR spectrometer is expected to impact research are: 1) assist in the development of oxygen scavengers to reduce degradation from radical anions in lithium batteries; 2) be a key technique in the investigation of multiple reagent effects on dormant sites in alkene polymerization; 3) assist in the development of new M-N-C catalysts that are designed to improve palladium complexes that transform cheap, abundant biomass-derived alcohol feedstock into value-added chemicals; and 4) provide reaction kinetics for new synthetic investigations of S, N, and O-heterocyclooctynes, which facilitate bioconjugation and bioorthogonal labeling.</p> <p>The Operando NMR is a stellar instrument for research learning for graduate, undergraduate, and post-graduate students. The spectrometer can be utilized in three ways: 1) variable temperatures and pressures (up to 1500 psi) operando mode using the WiHP-NMRR device; 2) reaction monitoring mode using Bruker BioSpin's InsightMR device; and 3) "normal" liquids NMR mode that is critical in support of synthetic progress by guiding chemists as to "did my reaction go as expected".&nbsp; The third mode is also important in providing a platform for hands-on learning experiences for undergraduates. The unique capabilities of the spectrometer are provided to researchers at UW-Madison and in Wisconsin and beyond. Currently over one hundred-thirty researchers have been trained to use the spectrometer. Due to the flexible setup of the spectrometer, over fifty students per year in two undergraduate laboratories in Physical Chemistry and Organic Chemistry have hands-on use of the spectrometer. The ability to switch between the three operating modes has greatly broadened the spectrometer's impact, for research benefiting from operando and reaction monitoring, for synthetic chemists, and for research and educational learning.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 01/16/2024<br> Modified by: Charles&nbsp;G&nbsp;Fry</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The Chemistry Magnetic Resonance Facility in the University of Wisconsin-Madison has purchased and installed a nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectrometer with state-of-the-art 500 MHz operando and reaction monitoring capabilities. The instrument was made available to researchers starting in July 2021. NMR is a primary technique for the characterization of chemical compounds and reactions. Two key examples are: (1) Information-rich data obtained from the instrument can confirm (or not) a compound's chemical structure, guiding chemists as to whether a reaction has proceeded as expected (or not). (2) Data obtained during a reaction can elucidate the kinetics and chemical details or mechanisms of the reaction. It is important that the reaction is run at the correct temperatures and pressures, i.e., at operando conditions. In the past, NMR experiments were limited to a small range of temperatures and pressures with a static sample. To obtain NMR data from a reaction run at high temperature and/or pressure, aliquots from the reaction vessel would have to be extracted at multiple time points during the reaction and then measured. The drawback for this method is data points are limited by the time involved to do the sample extractions. In addition, the extracted samples are moved to a new, different environment. Our new NMR spectrometer enables operando conditions to be used covering an expanded range of temperatures and pressures via a device invented in Chemistry at UW-Madison called the WiHP-NMRR. The spectrometer is equipped with another new device -- Bruker BioSpin's InsightMR -- that allows reaction mixtures to flow through the spectrometer, enabling real-time in situ measurements to be performed. The InsightMR reaction monitoring device allows much more data to be acquired in a much simpler manner.   These new operando and reaction monitoring capabilities have produced significant impacts on chemical research in a variety of areas. Data from the NMR spectrometer enabled chemists to achieve the following: (1) Alkene polymerization forms a major class of chemical manufacturing of plastics. The formation of "dormant" chemical sites that disrupt the desired alkene polymerization process has been identified using operando NMR. (2) Reaction monitoring by NMR provides significant insights into reactions that depend on light (photochemical reactions utilizing LED light). LED-NMR has provided detailed new information in the field of photochemical synthesis, proving to be enabling for such studies, and will be used in the design of new chemical processes in the area of asymmetric photoreactions. (3) Most chemical reactions involve multiple steps: e.g., compound A is added to B, their product is extracted and then further reacts with compound C, and so on. The reaction monitoring capability of the new NMR spectrometer assisted in the development of a one-step diamination (removal of amine, often as ammonia) reaction by providing data for key mechanistic insights. This one-step reaction is particularly useful for researchers that do not have access to electrochemical equipment.   In the next year or two, a few examples where the new NMR spectrometer is expected to impact research are: 1) assist in the development of oxygen scavengers to reduce degradation from radical anions in lithium batteries; 2) be a key technique in the investigation of multiple reagent effects on dormant sites in alkene polymerization; 3) assist in the development of new M-N-C catalysts that are designed to improve palladium complexes that transform cheap, abundant biomass-derived alcohol feedstock into value-added chemicals; and 4) provide reaction kinetics for new synthetic investigations of S, N, and O-heterocyclooctynes, which facilitate bioconjugation and bioorthogonal labeling.   The Operando NMR is a stellar instrument for research learning for graduate, undergraduate, and post-graduate students. The spectrometer can be utilized in three ways: 1) variable temperatures and pressures (up to 1500 psi) operando mode using the WiHP-NMRR device; 2) reaction monitoring mode using Bruker BioSpin's InsightMR device; and 3) "normal" liquids NMR mode that is critical in support of synthetic progress by guiding chemists as to "did my reaction go as expected". The third mode is also important in providing a platform for hands-on learning experiences for undergraduates. The unique capabilities of the spectrometer are provided to researchers at UW-Madison and in Wisconsin and beyond. Currently over one hundred-thirty researchers have been trained to use the spectrometer. Due to the flexible setup of the spectrometer, over fifty students per year in two undergraduate laboratories in Physical Chemistry and Organic Chemistry have hands-on use of the spectrometer. The ability to switch between the three operating modes has greatly broadened the spectrometer's impact, for research benefiting from operando and reaction monitoring, for synthetic chemists, and for research and educational learning.        Last Modified: 01/16/2024       Submitted by: CharlesGFry]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
