<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Workshop: International Collaboration in Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Diseases, 12 to 14 June 2020, Montpellier]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Katharina Dittmar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdittmar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927799</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This workshop aims to allow leading and upcoming US researchers in EEID research to communicate and synthesize current knowledge of epidemiology, ecology and evolution of infectious diseases in an international arena. By identifying and assessing major gaps in data, information and knowledge in the EEID, this workshop is going to contribute to the global community's effort and advance our ability and skills in predicting and mapping hot-spots, hot-moments, emergence, spread, and persistence of infectious diseases in the near future.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts mainly center around the long-term development of research priority areas and mechanisms for joint research and education activities in EEID between the US and other international stakeholders.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018797</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Harvill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric T Harvill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[harvill@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000225571</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 E CAMPUS RD RM 409]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NMJHD63STRC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 East Campus Rd, Tucker Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7242</Code>
<Text>Ecology of Infectious Diseases</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The importance of integrating the social sciences within a more traditional Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Diseases (EEID) framework has become a common feature of infectious disease policy and practice debates, regardless of disease system. However, to date, this transdisciplinary approach and integration remains challenging, fragmented, and under-funded, with limited reach and small initial investments. In this workshop, we brought together researchers from various fields with a variety of knowledge, perspectives, and theoretical underpinnings. The goal was to help design new transdisciplinary paths and collaborations, to foster a more holistic infrastructure, to tackle funding gaps that hinder the full integration of the social sciences into EEID, and present a strategic framework for addressing them. Further we hoped to create novel links between researchers in different continents and lead to new projects, but most importantly to push the field into exciting directions, ask new questions, generate new theory, and design novel empirical methodologies. Our first objectives were to carry out a landscape analysis of the new directions in topics EEID, to review experiences &amp; blockers/ barriers, and to review approaches.&nbsp; A series of questions were identified: Are we tackling the same broad scale problems through different lens? Can we identify risks, gaps &amp; opportunities to &ldquo;donate the armchair&rdquo; and truly cross collaborate?&nbsp; How can we better explore models &amp; data? Are coupled systems the way forward? Can we identify pressing next steps toward the development of new collaborations to pose transdisciplinary questions?<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Outputs</strong><br /><em>Direct immediate-term products of the workshop which might lead to outcomes</em></p> <ul> <li>Brought together inter- and intra-country researchers from different social science and mathematical, computational and life science communities</li> <li>Identified and highlighted key knowledge gaps and prioritised research and innovation needs</li> <li>Recommended how to increase future collaboration between social sciences and mathematics, computational and life scientists<br /><br /></li> </ul> <p><strong>Outcomes&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<br /></strong><em>Longer-term change that may not be seen immediately after the event</em></p> <ul> <li>Increased the number of inter- and intra- country partnerships between different social science and mathematical, computational and life science research communities</li> <li>Built strong transdisciplinary research communities in systems approaches to tackling infections that are ready to mobilise as funding opportunities materialise</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Prepared for future high scientific quality grant proposals in this area, including social science led applications</li> <li>Established engagement activities for continued dialogue between social scientists and mathematical, computational and life scientists internationally</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> </ul><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/26/2023<br> Modified by: Eric&nbsp;T&nbsp;Harvill</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The importance of integrating the social sciences within a more traditional Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Diseases (EEID) framework has become a common feature of infectious disease policy and practice debates, regardless of disease system. However, to date, this transdisciplinary approach and integration remains challenging, fragmented, and under-funded, with limited reach and small initial investments. In this workshop, we brought together researchers from various fields with a variety of knowledge, perspectives, and theoretical underpinnings. The goal was to help design new transdisciplinary paths and collaborations, to foster a more holistic infrastructure, to tackle funding gaps that hinder the full integration of the social sciences into EEID, and present a strategic framework for addressing them. Further we hoped to create novel links between researchers in different continents and lead to new projects, but most importantly to push the field into exciting directions, ask new questions, generate new theory, and design novel empirical methodologies. Our first objectives were to carry out a landscape analysis of the new directions in topics EEID, to review experiences & blockers/ barriers, and to review approaches. A series of questions were identified: Are we tackling the same broad scale problems through different lens? Can we identify risks, gaps & opportunities to donate the armchair and truly cross collaborate? How can we better explore models & data? Are coupled systems the way forward? Can we identify pressing next steps toward the development of new collaborations to pose transdisciplinary questions?      Outputs Direct immediate-term products of the workshop which might lead to outcomes  Brought together inter- and intra-country researchers from different social science and mathematical, computational and life science communities Identified and highlighted key knowledge gaps and prioritised research and innovation needs Recommended how to increase future collaboration between social sciences and mathematics, computational and life scientists      Outcomes Longer-term change that may not be seen immediately after the event  Increased the number of inter- and intra- country partnerships between different social science and mathematical, computational and life science research communities Built strong transdisciplinary research communities in systems approaches to tackling infections that are ready to mobilise as funding opportunities materialise   Prepared for future high scientific quality grant proposals in this area, including social science led applications Established engagement activities for continued dialogue between social scientists and mathematical, computational and life scientists internationally              Last Modified: 11/26/2023       Submitted by: EricTHarvill]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
