<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of a Multi-nuclear 400 MHz NMR Spectrometer Equipped with an Autosampler to Support Undergraduate Research at a Hispanic Serving/Minority Serving Institution]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>351157.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>351157</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kenneth Carter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>krcarter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922335</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is supported by the Major Research Instrumentation and the Chemistry Research Instrumentation programs. California State University San Bernardino (UEC at CSUSB) is acquiring a 400 MHz nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectrometer equipped with an automatic sample changer to support Dr. Jeremy Mallari and colleagues Drs. Kimberley Cousins, Douglas Smith and Jason Burke. This spectrometer allows research in a variety of fields such as those that accelerate chemical reactions of significant economic importance, as well as permitting the study of biologically relevant species. In general, NMR spectroscopy is one of the most powerful tools available to chemists for the elucidation of the structure of molecules. It is used to identify unknown substances, to characterize specific arrangements of atoms within molecules, and to study the dynamics of interactions between molecules in solution or in the solid state. Access to state-of-the-art NMR spectrometers is essential to chemists who are carrying out frontier research. This instrument is an integral part of teaching as well as research and research training of undergraduate students in chemistry and biochemistry at this institution and nearby institutions and community colleges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award of the NMR spectrometer is aimed at enhancing research and education at all levels. It especially impacts the development of ferroelectric and piezoelectric systems. The instrumentation is also aimed at supporting activities related to the extraction of lithium from seawater. In addition, it benefits the development of chemical tools to investigate malaria protease biology. The spectrometer is also to be used to investigate chalcone isomerase evolution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018196</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Burke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason R Burke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Jason.Burke@csusb.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000796775</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas C Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dcsmith@csusb.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000275792</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Mallari</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeremy P Mallari</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jeremy.mallari@csusb.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000796666</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimberley</FirstName>
<LastName>Cousins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kimberley R Cousins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kcousins@csusb.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000257041</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University Enterprises Corporation at CSUSB</Name>
<CityName>SAN BERNARDINO</CityName>
<ZipCode>924072318</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9095375929</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5500 UNIVERSITY PKWY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QJZ1F3UMLEJ4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY ENTERPRISES CORPORATION AT CSUSB</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University Enterprises Corporation at CSUSB]]></Name>
<CityName>San Bernardino</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>924072318</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5500 University Parkway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~351157</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Chemistry Department at California State University-San Bernardino (CSUSB) purchased a 400 MHz Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectrometer with a high-capacity autosampler to support faculty research efforts, undergraduate research training, and departmental laboratory courses by providing access to high-resolution NMR analysis. NMR spectroscopy is an essential technique in organic and biochemistry, and enables a range of experiments to elucidate molecular structure, conformation, and binding interactions in organic molecules. The system is equipped with a 64-slot autosampler as well as automated cloud data management and storage. This allows large numbers of samples to be analyzed by multiple users and has greatly increased NMR access for research groups on campus as well as to students in various chemistry laboratory courses. Students and faculty can access NMR data obtained, and process it on other computers, further increasing access. The institution continues to make ongoing investments to ensure the instrument remains operative, including sending three staff members to the company headquarters for technical support training, and prioritizing obtaining the the needed Helium gas supply for cooling the superconducting magnet.</p> <p>Intellectual merit: The instrument was installed in Spring 2021 and has since been used to support six different research projects conducted by four faculty investigators at CSUSB, including may undergraduate student researchers. Projects include detecting how plants communicate (Burke lab), seeking new ways to prevent transmission of malaria (Mallari lab), and developing new materials for microelectronics and other applications (Cousins and Smith labs). Dr. Jason Burke&rsquo;s group published a paper in the Journal of Biological Chemistry in which the authors characterized plant communications that take place when small molecules bind to a plant protein. The NMR instrument was essential during the synthesis and structural characterization of one of the small molecules used in this study. In a separate project, Dr. Jeremy Mallari&rsquo;s group has made extensive use of the instrument in order to synthesize and evaluate a series of ~30 novel small molecules that could stop parasites from infecting human hosts with malaria. Several compounds with potent anti-parasitic activity were identified, and a manuscript is in preparation to report the results of these studies. Finally, Dr. Cousins and Dr. Smith continue to work towards developing novel crystalline materials with properties that can be used in micro devices. NMR experiments are used to determine chemical structures of the compounds that comprise crystals created. Several new functional materials have resulted in student presentations and future publication.</p> <p>Broader impact: CSUSB serves a largely minority and disadvantaged student population, and the acquired instrument has helped to expand the use of modern instrumentation for our over 1000 chemistry and biology majors. Undergraduate research is a powerful high-impact teaching practice, though our ability to incorporate research projects into the curriculum had previously been limited by bottlenecks associated with data acquisition and analysis. The upgraded NMR system has eliminated these limitations and enabled us to significantly increase the amount of NMR experience that we are able to offer to our students in both upper and lower division courses. The instrument has enabled us to expand our course-based undergraduate research offerings, and for the last two years we have been piloting a semester-long organic synthesis research course for our Chemistry majors. In this course, students synthesize novel anti-malarial compounds using methodology developed by Dr. Mallari&rsquo;s research group. These courses have been a highly effective way of exposing a broader range of students to laboratory research, and it is notable that at least 5 of the 20 student participants to date have gone on to join a faculty research laboratory at CSUSB.</p> <p>In addition to course-based research, we have also revised parts of our curriculum to increase the number of experiments incorporating NMR analysis in our traditional Organic Chemistry laboratory courses. This gives students significantly more in-depth experience in analyzing complex data sets and more hands-on time with research grade instrumentation. These curriculum enhancements foster increased learning and student engagement, leading to: 1) increased student interest in laboratory research careers; 2) improved quality of training for our STEM majors.</p> <p>We are also providing access to this important analytical technique to students enrolled at community colleges in our area. Due to high costs, most community colleges are unable to host high-resolution NMR spectrometer for use in their courses. The chemistry department at neighboring Victor Valley College has already begun utilizing the NMR instrument at CSUSB to enhance their organic chemistry lab courses, giving their students similar opportunities to gain valuable experience with modern analysis. Other community colleges in the area have also expressed interest in using the instrument, and we anticipate expanding outreach in the future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/13/2023<br> Modified by: Jeremy&nbsp;P&nbsp;Mallari</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The Chemistry Department at California State University-San Bernardino (CSUSB) purchased a 400 MHz Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectrometer with a high-capacity autosampler to support faculty research efforts, undergraduate research training, and departmental laboratory courses by providing access to high-resolution NMR analysis. NMR spectroscopy is an essential technique in organic and biochemistry, and enables a range of experiments to elucidate molecular structure, conformation, and binding interactions in organic molecules. The system is equipped with a 64-slot autosampler as well as automated cloud data management and storage. This allows large numbers of samples to be analyzed by multiple users and has greatly increased NMR access for research groups on campus as well as to students in various chemistry laboratory courses. Students and faculty can access NMR data obtained, and process it on other computers, further increasing access. The institution continues to make ongoing investments to ensure the instrument remains operative, including sending three staff members to the company headquarters for technical support training, and prioritizing obtaining the the needed Helium gas supply for cooling the superconducting magnet.   Intellectual merit: The instrument was installed in Spring 2021 and has since been used to support six different research projects conducted by four faculty investigators at CSUSB, including may undergraduate student researchers. Projects include detecting how plants communicate (Burke lab), seeking new ways to prevent transmission of malaria (Mallari lab), and developing new materials for microelectronics and other applications (Cousins and Smith labs). Dr. Jason Burkes group published a paper in the Journal of Biological Chemistry in which the authors characterized plant communications that take place when small molecules bind to a plant protein. The NMR instrument was essential during the synthesis and structural characterization of one of the small molecules used in this study. In a separate project, Dr. Jeremy Mallaris group has made extensive use of the instrument in order to synthesize and evaluate a series of ~30 novel small molecules that could stop parasites from infecting human hosts with malaria. Several compounds with potent anti-parasitic activity were identified, and a manuscript is in preparation to report the results of these studies. Finally, Dr. Cousins and Dr. Smith continue to work towards developing novel crystalline materials with properties that can be used in micro devices. NMR experiments are used to determine chemical structures of the compounds that comprise crystals created. Several new functional materials have resulted in student presentations and future publication.   Broader impact: CSUSB serves a largely minority and disadvantaged student population, and the acquired instrument has helped to expand the use of modern instrumentation for our over 1000 chemistry and biology majors. Undergraduate research is a powerful high-impact teaching practice, though our ability to incorporate research projects into the curriculum had previously been limited by bottlenecks associated with data acquisition and analysis. The upgraded NMR system has eliminated these limitations and enabled us to significantly increase the amount of NMR experience that we are able to offer to our students in both upper and lower division courses. The instrument has enabled us to expand our course-based undergraduate research offerings, and for the last two years we have been piloting a semester-long organic synthesis research course for our Chemistry majors. In this course, students synthesize novel anti-malarial compounds using methodology developed by Dr. Mallaris research group. These courses have been a highly effective way of exposing a broader range of students to laboratory research, and it is notable that at least 5 of the 20 student participants to date have gone on to join a faculty research laboratory at CSUSB.   In addition to course-based research, we have also revised parts of our curriculum to increase the number of experiments incorporating NMR analysis in our traditional Organic Chemistry laboratory courses. This gives students significantly more in-depth experience in analyzing complex data sets and more hands-on time with research grade instrumentation. These curriculum enhancements foster increased learning and student engagement, leading to: 1) increased student interest in laboratory research careers; 2) improved quality of training for our STEM majors.   We are also providing access to this important analytical technique to students enrolled at community colleges in our area. Due to high costs, most community colleges are unable to host high-resolution NMR spectrometer for use in their courses. The chemistry department at neighboring Victor Valley College has already begun utilizing the NMR instrument at CSUSB to enhance their organic chemistry lab courses, giving their students similar opportunities to gain valuable experience with modern analysis. Other community colleges in the area have also expressed interest in using the instrument, and we anticipate expanding outreach in the future.        Last Modified: 12/13/2023       Submitted by: JeremyPMallari]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
