<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of a surface &amp; sorption characterization instrument to enable multidisciplinary research at a rural West Texas HSI]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>257361.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>257361</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Harsha Chelliah</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hchellia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927281</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award will the support acquisition of material surface characterization instrument for research and education at West Texas A&amp;M University (WTAMU) and the partner institution Amarillo College (AC), located in the rural Panhandle of Texas. Both institutions are non-PhD granting institutions, while WTAMU is designated as a Hispanic Serving Institution with an overall Hispanic population of 26%. The proposed instrument will be able to quantify the surface and volume in highly porous materials and particles when exposed to gases under controlled temperature and pressure conditions. Ongoing research of 11 faculty members from both institutions will benefit from the instrument while over 30 graduate and undergraduate students will be exposed to cutting-edge surface science research. In addition, over 170 students will have an opportunity to use the instrument through planned coursework.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed team from environmental engineering, mechanical engineering, agricultural engineering, chemistry, and biochemistry plans to study physisorption and chemisorption phenomena using a Micrometrics 3Flex system. The specific research  areas to be explored include highly porous biochar as an inexpensive material for treatment of wastewater; effect of small-scale atmospheric cellulose in hail storm damage; improving the viability of methanol fuel cells to produce high power output for electronics and vehicles in a small space; and increasing understanding of surface chemistry of high energy nanomaterials for use as solids fuel, energy storage media, and explosives. In addition, evaluation of best practices in engaging Hispanic students in science and technology is an important aspect of the proposed work. Specifically, inclusion of Hispanic students in state-of-the-art instrumentation and their desire to pursue science and technology topics will be evaluated.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018383</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Naruki</FirstName>
<LastName>Hiranuma</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Naruki Hiranuma</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nhiranuma@wtamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000741110</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Asanga</FirstName>
<LastName>Ranasinghe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Asanga D Ranasinghe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[adranasinghe@actx.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819975</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Howell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathan Howell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nhowell@wtamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000727312</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Hunt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily M Hunt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ehunt@mail.wtamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000376174</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sanjoy</FirstName>
<LastName>Bhattacharia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sanjoy K Bhattacharia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sbhattacharia@wtamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000820159</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>West Texas A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>CANYON</CityName>
<ZipCode>790160001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8066512732</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2501 4TH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XTV5KMWKWES1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M UNIVERSITY SYSTEM,THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HH6VX5XDL284</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[West Texas A&M University]]></Name>
<CityName>Canyon</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>790160001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2501 4th Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~257361</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>West Texas A&amp;M University (WTAMU) along with partner institution Amarillo College (AC, community college) was awarded a grant to purchase a Micromeritics 3Flex surface analyzer. Purchasing this instrument for WTAMU meant that the we would add it to a common research space at the university where several other common use instruments are housed, the Engineering Core Laboratory (ECORE). We had four goals for the project.</p> <p><strong>Goal 1-Transformative, cross-disciplinary research in the fields of engineering, chemistry, and atmospheric science</strong>. There was cross-disciplinary research which we were able to achieve during the three-year project life in two main fields&mdash;atmospheric science and environmental engineering.</p> <p>The first project concerned atmospheric ice-nucleating particles (INPs) which are particles made from mineral dust and non-proteinaceous biological (e.g., plant fiber) sources that can influence cloud formation, precipitation, and Earth&rsquo;s radiation budget due to their efficient freezing abilities. The characterization of INPs and aerosol particles from these sources is important. We typically characterize their specific surface area (SSA), which is the primary variable to estimate their ice-nucleation active surface site density, using a sorbate gas. However, it is still uncertain how these particles interact with water vapor under subzero temperatures. Thus, we used the 3Flex instrument with multiple sorbates. Our results indicate that the SSA of illite NX (a mineral dust proxy) is less temperature-dependent compared to cellulose materials. Therefore, illite NX may be suitable as a proxy. A second series concerned determination of the surface area of North Slope of Alaska (NSA) soils. These soils exhibited different surface properties &ndash; some possess high SSA with mesopores while some materials come with low SSA with micropores. We find that understanding total sorption properties via temperature-dependent water sorption could be key in understanding the physics of atmospheric ice nucleation on insoluble aerosol particles.</p> <p>A second project concerned the evaluation of adsorbent biochar made from cotton gin waste (CGW). Our interest in biochar made from CGW is to convert a low value material into something of higher value which can be used to amend soils. We examined the quality of biochar that could be made from CGW (16 unique samples created). We used the 3Flex to examine the microporosity of biochar and its affinity for water vapor. We found that higher temperature always increases microporosity and that water adsorption in biochar is not precisely consistent with production conditions. It will be valuable for other researchers and farmers to know how to optimize these parameters for any large-scale field use.</p> <p><strong>Goal 2 - Use of instrument to target Hispanic and female students</strong>. This goal concerned the inclusion of the 3Flex tool in the ECORE to encourage Hispanic and female students for growth and interest in STEM fields. From all student researchers, an external evaluation finds that 58.3% of them were from under-represented minorities (URM) and 62.5% which were female. In addition, our group conducted an on campus to survey 443 students (out of 658 solicited) from 18 unique course offerings over the three years of the project to examine Hispanic student factors for college choice. Important findings from the survey are that Hispanic students consider the following factors more than their non-Hispanic peers --commuting distance, scholarships and financial aid, encouragement from parents, and the university having Hispanic Serving Institution (HSI) status.</p> <p><strong>Goal 3 - Attracting researchers from outside of West Texas A&amp;M University (WTAMU)</strong>. This instrument is very unique for the rural region which is the Texas Panhandle. One must ravel 200+ miles to access the next nearest similar tool. We therefore, sought to use this tool as a means to attract others outside of our typical research networks. We were able to attract a local lab manager from an electrical generating utility, researchers from the Department of Energy Environmental Molecular Sciences Laboratory (EMSL) for soil sample examinations, researchers from Texas A&amp;M University-College Station for confirmatory analysis of a nanodiamond powder, and USDA-ARS researcher leaders in Bushland, TX for agricultural greenhouse gas reductions.</p> <p><strong>Goal 4 - Training graduates and undergraduates through increased interaction in the WTAMU Engineering Core Laboratory (ECORE)</strong>. Many modern instruments are difficult to purchase and require years of experience to use. Thus, we used the 3Flex to get students exposed to the tool. Some merely learned about the concepts of measurement. At the other extreme, graduate students and one post-doc were able to run the instrument independently. We were able to have an undergraduate reach which was 120 student per year. These interactions occurred through lab tours, educational content, and students analyzing their own samples directly. The graduate student reach was about 10 per year. While we find these interactions to be significant, the instrument, which of course will be maintained and used for at least 10-20 more years, will need to be incorporated into more courses as a way to expose more students to surface analysis.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/30/2023<br> Modified by: Nathan&nbsp;Howell</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018383/2018383_10701724_1703970354916_image_1___ice_nucleation_efficiency--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018383/2018383_10701724_1703970354916_image_1___ice_nucleation_efficiency--rgov-800width.png" title="Ice nucleation efficiency for atmospheric minerals and cellulose particles"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018383/2018383_10701724_1703970354916_image_1___ice_nucleation_efficiency--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Ice nucleation efficiency for atmospheric minerals and cellulose particles"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Ice nucleation efficiency of illite NX, MCC, and NCC in terms of ns,H2O and ns,N2 as a function of temperature (a) and the ns,N2 spectra of NSA samples and some additional reference INP freezing spectra (b). *Hiranuma et al. (2019) **Hiranuma et al. (2105) ***Wex et al. (2015) ****Atkinson et al. (2</div> <div class="imageCredit">Naruki Hiranuma</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Nathan&nbsp;Howell <div class="imageTitle">Ice nucleation efficiency for atmospheric minerals and cellulose particles</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018383/2018383_10701724_1703970807502_image_3___biochar_creation--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018383/2018383_10701724_1703970807502_image_3___biochar_creation--rgov-800width.png" title="Biochar creation process from beef cattle manure in graduate student project"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018383/2018383_10701724_1703970807502_image_3___biochar_creation--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Biochar creation process from beef cattle manure in graduate student project"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students designed their own individual research project in a course on engineering instrumentation in the spring of 2023. One group chose to create biochar from a local beef cattle manure source at a research feedlot and then analyze the specific surface area on the 3Flex. They felt it was important</div> <div class="imageCredit">David Takal, Syed Numair Abbas</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Nathan&nbsp;Howell <div class="imageTitle">Biochar creation process from beef cattle manure in graduate student project</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018383/2018383_10701724_1703970701492_image_2___cotton_gin_waste--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018383/2018383_10701724_1703970701492_image_2___cotton_gin_waste--rgov-800width.png" title="Typical cotton gin waste"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018383/2018383_10701724_1703970701492_image_2___cotton_gin_waste--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Typical cotton gin waste"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A typical sample of cotton gin waste with a mixture of unrecovered cotton fiber, dried bowls, stalks, and occasional seeds</div> <div class="imageCredit">Saman Aria, Nathan Howell</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Nathan&nbsp;Howell <div class="imageTitle">Typical cotton gin waste</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  West Texas A&M University (WTAMU) along with partner institution Amarillo College (AC, community college) was awarded a grant to purchase a Micromeritics 3Flex surface analyzer. Purchasing this instrument for WTAMU meant that the we would add it to a common research space at the university where several other common use instruments are housed, the Engineering Core Laboratory (ECORE). We had four goals for the project.   Goal 1-Transformative, cross-disciplinary research in the fields of engineering, chemistry, and atmospheric science. There was cross-disciplinary research which we were able to achieve during the three-year project life in two main fieldsatmospheric science and environmental engineering.   The first project concerned atmospheric ice-nucleating particles (INPs) which are particles made from mineral dust and non-proteinaceous biological (e.g., plant fiber) sources that can influence cloud formation, precipitation, and Earths radiation budget due to their efficient freezing abilities. The characterization of INPs and aerosol particles from these sources is important. We typically characterize their specific surface area (SSA), which is the primary variable to estimate their ice-nucleation active surface site density, using a sorbate gas. However, it is still uncertain how these particles interact with water vapor under subzero temperatures. Thus, we used the 3Flex instrument with multiple sorbates. Our results indicate that the SSA of illite NX (a mineral dust proxy) is less temperature-dependent compared to cellulose materials. Therefore, illite NX may be suitable as a proxy. A second series concerned determination of the surface area of North Slope of Alaska (NSA) soils. These soils exhibited different surface properties  some possess high SSA with mesopores while some materials come with low SSA with micropores. We find that understanding total sorption properties via temperature-dependent water sorption could be key in understanding the physics of atmospheric ice nucleation on insoluble aerosol particles.   A second project concerned the evaluation of adsorbent biochar made from cotton gin waste (CGW). Our interest in biochar made from CGW is to convert a low value material into something of higher value which can be used to amend soils. We examined the quality of biochar that could be made from CGW (16 unique samples created). We used the 3Flex to examine the microporosity of biochar and its affinity for water vapor. We found that higher temperature always increases microporosity and that water adsorption in biochar is not precisely consistent with production conditions. It will be valuable for other researchers and farmers to know how to optimize these parameters for any large-scale field use.   Goal 2 - Use of instrument to target Hispanic and female students. This goal concerned the inclusion of the 3Flex tool in the ECORE to encourage Hispanic and female students for growth and interest in STEM fields. From all student researchers, an external evaluation finds that 58.3% of them were from under-represented minorities (URM) and 62.5% which were female. In addition, our group conducted an on campus to survey 443 students (out of 658 solicited) from 18 unique course offerings over the three years of the project to examine Hispanic student factors for college choice. Important findings from the survey are that Hispanic students consider the following factors more than their non-Hispanic peers --commuting distance, scholarships and financial aid, encouragement from parents, and the university having Hispanic Serving Institution (HSI) status.   Goal 3 - Attracting researchers from outside of West Texas A&M University (WTAMU). This instrument is very unique for the rural region which is the Texas Panhandle. One must ravel 200+ miles to access the next nearest similar tool. We therefore, sought to use this tool as a means to attract others outside of our typical research networks. We were able to attract a local lab manager from an electrical generating utility, researchers from the Department of Energy Environmental Molecular Sciences Laboratory (EMSL) for soil sample examinations, researchers from Texas A&M University-College Station for confirmatory analysis of a nanodiamond powder, and USDA-ARS researcher leaders in Bushland, TX for agricultural greenhouse gas reductions.   Goal 4 - Training graduates and undergraduates through increased interaction in the WTAMU Engineering Core Laboratory (ECORE). Many modern instruments are difficult to purchase and require years of experience to use. Thus, we used the 3Flex to get students exposed to the tool. Some merely learned about the concepts of measurement. At the other extreme, graduate students and one post-doc were able to run the instrument independently. We were able to have an undergraduate reach which was 120 student per year. These interactions occurred through lab tours, educational content, and students analyzing their own samples directly. The graduate student reach was about 10 per year. While we find these interactions to be significant, the instrument, which of course will be maintained and used for at least 10-20 more years, will need to be incorporated into more courses as a way to expose more students to surface analysis.        Last Modified: 12/30/2023       Submitted by: NathanHowell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
