<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI:  Acquisition of a Raman Imaging Microscope at Western Washington University]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>295160.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>295160</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tanya Whitmer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>twhitmer@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922912</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is supported by the Major Research Instrumentation and the Chemistry Research Instrumentation programs. Western Washington University is acquiring a Raman imaging microscope to support Professor Steven Emory and colleagues: Sean Mulcahy, David Rider, Ying Bao and Manuel Montaño. This spectrometer allows research in a variety of fields of significant economic importance. In general, a Raman microscope begins with a standard optical microscope but then uses a laser to scan the surface of a sample to implement a chemical image over the entire field of view. The laser wavelengths probe the surface and produce a spectrum which identifies chemical components in the material. This analysis gives useful information on the properties of the material. This is a powerful analytical tool for identifying chemical composition qualitatively and semi-quantitatively. The microscope is being used in a number of important research areas and is an integral part of teaching as well as research and research training of undergraduate students both at this institution and at nearby universities such as Whatcom Community College and Pacific Lutheran University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award of the Raman microscope is aimed at enhancing research and education at all levels. The instrument acquisition impacts studies of polymer-nanoparticle composites for energy and catalysis applications and the use of earth-abundant photocatalysts for solar fuels. The instrumentation is used for exploring the utilization of organic crystals for electronic nanodevices and in applications of zinc oxide films in energy-related processes. In addition, the Raman Microscope provides information for employing nanomaterials for surface-enhanced detection and imaging as well as in making plasmonic gold nanorod and nanowire sensors. The microscope is used to study polymeric materials for potential biomedical applications and quantifying nanomaterials in the environment. The instrument is also employed in studies of deformation conditions of ancient subduction zones and in evaluating the toxicology of environmental microplastics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019208</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ying</FirstName>
<LastName>Bao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ying Bao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ying.bao@wwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000796241</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Rider</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David A Rider</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[david.rider@wwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000602117</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sean</FirstName>
<LastName>Mulcahy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sean R Mulcahy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sean.mulcahy@wwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000536349</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Emory</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven R Emory</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[semory@chem.wwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000451579</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Manuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Montano</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Manuel D Montano</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[manuel.montano@wwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819190</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Western Washington University</Name>
<CityName>BELLINGHAM</CityName>
<ZipCode>982255946</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3606502884</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>516 HIGH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U3ZFA57417D4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>U3ZFA57417D4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Western Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bellingham</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>982255946</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[516 High Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8607</Code>
<Text>Solar Energy Capture&amp;Conver</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~295160</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Western Washington University (WWU), a primarily undergraduate institution, acquired a Raman imaging microscope to support its scientific research and training programs.&nbsp; Raman spectroscopy is a powerful optical characterization tool that enables the identification of molecules based on their vibrational spectra.&nbsp; The microscope is now a centerpiece of a new Microimaging Laboratory (MIL) on the WWU campus.&nbsp; This facility houses advanced imaging tools such as an atomic force microscope and a fluorescence confocal microscope that were supported by other NSF grants.</p> <p>Scientific research by faculty and students is a cornerstone of science education, and thus the proposed Raman microscope has made an immediate impact on the training and education of students.&nbsp; During the grant period, 12 faculty and 35 student researchers were trained to independently operate the microscope.&nbsp; Thus far, this has resulted in one peer-reviewed publication, four master&rsquo;s theses, and 22 conference presentations.&nbsp; In addition, over 150 undergraduate students have utilized the Raman microscope in lab courses as part of their undergraduate education.&nbsp; This has enhanced the research opportunities and experiences of undergraduate students by exposing them to state-of-the-art research equipment.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>The Raman microscope directly supports the research programs of faculty in a range of disciplines including Chemistry, Energy, Engineering &amp; Design, Environmental Science, Geology, and Materials Science.&nbsp; The chemical imaging capabilities of the microscope were used to advance an array of projects including:&nbsp; 1) Identification of Environmental Micro- &amp; Nano-Plastics, 2) Synthesis &amp; Characterization of Metallic Nanomaterials on Silk Films for Biological Applications, 3) Investigation of Photothermal Catalysts for CO2-Derived Solar Fuels, 4) Investigation of Snow Algae Diversity &amp; Its Impact on Snowmelt, and 5) Temperature Conditions for the Formation of Metamorphic Belts.</p> <p>Faculty-mentored student research, especially at the undergraduate level, is a major component of the WWU experience.&nbsp; The Raman microscope provides mentoring opportunities and contributes to collaborative curricular and research efforts across a range of scientific disciplines on and off campus.&nbsp; This has enhanced the education of our highly accomplished students, many of whom go on to graduate school, industrial positions, or other professional degree programs.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/22/2023<br> Modified by: Steven&nbsp;R&nbsp;Emory</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2019208/2019208_10688006_1700677518365_Snow_Algae--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2019208/2019208_10688006_1700677518365_Snow_Algae--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Images and Raman Spectra from Snow Algae"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2019208/2019208_10688006_1700677518365_Snow_Algae--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Images and Raman Spectra from Snow Algae"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Raman Spectra Acquired from Three Different Snow Alga Shown.  Differences in carotenoids and chlorophyll are highlighted.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Manuel Montano</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;R&nbsp;Emory <div class="imageTitle">Images and Raman Spectra from Snow Algae</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2019208/2019208_10688006_1700682604699_Raman_from_Silver_Nanocubes--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2019208/2019208_10688006_1700682604699_Raman_from_Silver_Nanocubes--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Silver Nanocube Raman Spectra"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2019208/2019208_10688006_1700682604699_Raman_from_Silver_Nanocubes--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Silver Nanocube Raman Spectra"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Surface-Enhanced Raman Scattering Spectra Obtained from 4-Mercaptobenzoic Acid (4-MBA) on Silver Nanocubes.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ying Bao</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;R&nbsp;Emory <div class="imageTitle">Silver Nanocube Raman Spectra</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2019208/2019208_10688006_1700677111600_Nanoplastic_Raman_Image--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2019208/2019208_10688006_1700677111600_Nanoplastic_Raman_Image--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Polystyrene Raman Spectra and Image"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2019208/2019208_10688006_1700677111600_Nanoplastic_Raman_Image--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Polystyrene Raman Spectra and Image"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Raman Imaging of Polystyrene Nanoplastic Particles.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven Emory</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;R&nbsp;Emory <div class="imageTitle">Polystyrene Raman Spectra and Image</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Western Washington University (WWU), a primarily undergraduate institution, acquired a Raman imaging microscope to support its scientific research and training programs. Raman spectroscopy is a powerful optical characterization tool that enables the identification of molecules based on their vibrational spectra. The microscope is now a centerpiece of a new Microimaging Laboratory (MIL) on the WWU campus. This facility houses advanced imaging tools such as an atomic force microscope and a fluorescence confocal microscope that were supported by other NSF grants.   Scientific research by faculty and students is a cornerstone of science education, and thus the proposed Raman microscope has made an immediate impact on the training and education of students. During the grant period, 12 faculty and 35 student researchers were trained to independently operate the microscope. Thus far, this has resulted in one peer-reviewed publication, four masters theses, and 22 conference presentations. In addition, over 150 undergraduate students have utilized the Raman microscope in lab courses as part of their undergraduate education. This has enhanced the research opportunities and experiences of undergraduate students by exposing them to state-of-the-art research equipment.    The Raman microscope directly supports the research programs of faculty in a range of disciplines including Chemistry, Energy, Engineering & Design, Environmental Science, Geology, and Materials Science. The chemical imaging capabilities of the microscope were used to advance an array of projects including: 1) Identification of Environmental Micro- & Nano-Plastics, 2) Synthesis & Characterization of Metallic Nanomaterials on Silk Films for Biological Applications, 3) Investigation of Photothermal Catalysts for CO2-Derived Solar Fuels, 4) Investigation of Snow Algae Diversity & Its Impact on Snowmelt, and 5) Temperature Conditions for the Formation of Metamorphic Belts.   Faculty-mentored student research, especially at the undergraduate level, is a major component of the WWU experience. The Raman microscope provides mentoring opportunities and contributes to collaborative curricular and research efforts across a range of scientific disciplines on and off campus. This has enhanced the education of our highly accomplished students, many of whom go on to graduate school, industrial positions, or other professional degree programs.     Last Modified: 11/22/2023       Submitted by: StevenREmory]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
