<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Scholars: Affective Economies in Crowdfunding for Cancer]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>145801.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>145801</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christine Leuenberger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cleuenbe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927563</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Crowdfunding is a form of alternative finance wherein individuals appeal for small donations via a third-party online platform. Originally intended to help artists and entrepreneurs fund creative projects, U.S. crowdfunding economies are now dominated by campaigns to help patients and their families afford health care costs. Of the 250 million new campaigns launched annually to offset costs related to medical treatment, almost half are fundraisers for individuals diagnosed with cancer. While some crowdfunding appeals inspire the sympathy and support of a large public, most fail to widely circulate or raise significant sums. The median crowdfunding campaign for a cancer patient receives just 25% of its funding target. Crowdfunding for cancer thus represents an increasingly important but understudied phenomenon. This project investigates the social dynamics shaping this new form of micro-philanthropy by researching how and why donors’ sentiments and emotions motivate giving in some crowdfunding campaigns but not in others, creating significant disparities among cancer patients. It also explores how crowdfunding impacts cancer patients, and the ways in which the fundraising process reshapes the experience of being ill. Project outcomes will contribute to a broader understanding of how the growth of crowdfunding is shifting cultural perceptions regarding health care, the meaning of illness, and the rights and social roles of the sick.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study draws data from participant observations, ethnographic interviewing, and focus group interviews with cancer patients, donors to crowdfunding campaigns, social workers and patient navigators, and employees of crowdfunding corporations. It has three main objectives: (1) To investigate how crowdfunding exchanges are informed by the digital interfaces and online environments where campaigns are created and circulated; (2) To inquire into how the experience of illness is reshaped by the experience of crowdfunding; and (3) To investigate how crowdfunding campaigns affect cancer patients’ access to health care. This will provide new insights in two domains relevant to public interest and national policy debates. First, it sheds light on the understudied impacts of new digital platforms on society and culture. Second, it develops new knowledge regarding the predicaments that increasing health care costs create for sick and disabled Americans. This project contributes to Science and Technology Studies by advancing scholarship on technological transformations and their unintended consequences. It contributes to Anthropology by developing new insights regarding the impacts of cultural practices on the experience of illness, health outcomes, and health disparities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021152</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martha</FirstName>
<LastName>Lincoln</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martha Lincoln</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mlincoln@sfsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000553188</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Francisco State University</Name>
<CityName>SAN FRANCISCO</CityName>
<ZipCode>941321722</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4153387090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1600 HOLLOWAY AVE BUILDING NAD R</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F4SLJ5WF59F6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN FRANCISCO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Francisco State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>941321722</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>124Y</Code>
<Text>Science &amp; Technology Studies</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~145801</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&ldquo;Affective Economies in Crowdfunding for Cancer&rdquo; (#2021152) was a study of the emotional dynamics that play a role in online crowdfunding practices by cancer patients and survivors in the United States. The data collection and expenditure of NSF funds were completed in 2023, following two no-cost extensions owing to the impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic. The PI is very appreciative of the Science and Technology Studies Program of the National Science Foundation&rsquo;s support for this work.</p> <p>Select specific findings of the study include the following:</p> <ul> <li>Non-white study participants reported feeling pressure to document their illness meticulously in crowdfunding campaigns, owing to the suspicion or lack of sympathy that they anticipate in response to a public appeal for assistance.</li> <li>Study respondents with more advanced cancer, or with challenging transitions to survivorship, noted a poor match between the temporality of their illness and the temporality of an online fundraising campaign.</li> <li>Individuals diagnosed with cancer consistently report ambivalence about using crowdfunding platforms as a means of temporary or more long-term financial assistance&mdash;both acknowledging the meaning and value of receiving community support and expressing anxiety and discomfort about the dependency and possible social &ldquo;burden&rdquo; that such requests entail.</li> </ul> <p>Select specific outcomes of the project over its lifetime include the following:</p> <ul> <li>Recruiting of study participants. Study participants included individuals diagnosed with cancer who were using crowdfunding to afford their care; the family members and caregivers of cancer patients and survivors; individuals who had donated to crowdfunding campaigns by cancer patients and survivors; social workers and other professionals providing direct services to cancer patients and survivors.</li> <li>Semi-structured ethnographic interviews were recorded with 40 demographically diverse study participants, all of whom provided informed consent and received compensation in thanks for their time. This number of participants met the study team&rsquo;s goal for data collection.</li> <li>All interview data were cleaned, coded, and analyzed.</li> <li>Research literature and other relevant source materials were retrieved and reviewed.</li> <li>Study hypotheses were tested and refined.</li> <li>Presentation and workshopping of study findings took place at multiple interdisciplinary professional conferences over the funded study period, including:   <ul> <li>The annual conference of the Society for Applied Anthropology in March 2021</li> </ul> <ul> <li>&nbsp;The annual conference of the&nbsp;Society for the Social Studies of Science in October 2021 (NB, PI also organized a session, &ldquo;Caring Economies&rdquo;)</li> </ul> <ul> <li>The annual conference of the American Anthropological Association in November 2021</li> <li>The annual conference of the American Anthropological Association in November 2022 (NB, PI also co-organized a session, &ldquo;Unsettling Carescapes&rdquo;).</li> </ul> </li> <li>NSF funding was acknowledged on all occasions where study data were shared.</li> <li>A San Francisco State University Anthropology M.A. student was hired and trained as a Graduate Assistant, completing literature reviews, study participant recruting, data cleaning, qualitative coding, and co-authorship. In Fall 2023, the Graduate Assistant matriculated at a Ph.D. program to continue her training as a researcher in the social sciences.</li> <li>The write-up of major study findings in a peer-reviewed article, now under review (details below) and in draft articles to be submitted (including public-facing opinion essays to accompany the publication of study findings in scholarly journals).&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>In 2023, the Principal Investigator also received a fellowship from the Ann Johnson Institute for Science and Technology Studies at the University of South Carolina that allowed a week-long writing retreat for the finalization of a publication drawing on these study data. The retreat took place in June 2023 and permitted professional networking with other scholars pursuing research on the topic of "Medicine, Technology, and Marginalized Populations."</p> <p>In summer 2023, the Principal Investigator and Graduate Assistant completed a 9,000-word co-authored article titled &ldquo;Affective Economies in Crowdfunding for Cancer&rdquo; presenting major findings from this study. The article was desk-rejected for fit concerns by <em>Social Studies of Science </em>and <em>Social Science &amp; Medicine</em>,<em> </em>then submitted to the peer-reviewed journal <em>Medical Anthropology Quarterly</em> in September 2023. Constructive peer comments and an invitation to revise and resubmit the article were received from the editor-in-chief of <em>MAQ </em>on November 14, 2023, and the PI and Graduate Assistant submitted a revision on January 2, 2024.</p> <p>The Principal Investigator also completed an article for the Anthropology desk of Oxford Bibliographies on the topic &ldquo;Cancer.&rdquo; The article has now been peer-reviewed and resubmitted, and a final set of review comments from the Editor-in-Chief was received by the PI on December 19, 2023. The finalized article will be resubmitted by the PI no later than March 1, 2024.</p> <p>In addition to these two nearly finalized study products, further peer-reviewed, editor-reviewed, and public-facing publications will be forthcoming from the study. As data collection is now complete, study materials such as interview schedules and codebooks, as well as de-identified study data (including interview transcripts, field notes, and web materials), will be deposited at the Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research (ICPSR) at the University of Michigan (icpsr.umich.edu).</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 01/02/2024<br> Modified by: Martha&nbsp;Lincoln</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Affective Economies in Crowdfunding for Cancer (#2021152) was a study of the emotional dynamics that play a role in online crowdfunding practices by cancer patients and survivors in the United States. The data collection and expenditure of NSF funds were completed in 2023, following two no-cost extensions owing to the impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic. The PI is very appreciative of the Science and Technology Studies Program of the National Science Foundations support for this work.   Select specific findings of the study include the following:  Non-white study participants reported feeling pressure to document their illness meticulously in crowdfunding campaigns, owing to the suspicion or lack of sympathy that they anticipate in response to a public appeal for assistance. Study respondents with more advanced cancer, or with challenging transitions to survivorship, noted a poor match between the temporality of their illness and the temporality of an online fundraising campaign. Individuals diagnosed with cancer consistently report ambivalence about using crowdfunding platforms as a means of temporary or more long-term financial assistanceboth acknowledging the meaning and value of receiving community support and expressing anxiety and discomfort about the dependency and possible social burden that such requests entail.    Select specific outcomes of the project over its lifetime include the following:  Recruiting of study participants. Study participants included individuals diagnosed with cancer who were using crowdfunding to afford their care; the family members and caregivers of cancer patients and survivors; individuals who had donated to crowdfunding campaigns by cancer patients and survivors; social workers and other professionals providing direct services to cancer patients and survivors. Semi-structured ethnographic interviews were recorded with 40 demographically diverse study participants, all of whom provided informed consent and received compensation in thanks for their time. This number of participants met the study teams goal for data collection. All interview data were cleaned, coded, and analyzed. Research literature and other relevant source materials were retrieved and reviewed. Study hypotheses were tested and refined. Presentation and workshopping of study findings took place at multiple interdisciplinary professional conferences over the funded study period, including:    The annual conference of the Society for Applied Anthropology in March 2021   The annual conference of theSociety for the Social Studies of Science in October 2021 (NB, PI also organized a session, Caring Economies)   The annual conference of the American Anthropological Association in November 2021 The annual conference of the American Anthropological Association in November 2022 (NB, PI also co-organized a session, Unsettling Carescapes).   NSF funding was acknowledged on all occasions where study data were shared. A San Francisco State University Anthropology M.A. student was hired and trained as a Graduate Assistant, completing literature reviews, study participant recruting, data cleaning, qualitative coding, and co-authorship. In Fall 2023, the Graduate Assistant matriculated at a Ph.D. program to continue her training as a researcher in the social sciences. The write-up of major study findings in a peer-reviewed article, now under review (details below) and in draft articles to be submitted (including public-facing opinion essays to accompany the publication of study findings in scholarly journals).    In 2023, the Principal Investigator also received a fellowship from the Ann Johnson Institute for Science and Technology Studies at the University of South Carolina that allowed a week-long writing retreat for the finalization of a publication drawing on these study data. The retreat took place in June 2023 and permitted professional networking with other scholars pursuing research on the topic of "Medicine, Technology, and Marginalized Populations."   In summer 2023, the Principal Investigator and Graduate Assistant completed a 9,000-word co-authored article titled Affective Economies in Crowdfunding for Cancer presenting major findings from this study. The article was desk-rejected for fit concerns by Social Studies of Science and Social Science & Medicine, then submitted to the peer-reviewed journal Medical Anthropology Quarterly in September 2023. Constructive peer comments and an invitation to revise and resubmit the article were received from the editor-in-chief of MAQ on November 14, 2023, and the PI and Graduate Assistant submitted a revision on January 2, 2024.   The Principal Investigator also completed an article for the Anthropology desk of Oxford Bibliographies on the topic Cancer. The article has now been peer-reviewed and resubmitted, and a final set of review comments from the Editor-in-Chief was received by the PI on December 19, 2023. The finalized article will be resubmitted by the PI no later than March 1, 2024.   In addition to these two nearly finalized study products, further peer-reviewed, editor-reviewed, and public-facing publications will be forthcoming from the study. As data collection is now complete, study materials such as interview schedules and codebooks, as well as de-identified study data (including interview transcripts, field notes, and web materials), will be deposited at the Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research (ICPSR) at the University of Michigan (icpsr.umich.edu).     Last Modified: 01/02/2024       Submitted by: MarthaLincoln]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
