<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Undergraduate Research in a Fully Online Engineering Program: Effects on Retention, Persistence, Performance, STEM attitudes and Identity]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>295966.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>295966</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Abby Ilumoka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ailumoka@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922703</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project aims to serve the national interest by developing a framework for providing undergraduate research opportunities to students enrolled in online STEM programs. Specifically, the research team will design and test the impact of undergraduate research experiences for students in an online engineering program at Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University. The acute, longstanding need for increased numbers of well-prepared STEM graduates has driven the proliferation of online degree programs in undergraduate engineering and technology. These distance-learning programs have the potential to increase accessibility of STEM programs to diverse students, and thus support the growing demand for graduates with STEM skills. However, many online programs have low retention and graduation rates. The value of undergraduate research experiences for supporting student persistence and success is well documented for in-person learners.  The goal of this project is to provide online students with undergraduate research experiences, anticipating that the experiences will have similar effects for online learners.  To do so, it will develop a tailored framework that features broad research topics, increases student disciplinary knowledge and skills, and provides key supports to improve students’ academic performance, persistence, and graduation. It is expected that these outcomes will correlate with positive impacts of research experiences on the students’ attitudes toward STEM and STEM identity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will design, implement, and test an undergraduate research pilot program within an online engineering program at the University. Project activities include the creation of a research-oriented workshop series, addition of an elective research track, and specialized mentoring of the research students.  The project will conduct a mixed-methods research study to investigate the effectiveness of the framework, the impact of the framework on students’ STEM identity and attitude toward STEM, and other research questions. The key deliverable will be a sharable, customizable, scalable framework for providing research experiences in online courses and degree programs. It is expected that the work will produce insights about online student participation, a key area of research given the COVID-19-induced pivot to online learning. It is possible that this project can debunk stereotypes about the feasibility of incorporating undergraduate research and supporting development of a strong STEM identity in distance learning environments. This project is supported by the NSF IUSE: EHR Program, which supports research and development projects to improve the effectiveness of STEM education for all students. Through the Engaged Student Learning track, the program supports the creation, exploration, and implementation of promising practices and tools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021221</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Deters</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert W Deters</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[detersr1@erau.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000820758</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Faulconer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily K Faulconer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[faulcone@erau.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000800147</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brent</FirstName>
<LastName>Terwilliger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brent A Terwilliger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[terwillb@erau.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000689063</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University</Name>
<CityName>DAYTONA BEACH</CityName>
<ZipCode>321143910</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3862267695</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 AEROSPACE BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U5MMBAC9XAM5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EMBRY-RIDDLE AERONAUTICAL UNIVERSITY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University]]></Name>
<CityName>Daytona Beach</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>321143910</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Aerospace Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8244</Code>
<Text>EHR CL Opportunities (NSF 14-302)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~295966</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was implemented at Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University&rsquo;s Worldwide Campus from October 2020 to September 2023, focusing on enhancing undergraduate research opportunities for fully online engineering students. The project progressed through development, launch, and awareness-building phases, implementing the Worldwide Research Scholar Program with Research Skills Workshops, Research Mentoring, and curricular options. The goals of the project were to 1) increase engineering program persistence for fully online students, 2) improve retention, 3) increase academic performance, 4) positively influence STEM identity and attitudes, and 5) improve transferable skills through research engagement.</p> <p><strong>Enhancing Student Research Capacity and Opportunity </strong></p> <p>While initially proposed for online engineering students, the scope widened to include broad STEM participation due to recruitment challenges and research interest across disciplines. A survey of the distance student population revealed that nearly 75% had not engaged in research, yet the same percentage was interested in research, though noted barriers were time, costs, and knowing who to contact and where to start. This information was foundational in creating the framework of support.</p> <p><strong><em>Mentoring. </em></strong>We established the COMPASS Research Mentoring program, supporting 34 research mentees (30 undergraduate, 4 graduate) between August 2021 and September 2023. An interview evaluating the program showed mentee growth in time management, collaboration, communication, and information evaluation skills (Objective 5). They reported improved self-confidence, a stronger sense of belonging, and enhanced motivation (Objective 4). Notably, one student shared their redirected career path as a significant outcome of their research mentorship experience. Mentees reported development particularly in research ethics. When asked how mentoring affected confidence to succeed in advanced coursework (Objective 1), responses noted professional development, learning community, and continuous growth. Mentees shared how research mentorship affected their confidence in completing degree requirements at ERAU (Objective 2), noting learning community and professional development.</p> <p>In a survey, mentees reported their mentors demonstrated strong mentoring competencies in all areas (maintaining effective communication, aligning expectations, assessing understanding, fostering independence, addressing diversity, and promoting professional development), with mentees tending to rate mentor competencies higher than the mentors self-rated.</p> <p><strong><em>Workshops. </em></strong>Fourteen Research Skills Workshops supported students in early research experiences, bridging to research, active research, and research culmination, archived online through an open educational resource (OER) collection. Impact of workshops will be explored in future work.</p> <p><strong><em>Research Experiences. </em></strong>Two students completed the research independent study (RSCH 295), with successfully dissemination a clear indicator of proficiency of the research learning objectives (Objective 3). Research-related skills can be transferable to other coursework and career applications (Objective 5). Flexibility in degree programs or funding sources limited engagement in curricular options. However, seven students met the criteria in the program to be awarded a stipend for their research involvement. This result highlights the project&rsquo;s success in fostering student participation and commitment.</p> <p><strong><em>Affective Characteristics. </em></strong>STEM identity and attitudes of students engaged in research was evaluated (Objective 4), revealing that engaging in research positively influenced STEM identity.</p> <p><strong><em>Recognition. </em></strong>One student earned the Research Scholars Certificate upon graduation. It is anticipated more students will achieve this recognition over time as they approach graduation. Undergraduate researchers published 2 papers (with more under review), gave 5 conference presentations, and engaged in high-level stakeholder communication, traveling to the U.S. capitol to present to lawmakers. Furthermore, undergraduate students engaged in a research competition. Graduate students also used the framework and engaged in traditional and strategic dissemination.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p><strong><em>Transferability. </em></strong>Engagement of non-BSET/ technical STEM students suggested potential applicability to other STEM-related programs. Through robust advertising and outreach efforts, 3,563 students were reached. Key findings were made appropriately public, highlighting actions most likely to improve student learning, persistence, retention, and perspectives, accomplished through open dissemination of a Research Summary Document (RSD).</p> <p><strong><em>Dissemination. </em></strong>Despite recruiting challenges in the intended student population, a pivot to an expanded STEM population led to successful extraction of key findings. The insights were made publicly accessible through external dissemination. The following are results of this project: 3 manuscripts, 1 OER collection, 4 conference presentations, 1 editorial, 6 stakeholder communications, and 1 RSD.</p> <p>Undergraduate researchers disseminated their work to disciplinary communities through conferences, peer-reviewed journal publication, and strategic dissemination efforts, emphasizing the significance of their work and contributing to the broader impact of the project on the academic community. At the time of this report, 17% of undergraduate research mentees submitted work for publication in a peer-reviewed journal.</p> <p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p> <p>This project leveraged acquired knowledge to create and examine a comprehensive and adaptable framework for supporting undergraduate research in online STEM degrees. The Worldwide Research Scholars program, initially developed for a single engineering program, extended its benefits to the entire campus, reaching beyond the intended population as broad interest among students from various disciplines was discovered. The outcomes have not only altered expectations for distance students at the examined institution but have also led to an aspiration to challenge stereotypes about online education across different institutions.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/20/2023<br> Modified by: Emily&nbsp;K&nbsp;Faulconer</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This project was implemented at Embry-Riddle Aeronautical Universitys Worldwide Campus from October 2020 to September 2023, focusing on enhancing undergraduate research opportunities for fully online engineering students. The project progressed through development, launch, and awareness-building phases, implementing the Worldwide Research Scholar Program with Research Skills Workshops, Research Mentoring, and curricular options. The goals of the project were to 1) increase engineering program persistence for fully online students, 2) improve retention, 3) increase academic performance, 4) positively influence STEM identity and attitudes, and 5) improve transferable skills through research engagement.   Enhancing Student Research Capacity and Opportunity    While initially proposed for online engineering students, the scope widened to include broad STEM participation due to recruitment challenges and research interest across disciplines. A survey of the distance student population revealed that nearly 75% had not engaged in research, yet the same percentage was interested in research, though noted barriers were time, costs, and knowing who to contact and where to start. This information was foundational in creating the framework of support.   Mentoring. We established the COMPASS Research Mentoring program, supporting 34 research mentees (30 undergraduate, 4 graduate) between August 2021 and September 2023. An interview evaluating the program showed mentee growth in time management, collaboration, communication, and information evaluation skills (Objective 5). They reported improved self-confidence, a stronger sense of belonging, and enhanced motivation (Objective 4). Notably, one student shared their redirected career path as a significant outcome of their research mentorship experience. Mentees reported development particularly in research ethics. When asked how mentoring affected confidence to succeed in advanced coursework (Objective 1), responses noted professional development, learning community, and continuous growth. Mentees shared how research mentorship affected their confidence in completing degree requirements at ERAU (Objective 2), noting learning community and professional development.   In a survey, mentees reported their mentors demonstrated strong mentoring competencies in all areas (maintaining effective communication, aligning expectations, assessing understanding, fostering independence, addressing diversity, and promoting professional development), with mentees tending to rate mentor competencies higher than the mentors self-rated.   Workshops. Fourteen Research Skills Workshops supported students in early research experiences, bridging to research, active research, and research culmination, archived online through an open educational resource (OER) collection. Impact of workshops will be explored in future work.   Research Experiences. Two students completed the research independent study (RSCH 295), with successfully dissemination a clear indicator of proficiency of the research learning objectives (Objective 3). Research-related skills can be transferable to other coursework and career applications (Objective 5). Flexibility in degree programs or funding sources limited engagement in curricular options. However, seven students met the criteria in the program to be awarded a stipend for their research involvement. This result highlights the projects success in fostering student participation and commitment.   Affective Characteristics. STEM identity and attitudes of students engaged in research was evaluated (Objective 4), revealing that engaging in research positively influenced STEM identity.   Recognition. One student earned the Research Scholars Certificate upon graduation. It is anticipated more students will achieve this recognition over time as they approach graduation. Undergraduate researchers published 2 papers (with more under review), gave 5 conference presentations, and engaged in high-level stakeholder communication, traveling to the U.S. capitol to present to lawmakers. Furthermore, undergraduate students engaged in a research competition. Graduate students also used the framework and engaged in traditional and strategic dissemination.   Broader Impacts   Transferability. Engagement of non-BSET/ technical STEM students suggested potential applicability to other STEM-related programs. Through robust advertising and outreach efforts, 3,563 students were reached. Key findings were made appropriately public, highlighting actions most likely to improve student learning, persistence, retention, and perspectives, accomplished through open dissemination of a Research Summary Document (RSD).   Dissemination. Despite recruiting challenges in the intended student population, a pivot to an expanded STEM population led to successful extraction of key findings. The insights were made publicly accessible through external dissemination. The following are results of this project: 3 manuscripts, 1 OER collection, 4 conference presentations, 1 editorial, 6 stakeholder communications, and 1 RSD.   Undergraduate researchers disseminated their work to disciplinary communities through conferences, peer-reviewed journal publication, and strategic dissemination efforts, emphasizing the significance of their work and contributing to the broader impact of the project on the academic community. At the time of this report, 17% of undergraduate research mentees submitted work for publication in a peer-reviewed journal.   Conclusion   This project leveraged acquired knowledge to create and examine a comprehensive and adaptable framework for supporting undergraduate research in online STEM degrees. The Worldwide Research Scholars program, initially developed for a single engineering program, extended its benefits to the entire campus, reaching beyond the intended population as broad interest among students from various disciplines was discovered. The outcomes have not only altered expectations for distance students at the examined institution but have also led to an aspiration to challenge stereotypes about online education across different institutions.     Last Modified: 12/20/2023       Submitted by: EmilyKFaulconer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
