<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Assessing Transformative Justice]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>210246.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249663</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reginald Sheehan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsheehan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925389</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Title: Assessing Transformative Justice&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract: &lt;br/&gt;While transformative justice takes many forms, there is scant scholarly knowledge, whether theoretical or empirical, on the efficacy of these measures that may be employed during transitions from conflict to peace. This project will collect community-generated indicators of justice, recognition, and reconciliation in order to establish reparative impact. The goal is to examine the outcomes of transformative justice and derive a measurement for the efficacy of steps taken by states.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Employing a mixed-method approach, including focus groups, survey research, and an experimental design, this research will be based in various theories from law, political science, and international relations, in order to develop new theory on the role of reparative mechanisms and on the limits of transformative justice. The project will provide innovative consultation, assessment, and learning tools for measuring amends in terms of recognition, justice and reconciliation. The case studies of Colombia and the Democratic Republic of the Congo will be utilized due to their extensive reparations programs. Focus groups will be used to collect community-generated indicators followed by survey research methods to measure changes in perception and impact over time. Findings will advance scientific discovery and understanding of the ideas behind transformative justice.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021634</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Dixon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter Dixon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pdixon@brandeis.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000847627</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/19/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pamina</FirstName>
<LastName>Firchow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pamina M Firchow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pfirchow@brandeis.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000768287</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brandeis University]]></Name>
<CityName>WALTHAM</CityName>
<ZipCode>024532728</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7817362121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[415 SOUTH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MXLZGAMFEKN5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BRANDEIS UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brandeis University]]></Name>
<CityName>Waltham</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024532728</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[415 South St Mailstop 116]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128Y</Code>
<Text>Law &amp; Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LSS-Law And Social Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~30661</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~82300</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~97285</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~39417</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p id="docs-internal-guid-72aed344-7fff-b5fb-12b9-032fca20cf7b" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 12pt; margin-bottom: 12pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 10.5pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #333333; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The &ldquo;Everyday Justice&rdquo; Project supported a broad array of fieldwork in Antioquia, Colombia in two municipalities impacted by the country&rsquo;s internal armed conflict: Dabeiba and Urrao. The municipalities experienced similar levels of violence, but only one, Dabeiba, has benefited from Colombia&rsquo;s wide ranging set of peace and justice institutions, several of which were created as part of the 2016 peace deal between the Government of Colombia and the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia - People&rsquo;s Army (FARC). Drawing on focus groups, participatory workshops and interviews, we derived a unique database of 487 indicators of coexistence and 366 indicators of justice across eight villages in these two municipalities. The indicators speak to the breadth and depth of everyday experiences and understandings of conflict, coexistence and justice&ndash;and help highlight both the alignments and gaps between national and local visions of peace.</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 12pt; margin-bottom: 12pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 10.5pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #333333; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">This project was part of a larger effort to understand how diverse communities of Colombians understand peace on their own terms across diverse regions, in addition to Antioquia we worked in the Department of Northern Cauca and the region of Sumapaz. Like in Antioquia, we worked in municipalities in these regions with similar histories of armed conflict but divergent experiences of Colombia&rsquo;s national post-conflict response.</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 12pt; margin-bottom: 12pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 10.5pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #333333; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">We sought in this project to evaluate and inform Colombia&rsquo;s wealth of transitional justice institutions that emerged prior to and out of the 2016 Peace Accord. Using community standards the project informed activities of the Colombian Truth Commission, as well as its final report published in 2022, and continues to engage the country&rsquo;s national restorative justice court (Special Jurisdiction of Peace), as well as the follow-up Truth Commission (Comit&eacute; de Seguimiento) and the Colombian Victims Unit.</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 12pt; margin-bottom: 12pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 10.5pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #333333; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">As of 2023, the project has resulted in transitional justice related peer reviewed publications including in the </span><span style="font-size: 10.5pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #333333; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: italic; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Journal of Human Rights Practice</span><span style="font-size: 10.5pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #333333; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">, </span><span style="font-size: 10.5pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #333333; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: italic; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Action Research</span><span style="font-size: 10.5pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #333333; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"> and </span><span style="font-size: 10.5pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #333333; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: italic; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Law and Social Inquiry</span><span style="font-size: 10.5pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #333333; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">. For example, utilizing our unique dataset of &lsquo;everyday&rsquo; community-based indicators of coexistence and justice in Antioquia, we drew a distinction between &lsquo;state-led&rsquo; and &lsquo;community-led&rsquo; collective justice efforts and proposed that the latter can speak to both civilian and ex-combatant communities&rsquo; priorities and lived experiences, ultimately providing a pathway to coexistence between the two. This stands in contrast to the Colombian state&rsquo;s historic approach to collective reparations projects, which have to-date been state-led. Instead, a more community-led model of reparative justice could serve as a more pragmatic middle ground between the individual and state-led collective approaches that dominate transitional justice in Colombia and internationally.</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 12pt; margin-bottom: 12pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 10.5pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #333333; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">We have presented extensively on this work to Colombian and international audiences, alongside a dedicated team of Colombian researchers who continue to work on bottom-up peace research in the country to help guide its national post-conflict responses. We have also worked with Colombian and international organizations to train them in aspects of participatory methodologies and bottom-up measurement to support their work in ways that make peacebuilding more accountable to the communities they serve.</span></p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/12/2023<br> Modified by: Pamina&nbsp;M&nbsp;Firchow</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2021634/2021634_10580579_1702397952233_8--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2021634/2021634_10580579_1702397952233_8--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="Indicator Generation Focus Group"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2021634/2021634_10580579_1702397952233_8--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="Indicator Generation Focus Group"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An EPI Colombia Team member warms up a group of villagers as they prepare to discuss everyday indicators of coexistence and justice.</div> <div class="imageCredit">EPI Colombia Team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Pamina&nbsp;M&nbsp;Firchow <div class="imageTitle">Indicator Generation Focus Group</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2021634/2021634_10580579_1702398091154_2--rgov-214x142.JPG" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2021634/2021634_10580579_1702398091154_2--rgov-800width.JPG" title="Everyday Indicator Exhibition"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2021634/2021634_10580579_1702398091154_2--rgov-66x44.JPG" alt="Everyday Indicator Exhibition"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The village of Urrao was transformed into an exhibition of their own Everyday Indicators of Coexistence and Justice.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Edwin Cubillos</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Pamina&nbsp;M&nbsp;Firchow <div class="imageTitle">Everyday Indicator Exhibition</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2021634/2021634_10580579_1702398164099_2--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2021634/2021634_10580579_1702398164099_2--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="Indicator Lists"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2021634/2021634_10580579_1702398164099_2--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="Indicator Lists"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">EPI Colombia team members work with the community to verify and vet their final indicators of coexistence and justice.</div> <div class="imageCredit">EPI Colombia Team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Pamina&nbsp;M&nbsp;Firchow <div class="imageTitle">Indicator Lists</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The Everyday Justice Project supported a broad array of fieldwork in Antioquia, Colombia in two municipalities impacted by the countrys internal armed conflict: Dabeiba and Urrao. The municipalities experienced similar levels of violence, but only one, Dabeiba, has benefited from Colombias wide ranging set of peace and justice institutions, several of which were created as part of the 2016 peace deal between the Government of Colombia and the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia - Peoples Army (FARC). Drawing on focus groups, participatory workshops and interviews, we derived a unique database of 487 indicators of coexistence and 366 indicators of justice across eight villages in these two municipalities. The indicators speak to the breadth and depth of everyday experiences and understandings of conflict, coexistence and justiceand help highlight both the alignments and gaps between national and local visions of peace.   This project was part of a larger effort to understand how diverse communities of Colombians understand peace on their own terms across diverse regions, in addition to Antioquia we worked in the Department of Northern Cauca and the region of Sumapaz. Like in Antioquia, we worked in municipalities in these regions with similar histories of armed conflict but divergent experiences of Colombias national post-conflict response.   We sought in this project to evaluate and inform Colombias wealth of transitional justice institutions that emerged prior to and out of the 2016 Peace Accord. Using community standards the project informed activities of the Colombian Truth Commission, as well as its final report published in 2022, and continues to engage the countrys national restorative justice court (Special Jurisdiction of Peace), as well as the follow-up Truth Commission (Comit de Seguimiento) and the Colombian Victims Unit.   As of 2023, the project has resulted in transitional justice related peer reviewed publications including in the Journal of Human Rights Practice, Action Research and Law and Social Inquiry. For example, utilizing our unique dataset of everyday community-based indicators of coexistence and justice in Antioquia, we drew a distinction between state-led and community-led collective justice efforts and proposed that the latter can speak to both civilian and ex-combatant communities priorities and lived experiences, ultimately providing a pathway to coexistence between the two. This stands in contrast to the Colombian states historic approach to collective reparations projects, which have to-date been state-led. Instead, a more community-led model of reparative justice could serve as a more pragmatic middle ground between the individual and state-led collective approaches that dominate transitional justice in Colombia and internationally.   We have presented extensively on this work to Colombian and international audiences, alongside a dedicated team of Colombian researchers who continue to work on bottom-up peace research in the country to help guide its national post-conflict responses. We have also worked with Colombian and international organizations to train them in aspects of participatory methodologies and bottom-up measurement to support their work in ways that make peacebuilding more accountable to the communities they serve.     Last Modified: 12/12/2023       Submitted by: PaminaMFirchow]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
