<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[From Direct Instruction to Authentic Learning: A Shift to Increase Academic Success and Engineering Competencies among Youth of Color]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/07/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>145463.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>145463</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jumoke Ladeji-Osias</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jladejio@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927708</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Evidence shows that low-income youth of color are significantly underrepresented in postsecondary institutions and engineering-related fields. Many believe that these findings are connected, at least in part, to the emphasis on direct instruction that persists in many American urban high schools today. This project, based in an urban public high school, aims to support teachers as they move from direct instruction, which stresses content-based learning and rote memorization, to authentic learning, which focuses on project-based approaches and engineering literacies. During the grant period, we will observe classroom practice, create teacher inquiry groups, and conduct semi-structured interviews with teachers and students to understand the effects of this pedagogical shift on classroom learning and student outcomes. The project will demonstrate the instructional practices and pathways that are most likely to increase academic outcomes and college placement, which will ultimately create a more diverse group of individuals with the skills, literacies, and competencies to pursue careers in engineering.    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project seeks to validate that authentic learning is directly tied to college placement and success in engineering careers and seeks to explore the reactions among the students and teachers who are committed to moving their curricular and pedagogical approaches from direct instruction to authentic learning. Through a mixed-methods approach that combines classroom observations, student/teacher interviews, textual analysis of student work, and analysis of student-level data, the study will examine the ways that teachers and students react to these instructional changes, and how these shifts affect students' academic outcomes and diversify the pathways to and through engineering. The research will have broad implications to understanding and replicating instructional practices and learning processes that best prepare urban youth of color for postsecondary success and engineering careers by fundamentally restructuring the way that instruction is delivered. It will leverage the Next Generation Science Standards and the Engineering Habits of Mind to explore the development of engineering literacies. The findings from this study will generate a framework for understanding school reform and instructional change that takes into account teacher and student identities and perspectives, and outline the most promising ways for urban public high schools to increase academic engagement, engineering competencies, and college persistence among youth of color.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021452</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erika</FirstName>
<LastName>Kitzmiller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erika M Kitzmiller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ekitzmil@barnard.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000731960</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Barnard College</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276909</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128542708</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3009 BROADWAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LPQ1NHRK78M9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BARNARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Barnard College]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276598</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3900 Broadway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>EngEd-Engineering Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>110E</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>ENGINEERING EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001718DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~145463</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Access to higher education opportunities is not equitably distributed in the United States.&nbsp;Low-income, first-generation youth of color are much less likely to enroll in and complete four-year degree programs than their more affluent, white, and Asian peers, and these disparities have increased over the past few decades&nbsp;(Bailey &amp; Dynarski, 2011; Baker &amp; Robnett, 2012; Kim et al., 2017; Levin &amp; Belfield, 2007; Shapiro et al., 2018; Terrell &amp; Strayhorn, 2010).&nbsp;The dimensions of these inequities vary from access to social capital&nbsp;(Calarco, 2018; Jack, 2019; Yosso, 2005); parents&rsquo; level of education&nbsp;(Levin &amp; Belfield, 2007); poverty&nbsp;(Deming &amp; Dynarski, 2009); wealth&nbsp;(Zhan &amp; Sherraden, 2011); high school resources&nbsp;(Klasik, 2012); geography&nbsp;(Ardoin, 2019; Klasik et al., 2018); and racial background&nbsp;(Chute, 2009; E. McGee, 2015; E. O. McGee &amp; Martin, 2011). Although family background accounts for a considerable portion of these disparities, the support a student receives on the path to college is often intertwined with the opportunity structures&mdash;the resources and opportunities inside their public high schools.&nbsp;</p> <p>This study and its accompany book, <em>Unchartered: Reimagining the American High School, </em>shows what is possible when we reimagine the structural and instructional practices inside a high school to increase the number of high school graduates who apply to, enroll in, and most importantly, are prepared to graduate from four-year postsecondary degree programs. The reforms that were implemented over the five-year study operated at two levels: reforms that altered schoolwide structures and practices that strengthened classroom instruction. The study and book illustrates how I, as a researcher, collaborated with school administrators, educators, and youth to design, implement, and assess structural reforms&mdash;changes to the school schedule,&nbsp;course roster, and extracurricular offerings, as well as the instructional changes that teachers made inside their classrooms to advance a schoolwide college-bound culture that promoted academic excellence and socio-emotional development.&nbsp;It shows how&nbsp;small but significant changes in a school&rsquo;s structural arrangements and classroom instruction can generate a school culture that expands postsecondary preparation, opportunities, and experiences and contributes to socio-emotional growth and development for college-aspiring youth, many of whom are the first in their family to pursue their four-year college degrees in STEM and engineering fields.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">The study highlights the critical role that these youth played in shaping the study and ultimately the reforms that occurred. While I worked closely with Clayton administrators and educators throughout the project, the knowledge that youth shared about their high school and college preparation and experiences significantly shaped the reforms. For example, when the students shared that they were not applying to a wide array of school types or leveraging early decision mechanisms, Clayton administrators, educators, and I implemented and analyzed new practices and policies to address these shortcomings. When we learned that students relied heavily on their classroom teachers to assist them with college planning and decision, Clayton administrators, educators, and I devised ways for teachers to do this work without burdening their already taxed school lives.&nbsp;</p> <p>The study and book also showcases the critical role that&nbsp;Clayton&nbsp;teachers played in and beyond their classrooms to prepare their students for their lives in and beyond high school. I conducted hundreds of hours of classroom observations in Clayton classrooms. I deliberately selected Clayton teachers who represented a range of experiences and subjects so that I could capture and analyze the various ways that teachers teach and students learn. I have dedicated portraits throughout the book that explain these teachers&rsquo; curricular and pedagogical choices, how their identities shape classroom culture, and how students respond to their pedagogy and curriculum.</p> <p>Too often, school reform literature focuses solely on structural changes and downplays instructional practice. This study and book does not do that. Rather, it makes visible the central role that exemplary teachers play in any school reform effort. This work shows&nbsp;that small but significant changes in a school&rsquo;s structural arrangements&nbsp;<em>and</em>&nbsp;classroom instruction can strengthen the high-to-college pipeline for underrepresented youth and contribute to a school culture that promotes academic excellence, college opportunities, and ultimately, leads to better educational outcomes.&nbsp;It leverages qualitative and quantitative methods to illuminate how administrators, educators, researchers, and youth used this multi-faceted evidence to create, implement, and assess the reforms to alter the structural and instructional practice inside the high school.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 01/24/2024<br> Modified by: Erika&nbsp;M&nbsp;Kitzmiller</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Access to higher education opportunities is not equitably distributed in the United States.Low-income, first-generation youth of color are much less likely to enroll in and complete four-year degree programs than their more affluent, white, and Asian peers, and these disparities have increased over the past few decades(Bailey & Dynarski, 2011; Baker & Robnett, 2012; Kim et al., 2017; Levin & Belfield, 2007; Shapiro et al., 2018; Terrell & Strayhorn, 2010).The dimensions of these inequities vary from access to social capital(Calarco, 2018; Jack, 2019; Yosso, 2005); parents level of education(Levin & Belfield, 2007); poverty(Deming & Dynarski, 2009); wealth(Zhan & Sherraden, 2011); high school resources(Klasik, 2012); geography(Ardoin, 2019; Klasik et al., 2018); and racial background(Chute, 2009; E. McGee, 2015; E. O. McGee & Martin, 2011). Although family background accounts for a considerable portion of these disparities, the support a student receives on the path to college is often intertwined with the opportunity structuresthe resources and opportunities inside their public high schools.   This study and its accompany book, Unchartered: Reimagining the American High School, shows what is possible when we reimagine the structural and instructional practices inside a high school to increase the number of high school graduates who apply to, enroll in, and most importantly, are prepared to graduate from four-year postsecondary degree programs. The reforms that were implemented over the five-year study operated at two levels: reforms that altered schoolwide structures and practices that strengthened classroom instruction. The study and book illustrates how I, as a researcher, collaborated with school administrators, educators, and youth to design, implement, and assess structural reformschanges to the school schedule,course roster, and extracurricular offerings, as well as the instructional changes that teachers made inside their classrooms to advance a schoolwide college-bound culture that promoted academic excellence and socio-emotional development.It shows howsmall but significant changes in a schools structural arrangements and classroom instruction can generate a school culture that expands postsecondary preparation, opportunities, and experiences and contributes to socio-emotional growth and development for college-aspiring youth, many of whom are the first in their family to pursue their four-year college degrees in STEM and engineering fields.   The study highlights the critical role that these youth played in shaping the study and ultimately the reforms that occurred. While I worked closely with Clayton administrators and educators throughout the project, the knowledge that youth shared about their high school and college preparation and experiences significantly shaped the reforms. For example, when the students shared that they were not applying to a wide array of school types or leveraging early decision mechanisms, Clayton administrators, educators, and I implemented and analyzed new practices and policies to address these shortcomings. When we learned that students relied heavily on their classroom teachers to assist them with college planning and decision, Clayton administrators, educators, and I devised ways for teachers to do this work without burdening their already taxed school lives.   The study and book also showcases the critical role thatClaytonteachers played in and beyond their classrooms to prepare their students for their lives in and beyond high school. I conducted hundreds of hours of classroom observations in Clayton classrooms. I deliberately selected Clayton teachers who represented a range of experiences and subjects so that I could capture and analyze the various ways that teachers teach and students learn. I have dedicated portraits throughout the book that explain these teachers curricular and pedagogical choices, how their identities shape classroom culture, and how students respond to their pedagogy and curriculum.   Too often, school reform literature focuses solely on structural changes and downplays instructional practice. This study and book does not do that. Rather, it makes visible the central role that exemplary teachers play in any school reform effort. This work showsthat small but significant changes in a schools structural arrangementsandclassroom instruction can strengthen the high-to-college pipeline for underrepresented youth and contribute to a school culture that promotes academic excellence, college opportunities, and ultimately, leads to better educational outcomes.It leverages qualitative and quantitative methods to illuminate how administrators, educators, researchers, and youth used this multi-faceted evidence to create, implement, and assess the reforms to alter the structural and instructional practice inside the high school.           Last Modified: 01/24/2024       Submitted by: ErikaMKitzmiller]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
