<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: GP-IN: Traditional Knowledge In Geoscience: Policy and Research Practices]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>48003.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>48003</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>RISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div of Res, Innovation, Synergies, &amp; Edu</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brandon Jones</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbjones@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924713</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project engages in geoscience research, education, and policy training to align and braid Traditional Knowledge (TK) from Native American/Alaska Native (NA/AN) communities with Western science disciplines. The project encourages participation of underrepresented students (i.e. Indigenous, African American, Hispanic) into geoscience and policy research in an effort to demonstrate the diversity and potential for STEM careers and to provide rigorous geoscience research projects that are place- and community based in collaboration with NA/AN communities. The project builds upon multiple scientific paradigms blending biology, math, oceanography, chemistry, and environmental sciences with TK to encourage student interest in STEM. The program seeks to pointedly improve retention of NA/AN students in geoscience by fostering the creation of peer and mentor networks through collaborative research between tribal communities and academia. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs seek to develop an innovative and culturally aligned research program through the development of culturally aligned geoscience research and teaching models and by building on research in STEM education that provide theoretical and empirical justification for the project. The project investigates the impact of a culturally aligned geoscience research program to increase NA/AN students self-efficacy as scientists. The PIs believe that by acknowledging TK and STEM knowledge systems as valid modes of communicating science in the context of place, language, and culture the project effectively fosters intellectual justice and equal access to geoscience research and education. This program introduces a new model for undergraduate research by incorporating place- and community-based research coupled with TK and western knowledge systems, and through the incorporation of policy practices and drivers at both a federal and local scale. The program seeks to enhance the diversity of the geoscience workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2023007</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Judith</FirstName>
<LastName>Clarke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Judith B Clarke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Judith.B.Clarke@stonybrook.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000628083</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>STONY BROOK</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>W5510 FRANKS MELVILLE MEMORIAL L</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M746VC6XMNH9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117940701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 Administration Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~48003</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>SBU&rsquo;s funding was earmarked specifically for a Native graduate student with program evaluation skills to conduct the assessment of the project. I was unable to identify a Native SBU graduate student and therefore no expenses are listed for this reporting period, all programming costs were covered using alternative funding sources.</span></p> <p><span>Here are the AY2022-2023 outcomes:</span></p> <p><span>1)<span>&nbsp;</span></span><strong><span>June 18-21, 2023: Workshop for the Indigenous Geoscience Community</span></strong><span> (IGC) in Ketchikan, Alaska. </span><span>The purpose of the IGC is to address the urgent need for an international community of geoscience scholars and cultural practitioners that increases representation and leadership of Indigenous peoples in the geosciences. This includes providing a space for cross-cultural knowledge exchange, with support and mentorship for Indigenous geoscientists in a culturally respectful and ethical manner.&nbsp;</span><span>The workshop hosted 60 participants from 40 tribal nations and territories.</span></p> <p><span>2)<span>&nbsp;</span></span><strong><span>July 13, 2023: Published article, Ways of Knowing How Traditional Knowledge Enrich Geoscience Education - https://futurumcareers.com/ways-of-knowing. </span></strong><span>This article was produced by&nbsp;<span class="il">Futurum</span>&nbsp;Careers, a free online resource and magazine aimed at encouraging 14-19-year-olds worldwide to pursue careers in science, technology, engineering, math and medicine (STEM), and social sciences, humanities and the arts for people and the economy. </span><strong><span>DOI:&nbsp;</span></strong><a href="https://doi.org/10.33424/FUTURUM406" target="_blank"><span>https://doi.org/10.33424/FUTURUM406</span></a></p> <p><span>3)<span>&nbsp;</span></span><strong><span>July 6 to September 14, 2023: UMD Indigenous Geoscience Summer Internship. &nbsp;</span></strong><span><a href="https://sites.google.com/d.umn.edu/wfsmythe/home/opportunities">https://sites.google.com/d.umn.edu/wfsmythe/home/opportunities</a>. </span><span>The Internship Program is an opportunity to engage in science research, education, and policy training braiding Traditional Ecological Knowledge (TEK) from Native communities with various scientific disciplines. The program encourages participation of Alaska Native students into the sciences and policy research and considers traditions modes of knowledge transfer (stories, song, artistic expression). where interns will engage in geoscience research projects that are place- and community based in collaboration with Native communities. Participants will have the opportunity to build upon multiple scientific paradigms blending science with TK. The program provides an opportunity for interns to incorporate place- &amp; community-based research, while incorporating policy practices at federal and local scales.</span><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>4)<span>&nbsp;</span></span><strong><span>August 8<sup>th</sup>-12<sup>th</sup>, 2023: Hosted Indigenous Geoscience Symposium at the University of Hawaii-Manoa</span></strong><span> (UH-M). This was an opportunity for the summer research students to go to UH-M and meet the faculty, talk with graduate students, and tour the science research labs. This also included visiting the Bishop Museum, hiking the Gilbert Kahele Recreational Park, taking a Oahu Circle Island geological tour,</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 01/02/2024<br> Modified by: Judith&nbsp;B&nbsp;Clarke</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023007/2023007_10703902_1701466754634_Agenda_Indigenous_Geoscience_Symposium--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023007/2023007_10703902_1701466754634_Agenda_Indigenous_Geoscience_Symposium--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Indigenous Geoscience Symposium Agenda"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023007/2023007_10703902_1701466754634_Agenda_Indigenous_Geoscience_Symposium--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Indigenous Geoscience Symposium Agenda"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The symposium provided an opportunity for cross-cultural knowledge transfer that taught students research with multiple stakeholders, such as universities, tribal governments, Native communities, and policymakers.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Judith Brown Clarke</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Judith&nbsp;B&nbsp;Clarke <div class="imageTitle">Indigenous Geoscience Symposium Agenda</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  SBUs funding was earmarked specifically for a Native graduate student with program evaluation skills to conduct the assessment of the project. I was unable to identify a Native SBU graduate student and therefore no expenses are listed for this reporting period, all programming costs were covered using alternative funding sources.   Here are the AY2022-2023 outcomes:   1)June 18-21, 2023: Workshop for the Indigenous Geoscience Community (IGC) in Ketchikan, Alaska. The purpose of the IGC is to address the urgent need for an international community of geoscience scholars and cultural practitioners that increases representation and leadership of Indigenous peoples in the geosciences. This includes providing a space for cross-cultural knowledge exchange, with support and mentorship for Indigenous geoscientists in a culturally respectful and ethical manner.The workshop hosted 60 participants from 40 tribal nations and territories.   2)July 13, 2023: Published article, Ways of Knowing How Traditional Knowledge Enrich Geoscience Education - https://futurumcareers.com/ways-of-knowing. This article was produced byFuturumCareers, a free online resource and magazine aimed at encouraging 14-19-year-olds worldwide to pursue careers in science, technology, engineering, math and medicine (STEM), and social sciences, humanities and the arts for people and the economy. DOI:https://doi.org/10.33424/FUTURUM406   3)July 6 to September 14, 2023: UMD Indigenous Geoscience Summer Internship. https://sites.google.com/d.umn.edu/wfsmythe/home/opportunities. The Internship Program is an opportunity to engage in science research, education, and policy training braiding Traditional Ecological Knowledge (TEK) from Native communities with various scientific disciplines. The program encourages participation of Alaska Native students into the sciences and policy research and considers traditions modes of knowledge transfer (stories, song, artistic expression). where interns will engage in geoscience research projects that are place- and community based in collaboration with Native communities. Participants will have the opportunity to build upon multiple scientific paradigms blending science with TK. The program provides an opportunity for interns to incorporate place- & community-based research, while incorporating policy practices at federal and local scales.   4)August 8th-12th, 2023: Hosted Indigenous Geoscience Symposium at the University of Hawaii-Manoa (UH-M). This was an opportunity for the summer research students to go to UH-M and meet the faculty, talk with graduate students, and tour the science research labs. This also included visiting the Bishop Museum, hiking the Gilbert Kahele Recreational Park, taking a Oahu Circle Island geological tour,        Last Modified: 01/02/2024       Submitted by: JudithBClarke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
