<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant: Legacies of Colonial  Dislocation and Resettlement]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25187.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25187</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Using the concept of landesque capital—the cumulative investments of labor on durable improvements to the land and its continued maintenance—this research examines how a traditional colonized community responded to forced changes in their traditional settlement pattern.  First required to abandon a long-occupied homeland the group was resettled in centralized villages. However following resettlement in some cases group members reclaimed traditional areas. This research examines in detail both the abandonment and reclaimation process. It asks, what are the spatial and temporal patterns of the abandonment of some irrigation and field systems (and not others), and what are the spatial and temporal patterns of those that were later reclaimed. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The team will use a pedestrian archaeological survey and satellite remote sensing image analysis to investigate the construction, maintenance, abandonment, and reclamation of agricultural field and irrigation systems. These methods provide a unique opportunity to scale up beyond locality-level case studies toward regional scale analysis. The research complements traditional analyses of colonial written sources through a spatially-integrated archaeological, remote sensing, and ethnohistorical approach, which will, in turn, enable locality- to regional-perspectives on colonial mass resettlement. Ultimately, this research will enable a clearer understanding of both the traumas caused by forced resettlement and the varied forms of resilience of communities, as they forged new relationships to their built agricultural landscapes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2024316</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Wernke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven A Wernke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[s.wernke@vanderbilt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000392627</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gabriela</FirstName>
<LastName>Ore Menendez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>d</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gabriela d Ore Menendez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gabriela.ore@vanderbilt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000821853</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
<CityName>NASHVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>372032416</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 21ST AVE S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GTNBNWXJ12D5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372032410</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7606</Code>
<Text>Archaeology DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~25187</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default" style="text-align: center;">&nbsp;<strong>Legacies of Colonial Dislocation: Resettlement, Agricultural Deintensification and Infrastructural Reclamation in Huarochir&iacute;, Peru</strong></p> <p>This study focused on the spatial inequalities, in particular in Huarochiri, a region in the central Andes, about 40 km east of Lima, Peru, during the mid-colonial period (from the late 1570s to 1765), a time traditionally thought as the pick of colonial domination, right before the economic and political reforms known as the Bourbonic reforms, push by Phillip V from Spain.</p> <p>During the first decades of the colonial domination, specifically in the 1570s, the Spanish administration established the Reduccion General de Indios (General Resettlement of Indians, hereafter "Reduccion"), one of the largest mass forced resettlements ever undertaken by a colonial power. The Reduccion affected approximately 1.4 million indigenous people, forcing communities to abandon their settlements, usually dispersed along different elevations, micro-regions, and strategically located settlements, to build and inhabit compact, nucleated towns (referred to as "reducciones"). The Reduccion was part of a comprehensive set of colonial institutional reforms by the Viceroy Francisco de Toledo to foster Catholic evangelization, facilitate tribute collection, and monitor the social practices of Andean communities (Malaga Medina 1972, Mumford 2012, Saito 2012) . In the context of the forced resettlement, Andean communities were pushed away from their ancestral fields to new towns; this caused much of the workable land to be abandoned because of the distance between the new settlers.</p> <p>In this project, we bring the concept of landesque capital as the investment in durable infrastructure (Widgren 2007). For Andean communities, terraces, agricultural fields, and irrigation systems were part of the pre-Hispanic landesque capital. In the span of several decades, the original plan for the Reducciones did not stay the same, and communities were pushed away from the living conditions in the reduccion towns and pulled towards their once abandoned agricultural infrastructure, reclaiming previous agricultural lands (landesque capital)</p> <p>In that context, this research project explored the pull factors and the communities&rsquo; response to the mass resettlement, the reduccion. In that sense, the region of Huarochiri is an ideal region to answer this question because it offers a long list of archival documentation, ethnohistorical research, and archaeological data that complements our methodological approach: regional spatial analysis.</p> <p>Since the Reduccion was a Spanish mandate for the entire Peruvian viceroyalty, its impacts and effects must be addressed from a macro scale. As such, the project used multispectral satellite remote sensing to be able to focus on an entire region. Through image and geospatial analysis, we identify elements in the landscape, such as agricultural terraces and fields, to correlate them with the location of the first (and original) reducciones and then with the new settlements created, not by a Spanish administration mandate, but by the local communities need to reclaim their ancestral agricultural infrastructure, to then be able to reconstruct how the landscape changed between the mid colonial period.</p> <p>We identified the location of the original reducciones (Toledan reducciones) and the ones created by the communities (post-Toledan reducciones). Using satellite images from the PeruSat-1 satellite and after using image classification analysis, we identified and located agricultural infrastructure in the landscape and compared them with the location of the post-reducciones using geospatial analysis. We determined that the post-Toledan reducciones were closer to the already in-place agricultural fields and terraces.</p> <p>The location of the post-Toledan reducciones, closer to ancient agricultural infrastructure, reflects how the expansion of settlements under Spanish colonial administration in Huarochiri was not a passive endeavor following colonial mandates but an organic process pushed by Andean communities.</p> <p>The new post-Toledan and the original Toledan reducciones became the towns and districts of modern Peru, especially in the rural highland regions. In that framework, the understanding of where our modern geopolitical organization originated sheds light on the structural inequalities that originated during the Spanish colonial regime. The revision of how Andean highland communities came to show us how spatial inequality affects and transforms landscapes, especially when dislocated communities have to comply with top-down mandates that do not necessarily understand the socio-cultural dynamics and path dependencies highland communities live by. But at the same time, it shows how those same communities re-transformed and accommodated their space to fit their needs and desires and become active agents for landscape transformation.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Reference Cited</span></p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">Malaga Medina, A. (1975). "Las reducciones en el virreinato del Per&uacute; (1532-1580)." <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Revista de Historia de Am&eacute;rica</span>: 9-42.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">Mumford, J. R. (2012). <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Vertical Empire: the general resettlement of Indians in the colonial Andes</span>. Durham, NC; London, Duke University Press.&nbsp;</p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">Saito, A. (2012). Las reducciones ind&iacute;genas: &iquest;intrumento de etnocidio o espacio de etnog&eacute;nesis? <span style="text-decoration: underline;">54 Congreso Internacional de Americanistas</span>. Universidad de Viena.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">Widgren, M. (2007). Precolonial Landesque Capital: A Global Perspective. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Rethinking environmental history world-system history and global environmental change</span>. A. Hornborg, J. R. McNeill and J. M. Alier. Lanham, AltaMira Press<strong>: </strong>61-78.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/12/2023<br> Modified by: Gabriela&nbsp;D&nbsp;Ore Menendez</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Legacies of Colonial Dislocation: Resettlement, Agricultural Deintensification and Infrastructural Reclamation in Huarochir, Peru   This study focused on the spatial inequalities, in particular in Huarochiri, a region in the central Andes, about 40 km east of Lima, Peru, during the mid-colonial period (from the late 1570s to 1765), a time traditionally thought as the pick of colonial domination, right before the economic and political reforms known as the Bourbonic reforms, push by Phillip V from Spain.   During the first decades of the colonial domination, specifically in the 1570s, the Spanish administration established the Reduccion General de Indios (General Resettlement of Indians, hereafter "Reduccion"), one of the largest mass forced resettlements ever undertaken by a colonial power. The Reduccion affected approximately 1.4 million indigenous people, forcing communities to abandon their settlements, usually dispersed along different elevations, micro-regions, and strategically located settlements, to build and inhabit compact, nucleated towns (referred to as "reducciones"). The Reduccion was part of a comprehensive set of colonial institutional reforms by the Viceroy Francisco de Toledo to foster Catholic evangelization, facilitate tribute collection, and monitor the social practices of Andean communities (Malaga Medina 1972, Mumford 2012, Saito 2012) . In the context of the forced resettlement, Andean communities were pushed away from their ancestral fields to new towns; this caused much of the workable land to be abandoned because of the distance between the new settlers.   In this project, we bring the concept of landesque capital as the investment in durable infrastructure (Widgren 2007). For Andean communities, terraces, agricultural fields, and irrigation systems were part of the pre-Hispanic landesque capital. In the span of several decades, the original plan for the Reducciones did not stay the same, and communities were pushed away from the living conditions in the reduccion towns and pulled towards their once abandoned agricultural infrastructure, reclaiming previous agricultural lands (landesque capital)   In that context, this research project explored the pull factors and the communities response to the mass resettlement, the reduccion. In that sense, the region of Huarochiri is an ideal region to answer this question because it offers a long list of archival documentation, ethnohistorical research, and archaeological data that complements our methodological approach: regional spatial analysis.   Since the Reduccion was a Spanish mandate for the entire Peruvian viceroyalty, its impacts and effects must be addressed from a macro scale. As such, the project used multispectral satellite remote sensing to be able to focus on an entire region. Through image and geospatial analysis, we identify elements in the landscape, such as agricultural terraces and fields, to correlate them with the location of the first (and original) reducciones and then with the new settlements created, not by a Spanish administration mandate, but by the local communities need to reclaim their ancestral agricultural infrastructure, to then be able to reconstruct how the landscape changed between the mid colonial period.   We identified the location of the original reducciones (Toledan reducciones) and the ones created by the communities (post-Toledan reducciones). Using satellite images from the PeruSat-1 satellite and after using image classification analysis, we identified and located agricultural infrastructure in the landscape and compared them with the location of the post-reducciones using geospatial analysis. We determined that the post-Toledan reducciones were closer to the already in-place agricultural fields and terraces.   The location of the post-Toledan reducciones, closer to ancient agricultural infrastructure, reflects how the expansion of settlements under Spanish colonial administration in Huarochiri was not a passive endeavor following colonial mandates but an organic process pushed by Andean communities.   The new post-Toledan and the original Toledan reducciones became the towns and districts of modern Peru, especially in the rural highland regions. In that framework, the understanding of where our modern geopolitical organization originated sheds light on the structural inequalities that originated during the Spanish colonial regime. The revision of how Andean highland communities came to show us how spatial inequality affects and transforms landscapes, especially when dislocated communities have to comply with top-down mandates that do not necessarily understand the socio-cultural dynamics and path dependencies highland communities live by. But at the same time, it shows how those same communities re-transformed and accommodated their space to fit their needs and desires and become active agents for landscape transformation.   Reference Cited   Malaga Medina, A. (1975). "Las reducciones en el virreinato del Per (1532-1580)." Revista de Historia de Amrica: 9-42.   Mumford, J. R. (2012). Vertical Empire: the general resettlement of Indians in the colonial Andes. Durham, NC; London, Duke University Press.   Saito, A. (2012). Las reducciones indgenas: intrumento de etnocidio o espacio de etnognesis? 54 Congreso Internacional de Americanistas. Universidad de Viena.   Widgren, M. (2007). Precolonial Landesque Capital: A Global Perspective. Rethinking environmental history world-system history and global environmental change. A. Hornborg, J. R. McNeill and J. M. Alier. Lanham, AltaMira Press: 61-78.     Last Modified: 11/12/2023       Submitted by: GabrielaDOre Menendez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
