<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Joint Conference Convening of the HBCU STEM-US CEEQA:   Leveraging Collaboration and Partnerships to Impact Research and Quality Assurance in STEM]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tori Rhoulac Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tosmith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922315</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Historically Black Colleges and Universities-Undergraduate Program (HBCUs) funds workshops as a means of discussing and disseminating best practices in science, technology, engineering and mathematics education at HBCUs. The conference by Morehouse college seeks to examine the contributions of HBCUs to STEM undergraduate education and facilitate knowledge transfer that is essential to promote the use of best assessment practices to understand and expand an effective model for STEM education at HBCUs. The conference will be attended by sixty faculty members and researchers from forty HBCUs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will accomplish the planning and knowledge transfer agenda by: 1) presenting hands-on workshops on implementing and researching new educational strategies, such as course-based undergraduate research experiences, utilitarian Scientific Literacy curriculum, and best practices for assessment and evaluation; 2) building faculty capacity through proposal development training; 3) keynote presentations about center-wide research activities and defining student success; 4) poster sessions for networking and sharing ideas; 5) discovering and disseminating ways that HBCUs can use data to inform and strengthen STEM education; and 6) providing a venue for planning future activities, knowledge transfer and outreach.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/22/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025221</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Derrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Bryan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Derrick M Bryan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[derrick.bryan@morehouse.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000682987</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lycurgus</FirstName>
<LastName>Muldrow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lycurgus L Muldrow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lycurgus.muldrow@morehouse.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000075570</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/23/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Morehouse College</Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>303143773</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4706390633</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>830 WESTVIEW DR SW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KTE2MFWTKAE5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MOREHOUSE COLLEGE INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>KTE2MFWTKAE5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Morehouse College]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303143773</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49998</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In 2020, Morehouse College was awarded $49,998 to support the development and convening of a joint conference between the HBCU STEM Undergraduate Success Research Center (HBCU STEM US) and the HBCU Collaborative for Excellence in Educational Quality Assurance HBCU-CEEQA). The conference planned for 2020 did not occur because of the global pandemic.&nbsp;</p> <p>The goal of the conferences was to facilitate dialogue surrounding the topic of student success in STEM at HBCUs, as a part of sharing knowledge associated with HBCU STEM US. The collaboration between the HBCU STEM US Center and the HBCU-CEEQA sought to understand the unique contributions of HBCUs to STEM Education. Along with this, the intent of this joint conference was to share information that will assist in the understanding of the assets supporting the success of HBCUs to STEM Education, along with encouraging the continuation of interdisciplinary research, by faculty members of HBCUs, that will provide a fresh perspective on broadening participation research.</p> <p>This joint convening is supported by the missions of the HBCU STEM US Research Center and the HBCU-CEEQA. The written mission of the STEM Undergraduate Success Research center is: &ldquo;to understand and tell the stories of HBCUs through convergence research for us, and the nation; thereby, creating a national legacy of excellence in STEM education at HBCUs,&rdquo; and the mission of the HBCU-CEEQA is &ldquo;to demonstrate the effectiveness of HBCUs through the use of best-practices in assessment and evaluation by leveraging the collective expertise of assessment and institutional effectiveness professionals and other stakeholders.&rdquo; The overarching theme of all conference activities is to understand and tell the stories of HBCUs, creating a national record of the legacy of excellence in STEM education at HBCUs.</p> <p>Though there was a cancellation of the initial conference, three subsequent conferences did come out of this funding opportunity. The first of the conference series occurred May 13-14, 2021, in a virtual setting, with the theme of &ldquo;Understanding HBCU STEM Success: The Power of the Story.&rdquo; This was the second joint conference of the HBCU STEM Undergraduate Success Research Center and the HBCU Collaboration for Excellence in Educational Quality Assurance. Via this conference we provided a space to communicate and share information regarding a focus on STEM research that was interdisciplinary in its origin. Participants left this conference with a fresh goal and settled intent of broadening participation in STEM by those that may not fall directly under the umbrella.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The second convening occurred July 12-15, 2022, with dual themes of &ldquo;Understanding the Power of Story&rdquo; and &ldquo;Re-emerging Stronger and More Resolved in our Pursuit of Institutional Effectiveness and Student Success&rdquo;. This conference was virtual and featured workshops highlighting numerous aspects of research occurring in the center, including scientific literacy, The Data Concilium, CareFull Scholars program, and in person pre-conference CUREs workshops. Faculty workshops focused on student engagement, building student support assets, meaningful assessment for student learning, and sharing research initiatives and outcomes between institutions and across STEM fields. Additionally, virtual poster sessions took place.</p> <p>The third conference occurred with the HBCU STEM Undergraduate Success Research Center independently, on September 7-9, 2023, with the theme of &ldquo;Focusing on Excellence in STEM Student Success at HBCUs.&rdquo; Our goal for the conference was to engage in an exchange of ideas and work centered on integrating STEM education, research, and practice. This conference also gave us the opportunity to show student success in STEM at HBCU&rsquo;s. Further, we were able to expand the boundaries of academia by having external vendors in STEM education and research present. This was showcased by the presence of ThinkLive, a company using turntables and DJ style techniques to create curriculum for widening exposure to science coding, and mathematics. While other sessions were more focused on scholarship and research, including talks focused on topics such as &ldquo;Infusion of Inquiry-based and Culturally Science Teaching for STEM Education&rdquo;, &ldquo;The Interplay between STEM and Data Science&rdquo;, and &ldquo;Grant Writing&rdquo;.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 01/25/2024<br> Modified by: Derrick&nbsp;M&nbsp;Bryan</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2025221/2025221_10667690_1706218542089_Image_2--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2025221/2025221_10667690_1706218542089_Image_2--rgov-800width.png" title="HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2025221/2025221_10667690_1706218542089_Image_2--rgov-66x44.png" alt="HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE</div> <div class="imageCredit">HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Derrick&nbsp;M&nbsp;Bryan <div class="imageTitle">HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2025221/2025221_10667690_1706218588214_Image_3--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2025221/2025221_10667690_1706218588214_Image_3--rgov-800width.png" title="HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2025221/2025221_10667690_1706218588214_Image_3--rgov-66x44.png" alt="HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE</div> <div class="imageCredit">HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Derrick&nbsp;M&nbsp;Bryan <div class="imageTitle">HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2025221/2025221_10667690_1706218788107_Image_4--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2025221/2025221_10667690_1706218788107_Image_4--rgov-800width.png" title="HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2025221/2025221_10667690_1706218788107_Image_4--rgov-66x44.png" alt="HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE</div> <div class="imageCredit">HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Derrick&nbsp;M&nbsp;Bryan <div class="imageTitle">HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2025221/2025221_10667690_1706218494943_Image_1_alternate--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2025221/2025221_10667690_1706218494943_Image_1_alternate--rgov-800width.png" title="HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2025221/2025221_10667690_1706218494943_Image_1_alternate--rgov-66x44.png" alt="HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE</div> <div class="imageCredit">HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Derrick&nbsp;M&nbsp;Bryan <div class="imageTitle">HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2025221/2025221_10667690_1706218630302_Image_5--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2025221/2025221_10667690_1706218630302_Image_5--rgov-800width.png" title="HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2025221/2025221_10667690_1706218630302_Image_5--rgov-66x44.png" alt="HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE</div> <div class="imageCredit">HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Derrick&nbsp;M&nbsp;Bryan <div class="imageTitle">HBCU STEM US CONFERENCE</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  In 2020, Morehouse College was awarded $49,998 to support the development and convening of a joint conference between the HBCU STEM Undergraduate Success Research Center (HBCU STEM US) and the HBCU Collaborative for Excellence in Educational Quality Assurance HBCU-CEEQA). The conference planned for 2020 did not occur because of the global pandemic.   The goal of the conferences was to facilitate dialogue surrounding the topic of student success in STEM at HBCUs, as a part of sharing knowledge associated with HBCU STEM US. The collaboration between the HBCU STEM US Center and the HBCU-CEEQA sought to understand the unique contributions of HBCUs to STEM Education. Along with this, the intent of this joint conference was to share information that will assist in the understanding of the assets supporting the success of HBCUs to STEM Education, along with encouraging the continuation of interdisciplinary research, by faculty members of HBCUs, that will provide a fresh perspective on broadening participation research.   This joint convening is supported by the missions of the HBCU STEM US Research Center and the HBCU-CEEQA. The written mission of the STEM Undergraduate Success Research center is: to understand and tell the stories of HBCUs through convergence research for us, and the nation; thereby, creating a national legacy of excellence in STEM education at HBCUs, and the mission of the HBCU-CEEQA is to demonstrate the effectiveness of HBCUs through the use of best-practices in assessment and evaluation by leveraging the collective expertise of assessment and institutional effectiveness professionals and other stakeholders. The overarching theme of all conference activities is to understand and tell the stories of HBCUs, creating a national record of the legacy of excellence in STEM education at HBCUs.   Though there was a cancellation of the initial conference, three subsequent conferences did come out of this funding opportunity. The first of the conference series occurred May 13-14, 2021, in a virtual setting, with the theme of Understanding HBCU STEM Success: The Power of the Story. This was the second joint conference of the HBCU STEM Undergraduate Success Research Center and the HBCU Collaboration for Excellence in Educational Quality Assurance. Via this conference we provided a space to communicate and share information regarding a focus on STEM research that was interdisciplinary in its origin. Participants left this conference with a fresh goal and settled intent of broadening participation in STEM by those that may not fall directly under the umbrella.   The second convening occurred July 12-15, 2022, with dual themes of Understanding the Power of Story and Re-emerging Stronger and More Resolved in our Pursuit of Institutional Effectiveness and Student Success. This conference was virtual and featured workshops highlighting numerous aspects of research occurring in the center, including scientific literacy, The Data Concilium, CareFull Scholars program, and in person pre-conference CUREs workshops. Faculty workshops focused on student engagement, building student support assets, meaningful assessment for student learning, and sharing research initiatives and outcomes between institutions and across STEM fields. Additionally, virtual poster sessions took place.   The third conference occurred with the HBCU STEM Undergraduate Success Research Center independently, on September 7-9, 2023, with the theme of Focusing on Excellence in STEM Student Success at HBCUs. Our goal for the conference was to engage in an exchange of ideas and work centered on integrating STEM education, research, and practice. This conference also gave us the opportunity to show student success in STEM at HBCUs. Further, we were able to expand the boundaries of academia by having external vendors in STEM education and research present. This was showcased by the presence of ThinkLive, a company using turntables and DJ style techniques to create curriculum for widening exposure to science coding, and mathematics. While other sessions were more focused on scholarship and research, including talks focused on topics such as Infusion of Inquiry-based and Culturally Science Teaching for STEM Education, The Interplay between STEM and Data Science, and Grant Writing.              Last Modified: 01/25/2024       Submitted by: DerrickMBryan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
