<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Interparticle Metal-Metal Interactions in Electrocatalytic Carbon Dioxide Reduction Reactions]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>444739.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>444739</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmccabe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924826</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[A major challenge in the transition to clean energy is reducing emissions of carbon dioxide from fuel combustion. Using renewable electricity to convert carbon dioxide to value-added fuels and chemical products is a promising way of turning carbon emissions into a resource. Palladium is a unique metal that can catalyze the electrochemical conversion of carbon dioxide to formate ion (HCOO-).  Formate is a building-block compound that can be used to produce industrially important chemicals such as formaldehyde and methanol. The catalytic performance of palladium, however, is severely limited by rapid deactivation of the catalyst active site, and it is difficult to design improved systems without further understanding of both the reaction and deactivation mechanisms. This research project will study novel catalysts composed of palladium and a secondary metal.  The aim is to stabilize the catalyst active site and thereby develop catalysts can perform the sustained, efficient conversion of carbon dioxide into formate. This research project also will foster new teaching and learning opportunities for a large and diverse body of students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The aim of this research project is to investigate how nanoscale interparticle metal-metal interactions influence the catalytic mechanisms of carbon dioxide electroreduction on palladium.  The goals are to limit catalyst deactivation during the production of formate and to enable the synthesis of new products such as formaldehyde or methanol. Metal nanoparticles will be used as “electronic ligands” and modify the binding strength of palladium with reaction intermediates. The nanoparticles also can act as “collaborative ligands” that directly participate in catalysis by providing a secondary type of surface site. The electronic and collaborative interactions between palladium and a variety of other metals will be studied. Additionally, experiments will be performed to learn how these interactions change the binding energetics of palladium with the reaction intermediates and the potential-dependent reduction reaction pathways. Ultimately, the knowledge gained from these studies will be used to develop electrocatalysts that are stable for efficient conversion of carbon dioxide to formate and then on to more complex products.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028351</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hailiang</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hailiang Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hailiang.wang@yale.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000683115</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>NEW HAVEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>065118917</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>105 WALL ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[810 West Campus Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~444739</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project, a team led by Dr. Hailiang Wang at Yale University performed research into the catalysis of electrochemical reduction reactions of carbon dioxide, nitrate, and chlorinated organic compounds. These reactions, which often take place under mild conditions, hold promise for renewable energy storage, carbon emission mitigation, wastewater treatment, and green production of fuels and chemicals, but controlling their product selectivity and reaction rates remains highly challenging because of limited understanding of reaction mechanisms and structure-reactivity correlations of catalyst materials. Through combined efforts in catalyst material synthesis, electrocatalytic reaction studies, and in situ spectroscopic measurements, the team analyzed different sites on metal surfaces, active site-adsorbate interactions, and molecule-support interactions, as well as their effects on electrocatalytic kinetics. New sites on gold surfaces for the reduction of carbon dioxide to carbon monoxide were discovered. New roles of carbon nanotubes beyond being an inert support in the reduction of nitrate to ammonia were established. Comparison between extended metal surfaces and single atom sites was made in the dechlorination reactions. The team further explored synergy among these reactions. With a copper metal catalyst, the electrochemical reduction of chlorinated organic compounds such as 1,2-dichloroethane, trichloroethylene, and tetrachloroethylene into ethylene in aqueous media can be substantially enhanced by simultaneously carrying out carbon dioxide reduction, and the co-reduction of carbon dioxide and nitrate can lead to the formation of ethylamine, a new reaction for producing valuable organonitrogen compounds from inorganic wastes using renewable electricity. This project discovered new chemical interactions on the molecular level that can be utilized to advance these important yet still challenging electrochemical reactions toward applications in enregy storage, carbon emission reduction, and wastewater treatment. This project facilitated the training of three graduate students and two postdoctoral fellows. The research activities and results provided new contents for classroom teaching and outreach activities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 01/20/2024<br> Modified by: Hailiang&nbsp;Wang</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  In this project, a team led by Dr. Hailiang Wang at Yale University performed research into the catalysis of electrochemical reduction reactions of carbon dioxide, nitrate, and chlorinated organic compounds. These reactions, which often take place under mild conditions, hold promise for renewable energy storage, carbon emission mitigation, wastewater treatment, and green production of fuels and chemicals, but controlling their product selectivity and reaction rates remains highly challenging because of limited understanding of reaction mechanisms and structure-reactivity correlations of catalyst materials. Through combined efforts in catalyst material synthesis, electrocatalytic reaction studies, and in situ spectroscopic measurements, the team analyzed different sites on metal surfaces, active site-adsorbate interactions, and molecule-support interactions, as well as their effects on electrocatalytic kinetics. New sites on gold surfaces for the reduction of carbon dioxide to carbon monoxide were discovered. New roles of carbon nanotubes beyond being an inert support in the reduction of nitrate to ammonia were established. Comparison between extended metal surfaces and single atom sites was made in the dechlorination reactions. The team further explored synergy among these reactions. With a copper metal catalyst, the electrochemical reduction of chlorinated organic compounds such as 1,2-dichloroethane, trichloroethylene, and tetrachloroethylene into ethylene in aqueous media can be substantially enhanced by simultaneously carrying out carbon dioxide reduction, and the co-reduction of carbon dioxide and nitrate can lead to the formation of ethylamine, a new reaction for producing valuable organonitrogen compounds from inorganic wastes using renewable electricity. This project discovered new chemical interactions on the molecular level that can be utilized to advance these important yet still challenging electrochemical reactions toward applications in enregy storage, carbon emission reduction, and wastewater treatment. This project facilitated the training of three graduate students and two postdoctoral fellows. The research activities and results provided new contents for classroom teaching and outreach activities.        Last Modified: 01/20/2024       Submitted by: HailiangWang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
