<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: The realization of nasality across the typological spectrum]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18901.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18901</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jorge Valdes Kroff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jvaldesk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927920</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This dissertation project will advance our understanding of speech sounds  in human languages by investigating nasality in languages with rare nasal speech sound systems. Nasal sounds are produced with air flowing through the nasal cavity, such as [m] and [n] in English, and are present in nearly all of the world’s languages. However, much remains unknown about the range of possible nasal speech sounds systems in human languages, and what is responsible for the emergence of different types of nasal systems, meaning that there is a significant gap in our understanding of this fundamental aspect of human language. This study will help fill this gap by: 1) investigating nasality systems in languages that represent two distinct ends of the typological spectrum in terms of the size of the domains over which duration and intensity of nasality are controlled by speakers; and 2) investigating the hypothesis that nasality systems which are very sensitive to the duration and intensity of nasality are associated with languages where nasality plays an important role in making distinctions in meaning. With respect to the typological spectrum of nasality, at one extreme this project will investigate a language that distinguishes speech sounds that differ in the duration of nasality within individual sound segments, as evidenced in contrasts between prenasalized [nt] and postoralized [nt]. At the other extreme, it will investigate a language that exhibits a slow, gradual increase in nasality over entire words, and where nasality is thus less clearly tied to individual sound segments, but rather larger domains encompassing many sound segments. These rare phenomena indicate that speakers of human languages are sensitive to minute distinctions in nasality, both in its temporal extent as well as in the amount of nasal airflow. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;That speakers of human languages are sensitive to such fine-grained differences in nasality raises the question of why these phenomena are observed in some languages, but not others. This study investigates the hypothesis that part of the answer lies in the functional load of nasality (a measure of the amount of "work" that any particular contrast does in a language) in different human languages. The functional load of nasality is likely much higher in languages at these extremes of the typological spectrum than it is in other languages for which nasality has commonly been investigated, e.g. English or French, making such languages critical for understanding how the range of nasality systems found in human languages may arise. This project is based on intensive fieldwork with speakers of languages exhibiting different kinds of nasality systems, and relies on two key methodologies. First, interview-style elicitation techniques will allow for a detailed description of the rules that govern the realization of nasality in these languages. Second, the project will develop a corpus of oral narratives in these languages, which will be transcribed, translated, and archived for the preservation and dissemination of these data. An analysis of the corpora will make it possible to measure the functional load of nasality in these languages and shed light on how functional load is related to the types of speech sounds found in human languages.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/15/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029704</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lev</FirstName>
<LastName>Michael</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lev Michael</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[levmichael@berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000529514</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sharon</FirstName>
<LastName>Inkelas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sharon Inkelas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[inkelas@socrates.berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000466754</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Faytak</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew Faytak</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[faytak@buffalo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000873533</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/07/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/15/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Myriam</FirstName>
<LastName>Lapierre</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Myriam Lapierre</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mylapier@uw.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824290</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1608 4TH ST STE 201</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GS3YEVSS12N6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Linguistics Department]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947202650</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1203 Dwinelle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>123Y</Code>
<Text>DLI DDRIG-DynLangInfrast DDRIG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5913</Code>
<Text>BRAZIL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~18901</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This project documented and described the nasality-related phonological processes of two indigenous languages of the Brazilian Amazon, Pan&atilde;ra and Kawaiwete. This project advances our understanding of the necessary level of granularity to be encoded in phonological representations.</span></p> <p><span>Lapierre&rsquo;s general documentation of the languages covers elicitation on </span><span>a variety of grammatical topics, as well as the recording of naturally occurring speech in the form of traditional narratives.</span></p> <p><span>Lapierre's dissertation (2023a) provides a detailed description of the nasality-related phonological process in both Pan&atilde;ra and Kawaiwete. Pan&atilde;ra exhibits two phonological processes resulting in surface [NT] (nasal consonant-oral consonant) sequences, namely&nbsp;post-oralization of nasal consonants, whereby nasal consonants are post-oralized before an oral vowel; and pre-nasalization of oral obstruents, whereby oral obstruents are pre-nasalized after a nasal vowel. Kawaiwete exhibits coarticulatory nasalization, whereby vowels are lightly nasalized adjacent to nasal consonants, and vowels preceding a phonemically nasal vowel are also lightly nasalized.</span></p> <p><span>Lapierre's dissertation analyzes of the phonological representation of partially nasal segments in Pan&atilde;ra and Kawaiwete. She finds that the traditional notion of a segment may be divided into a tripartite representation on both the time dimension and the magnitude of nasal gesture dimension.&nbsp;The proposed representational model integrates&nbsp;the basic architecture of Q Theory&nbsp;(Inkelas &amp; Shih 2016; 2017; Shih &amp; Inkelas 2014; 2019) and&nbsp;subfeatural representations&nbsp;(Lionnet2017) into a unified&nbsp;framework.&nbsp;On the basis of Pan&atilde;ra, the author argues for&nbsp;Q-theoretic&nbsp;subsegmental representations, which divide the segment into three quantized and ordered subsegments&nbsp;(q1q2q3). This architecture provides the level of granularity&nbsp;necessary to distinguish between the two types of [NT]s. Lapierre&nbsp;argues on the basis of Kawaiwete for a&nbsp;scalar&nbsp;decomposition of&nbsp;phonological features, where&nbsp;continuous values can be grouped into three subfeatural categories:&nbsp;fully nasal&nbsp;[+nasal], partially nasal [</span><span>&#119909;</span><span>nasal], and fully oral [&ndash;nasal]. A model of phonological representations making use of both subsegments and subfeatures&nbsp;is not only able to account for the&nbsp;Pan&atilde;ra and Kawaiwete data, but can be extended to account for&nbsp;the full typology&nbsp;of&nbsp;phonological processes involving local nasalization or oralization.</span></p> <p><span>Lapierre's findings are available via her dissertation (2023a). Her findings for Pan&atilde;ra have been presented in multiple venues (Lapierre &amp; Lin 2018, Lapierre &amp; Lin 2019b, Lapierre 2020a, 2020b, 2021a, 2021b, 2022a, 2022b; Lin &amp; Lapierre 2020) and published (Lapierre &amp; Lin 2019a, Lapierre&nbsp;2023b). Her findings on Kawaiwete have also been presented (Lapierre &amp; De Falco 2023). In addition, all field data has been archived (Lapierre 2020c, 2020d).</span></p> <p><span>References:</span></p> <p><span>Lapierre, Myriam. (2023a).&nbsp;Towards a Theory of Subsegmental and Subfeatural Representations: The Phonology and Typology of Nasality.&nbsp;UC Berkeley Doctoral Dissertation.<br />Lapierre, Myriam. (2023b).&nbsp;Two types of [NT]s in Pan&atilde;ra: Evidence for temporally ordered subsegmental units.&nbsp;<em>Glossa: a journal of general linguistics</em>.<br />Myriam&nbsp;Lapierre. (2020c).&nbsp;<em>Pan&atilde;ra Fieldwork Materials</em>. University of California, Berkeley: Survey of California and Other Indian Languages. URL: http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.7297/X20R9MWN.<br />Myriam&nbsp;Lapierre. (2020d).&nbsp;<em>Kawaiwete Fieldwork Materials</em>. University of California, Berkeley: Survey of California and Other Indian Languages. </span><span lang="PT-BR">URL: http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.7297/X2Z036NC.</span><span><br /></span><span lang="PT-BR">Lapierre, Myriam&nbsp;&amp; Ella De Falco. </span><span>(2023). Three degrees of vowel nasality in Kawaiwete. Talk to be presented at the 10<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;Conference on Indigenous Languages of Latin America, University of Texas at Austin.<br />Lapierre, Myriam. (2022a).<em>&nbsp;Advancing the goals of scientific research and native speaker communities in synergy: A case study from Pan&atilde;ra</em>. Talk presented at the Linguistics Department Colloquium Series, UCLA.<br />Lapierre, Myriam. (2022b). The Typology of Local Nasal and Oral Assimilation. Talk presented at the Fourth Symposium on Amazonian Languages, UC Berkeley.<br /></span><span lang="PT-BR">Lapierre, Myriam. (2021a).<em>&nbsp;Consonantes nasales complejas en pan&atilde;ra</em>. Talk presented at the 2do Coloquio Internacional de Lingu</span><span lang="PT-BR">&#776;</span><span lang="PT-BR">&iacute;stica en Bolivia, Linguistics Summer School Bolivia.</span><span><br />Lapierre, Myriam. (2021b).<em>&nbsp;Towards a Theory of Subsegmental Representations: The Phonology and Typology of Nasality</em>. Talk presented at the Linguistics Department Colloquium series, University of Washington.<br />Lapierre, Myriam. (2020a).<em>&nbsp;Two types of [NT]s in Pan&atilde;ra: Evidence from production and perception</em>. Talk presented at the Linguistics Department Open House, UC Berkeley.<br />Lapierre, Myriam. (2020b).<em>&nbsp;Two types of [NT]s in Pan&atilde;ra: Evidence from production and perception</em>. Poster presented at the 8th Annual Meeting on Phonology, UC Santa Cruz.<br />Lapierre, Myriam&nbsp;&amp;&nbsp;Susan Lin. (2019a). Cues to Pan&atilde;ra Nasal-Oral Stop Sequence Perception.&nbsp;<em>Proceedings of the 2019 Congress of International Phonetic Sciences</em>. Melbourne, Australia.<br />Lapierre, Myriam&nbsp;&amp; Susan Lin. (2019b).<em>&nbsp;Cues to Pan&atilde;ra Nasal-Oral Stop Sequence Perception</em>. Talk presented at the 2019 Congress of International Phonetic Sciences, Melbourne, Australia.<br />Lapierre, Myriam. (2019).<em>&nbsp;Two types of [NT]s in Pan&atilde;ra: Evidence from production and perception</em>. Talk presented at Third Symposium on Amazonian Languages, UC Berkeley.<br />Lapierre, Myriam&nbsp;&amp; Susan Lin. (2018).<em>&nbsp;Patterns of nasal coarticulation in Panar&aacute;</em>. Poster presented at the 16th Conference on Laboratory Phonology, Lisbon, Portugal.<br />Lin, Susan &amp;&nbsp;Myriam Lapierre. (2020).<em>&nbsp;Articulatory patterns in contrasting nasal-stop sequences in Pan&atilde;ra</em>. Talk presented at the 94th Annual Meeting of the LSA, New Orleans, Louisiana.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 01/11/2024<br> Modified by: Myriam&nbsp;Lapierre</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This project documented and described the nasality-related phonological processes of two indigenous languages of the Brazilian Amazon, Panra and Kawaiwete. This project advances our understanding of the necessary level of granularity to be encoded in phonological representations.   Lapierres general documentation of the languages covers elicitation on a variety of grammatical topics, as well as the recording of naturally occurring speech in the form of traditional narratives.   Lapierre's dissertation (2023a) provides a detailed description of the nasality-related phonological process in both Panra and Kawaiwete. Panra exhibits two phonological processes resulting in surface [NT] (nasal consonant-oral consonant) sequences, namelypost-oralization of nasal consonants, whereby nasal consonants are post-oralized before an oral vowel; and pre-nasalization of oral obstruents, whereby oral obstruents are pre-nasalized after a nasal vowel. Kawaiwete exhibits coarticulatory nasalization, whereby vowels are lightly nasalized adjacent to nasal consonants, and vowels preceding a phonemically nasal vowel are also lightly nasalized.   Lapierre's dissertation analyzes of the phonological representation of partially nasal segments in Panra and Kawaiwete. She finds that the traditional notion of a segment may be divided into a tripartite representation on both the time dimension and the magnitude of nasal gesture dimension.The proposed representational model integratesthe basic architecture of Q Theory(Inkelas & Shih 2016; 2017; Shih & Inkelas 2014; 2019) andsubfeatural representations(Lionnet2017) into a unifiedframework.On the basis of Panra, the author argues forQ-theoreticsubsegmental representations, which divide the segment into three quantized and ordered subsegments(q1q2q3). This architecture provides the level of granularitynecessary to distinguish between the two types of [NT]s. Lapierreargues on the basis of Kawaiwete for ascalardecomposition ofphonological features, wherecontinuous values can be grouped into three subfeatural categories:fully nasal[+nasal], partially nasal [&#119909;nasal], and fully oral [nasal]. A model of phonological representations making use of both subsegments and subfeaturesis not only able to account for thePanra and Kawaiwete data, but can be extended to account forthe full typologyofphonological processes involving local nasalization or oralization.   Lapierre's findings are available via her dissertation (2023a). Her findings for Panra have been presented in multiple venues (Lapierre & Lin 2018, Lapierre & Lin 2019b, Lapierre 2020a, 2020b, 2021a, 2021b, 2022a, 2022b; Lin & Lapierre 2020) and published (Lapierre & Lin 2019a, Lapierre2023b). Her findings on Kawaiwete have also been presented (Lapierre & De Falco 2023). In addition, all field data has been archived (Lapierre 2020c, 2020d).   References:   Lapierre, Myriam. (2023a).Towards a Theory of Subsegmental and Subfeatural Representations: The Phonology and Typology of Nasality.UC Berkeley Doctoral Dissertation. Lapierre, Myriam. (2023b).Two types of [NT]s in Panra: Evidence for temporally ordered subsegmental units.Glossa: a journal of general linguistics. MyriamLapierre. (2020c).Panra Fieldwork Materials. University of California, Berkeley: Survey of California and Other Indian Languages. URL: http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.7297/X20R9MWN. MyriamLapierre. (2020d).Kawaiwete Fieldwork Materials. University of California, Berkeley: Survey of California and Other Indian Languages. URL: http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.7297/X2Z036NC. Lapierre, Myriam& Ella De Falco. (2023). Three degrees of vowel nasality in Kawaiwete. Talk to be presented at the 10thConference on Indigenous Languages of Latin America, University of Texas at Austin. Lapierre, Myriam. (2022a).Advancing the goals of scientific research and native speaker communities in synergy: A case study from Panra. Talk presented at the Linguistics Department Colloquium Series, UCLA. Lapierre, Myriam. (2022b). The Typology of Local Nasal and Oral Assimilation. Talk presented at the Fourth Symposium on Amazonian Languages, UC Berkeley. Lapierre, Myriam. (2021a).Consonantes nasales complejas en panra. Talk presented at the 2do Coloquio Internacional de Lingu&#776;stica en Bolivia, Linguistics Summer School Bolivia. Lapierre, Myriam. (2021b).Towards a Theory of Subsegmental Representations: The Phonology and Typology of Nasality. Talk presented at the Linguistics Department Colloquium series, University of Washington. Lapierre, Myriam. (2020a).Two types of [NT]s in Panra: Evidence from production and perception. Talk presented at the Linguistics Department Open House, UC Berkeley. Lapierre, Myriam. (2020b).Two types of [NT]s in Panra: Evidence from production and perception. Poster presented at the 8th Annual Meeting on Phonology, UC Santa Cruz. Lapierre, Myriam&Susan Lin. (2019a). Cues to Panra Nasal-Oral Stop Sequence Perception.Proceedings of the 2019 Congress of International Phonetic Sciences. Melbourne, Australia. Lapierre, Myriam& Susan Lin. (2019b).Cues to Panra Nasal-Oral Stop Sequence Perception. Talk presented at the 2019 Congress of International Phonetic Sciences, Melbourne, Australia. Lapierre, Myriam. (2019).Two types of [NT]s in Panra: Evidence from production and perception. Talk presented at Third Symposium on Amazonian Languages, UC Berkeley. Lapierre, Myriam& Susan Lin. (2018).Patterns of nasal coarticulation in Panar. Poster presented at the 16th Conference on Laboratory Phonology, Lisbon, Portugal. Lin, Susan &Myriam Lapierre. (2020).Articulatory patterns in contrasting nasal-stop sequences in Panra. Talk presented at the 94th Annual Meeting of the LSA, New Orleans, Louisiana.        Last Modified: 01/11/2024       Submitted by: MyriamLapierre]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
