<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Correlating Device Performance and Interfacial Properties for Weyl Spintronics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>298154.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>298154</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>uvarshne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925385</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This grant supports research into understanding new mechanisms by which electrical currents can be used to switch the magnetic orientation of thin magnetic layers in devices for data processing and storage. The use of current pulses to alter magnetism is central to the operating principles of a variety of electronic and spintronic devices.  However, new materials systems are needed to reduce the power consumption required for magnetic switching and to enable future device scaling. This award supports fundamental research to identify quantum materials known as Weyl semimetals that enable significant improvements in the efficiency of current-induced magnetic switching. The project will characterize a variety of Weyl semimetals for use in magnetic devices with emphasis on understanding how the switching metrics are influenced by the interfacial properties between the Weyl semimetal and the magnetic layer. The project will also identify how Weyl semimetals can be used to enable switching of perpendicular magnets to facilitate emerging device concepts. The insights into how new quantum materials can reduce power consumption in electronic and magnetic devices may lead to new advances in electronics and computing devices, providing broad societal benefit. The students’ research training enabled by this project will serve to advance the U.S. economic interests by providing them with the experimental skill set needed to contribute to the technological sector.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This collaborative project will lay the groundwork for low-power spintronic devices through a series of research activities aimed at providing a detailed understanding of spin-orbit torques generated by Weyl semimetals. The charge-to-spin conversion process will be thoroughly characterized at a series of interfaces between Weyl semimetals and ferromagnetic metals to quantify torque efficiencies. The interfacial properties of these same structures will be characterized using resonant x-ray reflectivity, a technique that allows for both the elemental concentration and magnetization to be determined as a function of depth across the interfaces. The correlations between spin-orbit torque efficiency and the composition and magnetic properties of the interfaces will elucidate the roles of intrinsic (Weyl physics) and extrinsic (non-idealities at the interfaces) contributions to the torques. These activities will yield a thorough understanding of spin-orbit torques across real interfaces in device-based structures fabricated using industry-relevant deposition processes. The research will also identify novel spin-orbit torques, including those associated with an out-of-plane spin polarization, enabled by the unique properties of Weyl semimetals and quantify torque metrics relevant for non-volatile magnetic memory devices and thermally driven stochastic oscillators, where the magnetization of the free magnetic layer is controlled via spin-orbit torques. Through these research activities, this project will advance progress toward employing Weyl semimetals in emerging electronic and spintronic device architectures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031871</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Axel</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoffmann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Axel F Hoffmann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[axelh@illinois.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000800482</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>URBANA</CityName>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S WRIGHT ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y8CWNJRCNN91</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Board of Trustees of the University of Illinois]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S. Wright St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>107E</Code>
<Text>Magnetics and spin electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~298154</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Professors Steven May (Drexel University) and Axel Hoffmann (University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign) recently completed research for award ECCS-2031870, studying the deposition of heterostructures containing Weyl semimetals and ferromagnets and the generation of spin-orbit torques from these Weyl thin films. A central challenge within the field of spintronics is to identify material systems capable of efficiently converting charge currents to spin currents that can enable low-power magnetization switching within the ferromagnetic materials used to store information. To this end, spin-orbit torques generated by passing currents through topological insulators have recently emerged as a promising strategy for magnetization switching. However, charge-to-spin conversion processes in other topological materials, such as Weyl semimetals, are less understood.</span><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>To fill in this knowledge gap and evaluate their potential for spintronic devices, the researchers identified deposition conditions to produce thin films of topological semimetals Mn<sub>3</sub>Sn, MoTe<sub>2</sub>, and FeSn using molecular beam epitaxy and co-sputtering. After establishing conditions to yield continuous and phase pure topological films, the teams synthesized heterostructures consisting of the Weyl semimetals and ferromagnetic metals such as Ni<sub>80</sub>Fe<sub>20</sub>, Fe and Co. The structural properties of the heterostructures were characterized in detail to understand phase stability, the presence of strain, and, importantly for devices, interfacial roughness and intermixing. Project highlights related to film deposition include the growth of single crystal and continuous FeSn films using ferromagnetic Fe and Co buffer layers, deposition of Mn<sub>3</sub>Sn films with controlled crystallographic orientations, and stabilization of the topological 1T&rsquo; phase of MoTe<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;in sputter-deposited films.</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Heterostructures containing the topological films interfaced with ferromagnetic layers were characterized using spin-torque ferromagnetic resonance measurements to quantify spin-orbit torques. A novel combination of conventional in-plane damping-like torques, unconventional out-of-plane damping-like torques, and unconventional in-plane field-like torques were observed in MoTe<sub>2</sub>/Ni<sub>80</sub>Fe<sub>20</sub>&nbsp;structures. While the conventional in-plane torques exhibit a decreasing efficiency as the thickness of the MoTe<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;layer is decreased, the unconventional torques are largely independent of the MoTe<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;thickness. This indicates that these unconventional torques are likely generated at the interface rather than the bulk of the MoTe<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;layer. Furthermore, MoTe<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;films grown by chemical vapor deposition show only conventional spin-orbit torques, suggesting that the observed strain in the MoTe<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;sputter-deposited films is likely important for generating the unconventional torques. The unconventional out-of-plane torques generated by the MoTe<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;films are promising for applications in spintronic devices where out-of-plane magnetization switching is required. Spin-orbit torques from epitaxial FeSn/ferromagnetic metal structures were also measured. In this system, conventional spin-orbit torques with efficiencies of approximately 0.3 were observed.</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>This grant provided the primary support for education and training of two PhD students, partial support for one PhD student and incorporated a postdoctoral researcher into the team as well. Additionally, six undergraduate students participated in this project, including multiple female students and students from under-represented minority groups. Two of these undergraduates are planning to enter doctoral studies in the coming year, two others are now fully employed as engineers. The project also supported outreach activities in which two high school students carried out work in a lab at Drexel as part of their school science fair competition. Detailed research results have been disseminated to the research community and public through conference presentations, submitted manuscripts and manuscripts currently in preparation.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/20/2023<br> Modified by: Axel&nbsp;F&nbsp;Hoffmann</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Professors Steven May (Drexel University) and Axel Hoffmann (University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign) recently completed research for award ECCS-2031870, studying the deposition of heterostructures containing Weyl semimetals and ferromagnets and the generation of spin-orbit torques from these Weyl thin films. A central challenge within the field of spintronics is to identify material systems capable of efficiently converting charge currents to spin currents that can enable low-power magnetization switching within the ferromagnetic materials used to store information. To this end, spin-orbit torques generated by passing currents through topological insulators have recently emerged as a promising strategy for magnetization switching. However, charge-to-spin conversion processes in other topological materials, such as Weyl semimetals, are less understood.      To fill in this knowledge gap and evaluate their potential for spintronic devices, the researchers identified deposition conditions to produce thin films of topological semimetals Mn3Sn, MoTe2, and FeSn using molecular beam epitaxy and co-sputtering. After establishing conditions to yield continuous and phase pure topological films, the teams synthesized heterostructures consisting of the Weyl semimetals and ferromagnetic metals such as Ni80Fe20, Fe and Co. The structural properties of the heterostructures were characterized in detail to understand phase stability, the presence of strain, and, importantly for devices, interfacial roughness and intermixing. Project highlights related to film deposition include the growth of single crystal and continuous FeSn films using ferromagnetic Fe and Co buffer layers, deposition of Mn3Sn films with controlled crystallographic orientations, and stabilization of the topological 1T phase of MoTe2in sputter-deposited films.      Heterostructures containing the topological films interfaced with ferromagnetic layers were characterized using spin-torque ferromagnetic resonance measurements to quantify spin-orbit torques. A novel combination of conventional in-plane damping-like torques, unconventional out-of-plane damping-like torques, and unconventional in-plane field-like torques were observed in MoTe2/Ni80Fe20structures. While the conventional in-plane torques exhibit a decreasing efficiency as the thickness of the MoTe2layer is decreased, the unconventional torques are largely independent of the MoTe2thickness. This indicates that these unconventional torques are likely generated at the interface rather than the bulk of the MoTe2layer. Furthermore, MoTe2films grown by chemical vapor deposition show only conventional spin-orbit torques, suggesting that the observed strain in the MoTe2sputter-deposited films is likely important for generating the unconventional torques. The unconventional out-of-plane torques generated by the MoTe2films are promising for applications in spintronic devices where out-of-plane magnetization switching is required. Spin-orbit torques from epitaxial FeSn/ferromagnetic metal structures were also measured. In this system, conventional spin-orbit torques with efficiencies of approximately 0.3 were observed.      This grant provided the primary support for education and training of two PhD students, partial support for one PhD student and incorporated a postdoctoral researcher into the team as well. Additionally, six undergraduate students participated in this project, including multiple female students and students from under-represented minority groups. Two of these undergraduates are planning to enter doctoral studies in the coming year, two others are now fully employed as engineers. The project also supported outreach activities in which two high school students carried out work in a lab at Drexel as part of their school science fair competition. Detailed research results have been disseminated to the research community and public through conference presentations, submitted manuscripts and manuscripts currently in preparation.        Last Modified: 12/20/2023       Submitted by: AxelFHoffmann]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
