<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Spillover of coffee diseases into forest ecosystems and consequences for forest plant communities]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Betsy Von Holle</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mvonholl@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924974</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Many agricultural lands and protected natural areas are physically adjacent to each other and interact with each other, yet there have been few studies of how agricultural and natural ecosystems influence each other and what the consequences of these interactions are for both the effectiveness of agricultural management and the conservation of natural lands. Spillover is a term from disease ecology recently applied more generally to describe the movement and effects of organisms as they cross habitat boundaries. This project will advance understanding of the importance of spillover between agriculture and natural habitats and of the role of birds as well as wind in the dispersal of plant-associated fungi. By comparing fungi and plant disease between two types of coffee management, sun and shade, this research will inform decisions on the relative benefits of these agricultural strategies for coffee fungal disease management and for minimizing negative effects of spillover. This project will train a graduate student and two undergraduate students from underrepresented groups in science as well as provide outreach to student and community groups. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The field of phylogenetic ecology provides a clear framework for predicting patterns and effect size of pathogen spillover from one host to others that can be applied to the spillover of pathogens from agricultural to natural systems. This research will estimate fungal movement by wind and birds, measure disease incidence in the forest, and assess effects of coffee on native forest plant communities by comparing community composition of understory plants at plots near and away from coffee. This project is high risk-high reward in its application of a phylogenetic framework to the community ecology of fungal spillover, its measurement of bi-directional movement and spillover from agriculture to natural habitats, and its examination of the role of birds as well as wind in the dispersal of plant-associated fungi. By examining the coffee-forest interface at sites where coffee is an introduced species yet closely related to many understory plant species, this project will test two integral hypotheses of phylogenetic community ecology: 1) more closely related hosts share more pathogens and disease than distantly related hosts; and 2) more closely related pathogens share more host species than less closely related pathogens. Testing the utility of a phylogenetic framework for predicting disease and plant community composition is important for developing a predictive understanding of biotic interactions between agricultural and natural plant communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037121</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
<LastName>Aldrich-Wolfe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Laura Aldrich-Wolfe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[laura.aldrichwolfe@ndsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000457723</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Dakota State University Fargo</Name>
<CityName>FARGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>581055750</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7012318045</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1310 BOLLEY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ND00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EZ4WPGRE1RD5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH DAKOTA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EZ4WPGRE1RD5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Dakota State University Fargo]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
<ZipCode>581086050</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ND00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1128</Code>
<Text>Population &amp; Community Ecology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This two-year study assessed the potential for wind and birds to move fungi from agricultural sites to adjacent forest, influencing the fungal communities of the understory in these forests, the types and prevalence of plant diseases, and ultimately the community composition of forest plant communities. By documenting the fungal propagules carried by birds and air currents and comparing them with those present in and on leaves in the tropical forest understory and in adjacent coffee fields, the researchers were able to determine which fungi were likely increasing in abundance in plants in forests as a result of proximity to coffee and dispersal from coffee via birds or wind, and to construct models to predict impacts of these changes in fungal communities on the composition of the adjacent forest understory.</p> <p>Findings from this research suggest that crops, particularly those grown at high density, may shape fungal and plant communities of adjacent natural areas and act as reservoirs for plant disease in protected lands. Birds as well as wind may disperse plant-associated fungi, as well as dispersing different types of plant-associated fungi, so that impacts of agriculture on fungal communities of adjacent natural areas likely also depend on the abundance and diversity of animal communities that use both land types. Protection of natural areas likely entails improved monitoring of movement, especially of microorganisms, across crop boundaries, as well as consideration of the influence of crop management.</p> <p>This research project provided for the training of two graduate and three undergraduate students, two of whom were from underrepresented groups in STEM disciplines. In addition to data and project management skills, students acquired valuable transferable skills, such as DNA extraction, use of bioinformatics pipelines, detection of microorganisms using DNA barcodes, and isolation and propagation of fungi in culture. The project strengthened cross-cultural ties between Costa Ricans and U.S. researchers and citizens, through project planning and implementation with Costa Rican scientists, facilitating visits to the U.S. by two Costa Rican scientists, formation of a field team of U.S. and Costa Rican birders, use of the Las Cruces Biological Station in southern Costa Rica, and outreach to U.S. K-12 and undergraduate students and Costa Rican farmers and the local community. New fungi discovered during the course of the project have the potential to be developed for biocontrol of diseases in agriculture.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/29/2023<br> Modified by: Laura&nbsp;Aldrich-Wolfe</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This two-year study assessed the potential for wind and birds to move fungi from agricultural sites to adjacent forest, influencing the fungal communities of the understory in these forests, the types and prevalence of plant diseases, and ultimately the community composition of forest plant communities. By documenting the fungal propagules carried by birds and air currents and comparing them with those present in and on leaves in the tropical forest understory and in adjacent coffee fields, the researchers were able to determine which fungi were likely increasing in abundance in plants in forests as a result of proximity to coffee and dispersal from coffee via birds or wind, and to construct models to predict impacts of these changes in fungal communities on the composition of the adjacent forest understory.   Findings from this research suggest that crops, particularly those grown at high density, may shape fungal and plant communities of adjacent natural areas and act as reservoirs for plant disease in protected lands. Birds as well as wind may disperse plant-associated fungi, as well as dispersing different types of plant-associated fungi, so that impacts of agriculture on fungal communities of adjacent natural areas likely also depend on the abundance and diversity of animal communities that use both land types. Protection of natural areas likely entails improved monitoring of movement, especially of microorganisms, across crop boundaries, as well as consideration of the influence of crop management.   This research project provided for the training of two graduate and three undergraduate students, two of whom were from underrepresented groups in STEM disciplines. In addition to data and project management skills, students acquired valuable transferable skills, such as DNA extraction, use of bioinformatics pipelines, detection of microorganisms using DNA barcodes, and isolation and propagation of fungi in culture. The project strengthened cross-cultural ties between Costa Ricans and U.S. researchers and citizens, through project planning and implementation with Costa Rican scientists, facilitating visits to the U.S. by two Costa Rican scientists, formation of a field team of U.S. and Costa Rican birders, use of the Las Cruces Biological Station in southern Costa Rica, and outreach to U.S. K-12 and undergraduate students and Costa Rican farmers and the local community. New fungi discovered during the course of the project have the potential to be developed for biocontrol of diseases in agriculture.     Last Modified: 11/29/2023       Submitted by: LauraAldrich-Wolfe]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
