<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[27th Annual National EPSCoR Conference, Portland Maine]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>700672.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>700672</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>OIA-Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jose Colom</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jcolom@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927088</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The 27th NSF EPSCoR National Conference supports the work and mission of NSF EPSCoR. The goals of NSF EPSCoR are to increase research capacity, strengthen STEM education, and advance science and engineering in jurisdictions that have historically received limited funding from NSF. Under the overarching theme of “Translating Stakeholder Needs into Impactful Research Outcomes,” the event will focus on and demonstrate NSF EPSCoR's unique ability to engage stakeholders through broadening impacts, community science projects, educational opportunities, and partnerships. Each jurisdiction will be asked to present on their programs that can be used as national models for creating strategic stakeholder engagement, leading to improved scientific research impacts and educational outcomes. In addition, the conference will serve as a platform for attendees to learn more about NSF EPSCoR and funding opportunities with a special emphasis on Track-2 and 4 proposals. Other strands will include broadening participation in STEM, economic development, convergence science, “pandemic” best practices, and professional development for students. There will be a poster session for students, and a community science showcase for all participants. This conference will be evaluated to determine the effectiveness of the program, and also to help improve future events.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2038037</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Khodadad</FirstName>
<LastName>Varahramyan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Khodadad Varahramyan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[varahramyan@maine.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000174373</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maine</Name>
<CityName>ORONO</CityName>
<ZipCode>044695717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2075811484</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5717 CORBETT HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PB3AJE5ZEJ59</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MAINE SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maine]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<ZipCode>044695717</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9168</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Outreach and Workshops</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9168</Code>
<Text>EPSCOR OUTREACH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~700672</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Under the theme &ldquo;Translating Stakeholder Needs into Impactful Research Outcomes,&rdquo; the 27<sup>th</sup> NSF EPSCoR National Conference took place in Portland, Maine on November 13-16, 2022. The event&rsquo;s Program and Logistics Committee focused on six main objectives (Community Science, Broadening Participation and Collaboration in STEM, Economic Competitiveness, Convergence Science, Pandemic Best Practices, and Professional Development for Postdocs, Graduate and Undergraduate Students) to ensure a successful and productive event which both supported and advanced NSF EPSCoR&rsquo;s mission and values. There were 476 individuals who registered for the conference, with 435 attending.</span></p> <p><span>The external evaluator, SustainaMetrix, was present throughout the conference and conducted a post-survey measuring the quality of the event, garnering a total of 186 respondents. Overall, 48% of respondents rated the overall quality of the conference &ldquo;excellent&rdquo; and 42% &ldquo;very good.&rdquo; 56% of respondents also reported they were, &ldquo;extremely likely to implement new insights from the conference.&rdquo; The <em>27th NSF EPSCoR National Conference External Evaluation Report,</em></span><span> </span><span>which was delivered to NSF in 2023, and has since been shared with Nebraska EPSCoR, was very informative and noted key observations that future NSF conferences may benefit from.</span></p> <p><span>Stakeholder engagement was a key focus area of the conference. Many of the morning plenary sessions touched on stakeholder engagement as well as the broader impacts of EPSCoR programming, community science, and nurturing collaborative and inclusive science. Professor Damian Brady, University of Maine, conducted a plenary <em><span>The Impact of SEANET on Maine&rsquo;s Economy &amp;</span></em><span> <em>Workforce</em></span> (42% of respondents rated &ldquo;extremely relevant&rdquo;), which was a shining example of successful stakeholder engagement and impactful broader impacts. Additionally, organizers dedicated one of the five afternoon breakout tracks to stakeholder engagement, with six sessions held in the track held over two days. Lastly, a half-day <em>Community Science Workshop</em> was hosted by Professor Linda Silka, University of Maine, and Professor <span>M&oacute;nica Ram&iacute;rez-Andreotta, University of Arizona, prior to the official conference start (41% of respondents rated &ldquo;excellent&rdquo;).</span></span></p> <p><span>Jurisdictional successes and best practices were highlighted during plenary and breakout sessions, with Brady&rsquo;s plenary on SEANET as a prime example. Other sessions like <em>State EPSCoR Governance</em> were reviewed widely as &ldquo;extremely useful&rdquo; and should benefit many EPSCoR jurisdictions. The Workforce Development Track, which included panels like <em>Best Practices for Engaging Underrepresented Minorities in Community Science</em> (59% of respondents rated &ldquo;extremely useful&rdquo;) highlighted successes across EPSCoR jurisdictions. Plenaries like <em>Co-created Community Science to Cultivate Justice, Action, and Resiliency</em></span><span> (49% of respondents rated &ldquo;extremely relevant&rdquo;) and other breakout sessions like <em><span>Best Practices for Undergraduate Mentoring and Supporting Diversity </span></em><span>(66% of respondents rated &ldquo;extremely useful&rdquo;) gave attendees tools and insights into how to nurture diversity and inclusion within their programs.</span></span></p> <p><span>Prior to the event, conference organizers conducted an outreach campaign inviting faculty at primarily undergraduate and/or minority serving institutions in EPSCoR jurisdictions to attend. Hundreds of faculty and other researchers were contacted, and while responses were mixed, valuable lessons were learned. In the future, it is highly recommended that first-time attendees be budgeted separately from jurisdictional dignitaries to streamline the recruiting and travel approvals for these individuals, and this guidance has been shared with Nebraska EPSCoR. </span></p> <p><span>Another important priority for conference organizers was to elevate students and junior faculty, with independent tracks organized for both groups. A Junior Faculty track included sessions like <em>How to Manage a Successful Track-2</em> (58% of respondents rated &ldquo;extremely useful&rdquo;) and <em>Strategies for Achieving Tenure </em>(50% of respondents rated &ldquo;extremely useful&rdquo;). This track was especially important for supporting faculty who may have never participated in EPSCoR programming or only in a limited capacity, with pathways for deeper engagement communicated. A dedicated Student Track was offered in response to feedback received from past national conferences, where students were encouraged to attend and engage with peers and the broader EPSCoR research community. This track included a workshop with the Alan Alda Center and a dedicated poster session that highlighted research from students and other early career researchers.</span></p> <p><span>Health and safety were a priority for organizers as COVID-19 loomed over every decision being made in the planning process. The most important action taken was delaying the conference twice until state and national health advisories were lifted. Preserving the in-person aspect of the conference proved important, given attendees continued conversations in between sessions and into the evenings.</span></p> <p><span>Based on external evaluation, the 27<sup>th</sup> NSF EPSCoR National Conference was a success, delivering on the thematic objectives of driving stakeholder engagement and broader impacts and nurturing a more diverse and inclusive EPSCoR research community. This conference and its external evaluation report may serve as a resource that future conference organizers can model and benefit from.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/13/2023<br> Modified by: Kody&nbsp;Varahramyan</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701286920309_Conference_Photos_08--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701286920309_Conference_Photos_08--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sandra Richardson Welcomes Conference"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701286920309_Conference_Photos_08--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sandra Richardson Welcomes Conference"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Sandra Richardson greets attendees to kick off the 27th NSF EPSCoR National Conference.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Maine EPSCoR</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kody&nbsp;Varahramyan <div class="imageTitle">Sandra Richardson Welcomes Conference</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701286777508_Conference_Photos_5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701286777508_Conference_Photos_5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Career Path Panel"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701286777508_Conference_Photos_5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Career Path Panel"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Panel for the student track discusses their career paths outside of academia during the 27th NSF EPSCoR National Conference.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Maine EPSCoR</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kody&nbsp;Varahramyan <div class="imageTitle">Career Path Panel</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701287249810_Conference_Photos_4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701287249810_Conference_Photos_4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="27th NSF EPSCoR Conference Poster Presentation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701287249810_Conference_Photos_4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="27th NSF EPSCoR Conference Poster Presentation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Graduate student presents their poster during the 27th NSF EPSCoR National Conference's poster session.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Maine EPSCoR</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kody&nbsp;Varahramyan <div class="imageTitle">27th NSF EPSCoR Conference Poster Presentation</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701287160625_Conference_Photos_3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701287160625_Conference_Photos_3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Opening Land Acknowledgement & Wabanaki Traditional Storytelling by John Bear Mitchell"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701287160625_Conference_Photos_3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Opening Land Acknowledgement & Wabanaki Traditional Storytelling by John Bear Mitchell"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">John Bear Mitchell (University of Maine and WaYS) delivers the land acknowledgement and tells a traditional Wabanaki story about Portland, ME.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Maine EPSCoR</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kody&nbsp;Varahramyan <div class="imageTitle">Opening Land Acknowledgement & Wabanaki Traditional Storytelling by John Bear Mitchell</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701286854496_Conference_Photos_07--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701286854496_Conference_Photos_07--rgov-800width.jpg" title="27th NSF ESPCoR National Conference Attendees"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701286854496_Conference_Photos_07--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="27th NSF ESPCoR National Conference Attendees"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Attendees at the 27th NSF EPSCoR National Conference gather in Merrill Auditorium.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Maine EPSCoR</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kody&nbsp;Varahramyan <div class="imageTitle">27th NSF ESPCoR National Conference Attendees</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701287019404_Conference_Photos_10--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701287019404_Conference_Photos_10--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Pre-conference Workshop on Community Science"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2038037/2038037_10703416_1701287019404_Conference_Photos_10--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Pre-conference Workshop on Community Science"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Attendees for the pre-conference Community Science Workshop discuss.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Maine EPSCoR</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kody&nbsp;Varahramyan <div class="imageTitle">Pre-conference Workshop on Community Science</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Under the theme Translating Stakeholder Needs into Impactful Research Outcomes, the 27th NSF EPSCoR National Conference took place in Portland, Maine on November 13-16, 2022. The events Program and Logistics Committee focused on six main objectives (Community Science, Broadening Participation and Collaboration in STEM, Economic Competitiveness, Convergence Science, Pandemic Best Practices, and Professional Development for Postdocs, Graduate and Undergraduate Students) to ensure a successful and productive event which both supported and advanced NSF EPSCoRs mission and values. There were 476 individuals who registered for the conference, with 435 attending.   The external evaluator, SustainaMetrix, was present throughout the conference and conducted a post-survey measuring the quality of the event, garnering a total of 186 respondents. Overall, 48% of respondents rated the overall quality of the conference excellent and 42% very good. 56% of respondents also reported they were, extremely likely to implement new insights from the conference. The 27th NSF EPSCoR National Conference External Evaluation Report, which was delivered to NSF in 2023, and has since been shared with Nebraska EPSCoR, was very informative and noted key observations that future NSF conferences may benefit from.   Stakeholder engagement was a key focus area of the conference. Many of the morning plenary sessions touched on stakeholder engagement as well as the broader impacts of EPSCoR programming, community science, and nurturing collaborative and inclusive science. Professor Damian Brady, University of Maine, conducted a plenary The Impact of SEANET on Maines Economy & Workforce (42% of respondents rated extremely relevant), which was a shining example of successful stakeholder engagement and impactful broader impacts. Additionally, organizers dedicated one of the five afternoon breakout tracks to stakeholder engagement, with six sessions held in the track held over two days. Lastly, a half-day Community Science Workshop was hosted by Professor Linda Silka, University of Maine, and Professor Mnica Ramrez-Andreotta, University of Arizona, prior to the official conference start (41% of respondents rated excellent).   Jurisdictional successes and best practices were highlighted during plenary and breakout sessions, with Bradys plenary on SEANET as a prime example. Other sessions like State EPSCoR Governance were reviewed widely as extremely useful and should benefit many EPSCoR jurisdictions. The Workforce Development Track, which included panels like Best Practices for Engaging Underrepresented Minorities in Community Science (59% of respondents rated extremely useful) highlighted successes across EPSCoR jurisdictions. Plenaries like Co-created Community Science to Cultivate Justice, Action, and Resiliency (49% of respondents rated extremely relevant) and other breakout sessions like Best Practices for Undergraduate Mentoring and Supporting Diversity (66% of respondents rated extremely useful) gave attendees tools and insights into how to nurture diversity and inclusion within their programs.   Prior to the event, conference organizers conducted an outreach campaign inviting faculty at primarily undergraduate and/or minority serving institutions in EPSCoR jurisdictions to attend. Hundreds of faculty and other researchers were contacted, and while responses were mixed, valuable lessons were learned. In the future, it is highly recommended that first-time attendees be budgeted separately from jurisdictional dignitaries to streamline the recruiting and travel approvals for these individuals, and this guidance has been shared with Nebraska EPSCoR.    Another important priority for conference organizers was to elevate students and junior faculty, with independent tracks organized for both groups. A Junior Faculty track included sessions like How to Manage a Successful Track-2 (58% of respondents rated extremely useful) and Strategies for Achieving Tenure (50% of respondents rated extremely useful). This track was especially important for supporting faculty who may have never participated in EPSCoR programming or only in a limited capacity, with pathways for deeper engagement communicated. A dedicated Student Track was offered in response to feedback received from past national conferences, where students were encouraged to attend and engage with peers and the broader EPSCoR research community. This track included a workshop with the Alan Alda Center and a dedicated poster session that highlighted research from students and other early career researchers.   Health and safety were a priority for organizers as COVID-19 loomed over every decision being made in the planning process. The most important action taken was delaying the conference twice until state and national health advisories were lifted. Preserving the in-person aspect of the conference proved important, given attendees continued conversations in between sessions and into the evenings.   Based on external evaluation, the 27th NSF EPSCoR National Conference was a success, delivering on the thematic objectives of driving stakeholder engagement and broader impacts and nurturing a more diverse and inclusive EPSCoR research community. This conference and its external evaluation report may serve as a resource that future conference organizers can model and benefit from.        Last Modified: 12/13/2023       Submitted by: KodyVarahramyan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
