<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[The Divergent Effects of Conflict on Ethnic Voting]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>43653.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>43653</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lee Walker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lwalker@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project asks what determines whether salient ethnic divisions from conflict continue to be the source of political mobilization in post-conflict elections. The PIs identify an empirical puzzle that suggests that even an ethnic group heavily affected by conflict may choose representation through a national rather than an ethnic party. The key to the puzzle lies in the different experiences of conflict that bred different rebel-civilian relationships. The PIs theorize that the experience of 'in-group betrayal' (siding with state counterinsurgency rather than ethnic rebels) during ethnic war can undermine the perceived legitimacy of ethno-national political movement and thereby disincentivize ethnic mobilization in post-conflict elections. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While political scientists have linked elections in post-conflict environments as arenas for renewed violence, little is known about how wartime identity politics might have influenced these outcomes. This project connects ethnic politics literature with conflict literature by drawing attention to how the rebel-civilian relationship affects post-conflict electoral politics.  The PIs propose that experience of harm inflicted by in-group rebel leaders affect the likelihood of ethnic political mobilization among conflict-affected groups. Methodologically, the PIs use a survey experiment procedure to assess the validity of the causal mechanism of 'in-group betrayal' in a highly sensitive political environment. Identifying the source of cross-ethnic political mobilization after a violent conflict has important implications for post-war reconstruction. In line with the U.S. efforts for peaceful transition of war-torn states, this project contributes to making better peace-building strategies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2046572</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Laitin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David D Laitin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dlaitin@stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000169426</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>STANFORD</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 JANE STANFORD WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HJD6G4D6TJY5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[450 Jane Stanford Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>118Y</Code>
<Text>Security &amp; Preparedness</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~43653</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Outcome Report for NSF Grant #&nbsp;2046572</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>PI: David Laitin</p> <p>PhD trainee: Jiwon Kim</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Introduction</strong></p> <p>Since the 2021 military coup, politics in Myanmar has grown more tumultuous, particularly in the ethnic minority areas. The Myanmar military, ethnic armed organizations (EAOs) seeking self-determination, and the pro-democracy movement led by the National Unity Government (NUG) all vie for control in these areas.</p> <p>Against this backdrop, some ethnic minority populations have joined the pro-democracy resistance, while others remain neutral. The question arises whether ethnic minorities will support and trust the NUG or perceive it as another Bamar-driven initiative.&nbsp;</p> <p>A key distinction in the ethnic minority areas is the presence of over twenty EAOs, offering security and social services such as education, healthcare, and dispute resolution. This raises questions about whether exposure to EAO administration influences perceptions of other political actors, particularly the NUG.</p> <p>To explore this, the project analyzes an original online survey targeting ethnic minority areas in Myanmar. Utilizing Facebook ads for recruitment and providing translations into Burmese and six minority languages, the survey collected responses from 1,113 individuals representing 35 ethnic groups. Participants were asked about their beliefs regarding the NUG's commitment to their ethnic group's interests and their exposure to governance activities by the EAO they are most familiar with.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>A High Level of Trust for NUG</strong></p> <p>Results of the survey shows that in general, trust for the NUG is high among ethnic minority communities. Out of all the respondents, 69% said they trust the NUG and 79% said the NUG will be effective in providing social services to their ethnic group&rsquo;s area.</p> <p>People were also mostly confident that the NUG will care for the interests of their ethnic group or ethnic minorities in general. 70% said the NUG will care for their ethnic group&rsquo;s interest, while 49% said the NUG will place their ethnic group&rsquo;s people in positions of power. 51% said it will prioritize the interests of Bamar and ethnic minority people equally.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>[Figure 1]</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>EAO Governance and Trust for EAOs</strong></p> <p>Meanwhile, people in ethnic minority areas have a moderate level of exposure to governance provision by ethnic armed organizations (EAOs). About 33-38% of respondents said they have either directly experienced or know someone who has experienced their EAO providing education and medical care, solving community problems, and dealing with crimes and drugs.</p> <p>Exposure to negative activities of governance&mdash;such as taxation, forcible recruitment, engaging in business with the Myanmar military (Tatmadaw), and violence against civilians&mdash;was much lower in general. Although 30% have directly or indirectly experienced taxation, other activities only had 8-15% respondents who have direct or indirect exposure.</p> <p>A significant correlation was found between exposure to EAO governance and trust for the EAOs. Individuals who had more exposure to positive governance activities had higher trust for the EAOs, and those with more negative exposure had lower trust for the EAOs. The relationships were true even after taking into account respondents&rsquo; strength of ethnic identity, exposure to violence by Myanmar military, and ethno-political beliefs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>[Figure 2]</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>EAO Governance and Trust for NUG</strong></p> <p>The survey shows that EAO governance affects trust not only for the EAOs but also for the NUG. More exposure to positive EAO governance predicts slightly lower trust for the NUG, as long as the EAO is not seen as explicitly supportive of the NUG. If the respondent thinks that their EAO is neutral towards the NUG, then going from an average exposure score of 0 (never heard) to 3 (experienced first hand) moves their average perception of NUG from 5 (somewhat positive) to 4 (neither positive nor negative). This is true even after taking into account respondent&rsquo;s exposure to NUG governance, belief in democracy, strength of ethnic identity, and other demographic variables.</p> <p>This is a significant result considering the near universal popularity of the NUG in Myanmar. This means that those who are more used to receiving social services and governance from EAOs are less likely to trust that the NUG will care for their ethnic group&rsquo;s interest if it gains control of the country.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>[Figure 3]&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Implications</strong></p> <p>This study sheds important light into the political implications of ethnic rebel governance. While it has been well known in the literature that rebels can act like a state and perform governance functions, its political implications have not been studied well. This paper is one of the first few to highlight that rebel governance has political influence on the civilians who are exposed to it.</p> <p>The study also brings significant implications for the future of Myanmar politics. The findings suggest that ethnic armed organizations are important political actors with a high level of trust among the ethnic minority population. Moreover, they imply that the NUG would benefit from directly cooperating with the EAOs in order to build trust among ethnic minority people.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 01/17/2024<br> Modified by: David&nbsp;D&nbsp;Laitin</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2046572/2046572_10721526_1705509353343_h2a_m1_margeff_FEmodel--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2046572/2046572_10721526_1705509353343_h2a_m1_margeff_FEmodel--rgov-800width.png" title="[Figure 3] Change in Perception of the NUG based on Reported Exposure to Positive EAO Governance Activities"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2046572/2046572_10721526_1705509353343_h2a_m1_margeff_FEmodel--rgov-66x44.png" alt="[Figure 3] Change in Perception of the NUG based on Reported Exposure to Positive EAO Governance Activities"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jiwon Lee Kim</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">David&nbsp;D&nbsp;Laitin <div class="imageTitle">[Figure 3] Change in Perception of the NUG based on Reported Exposure to Positive EAO Governance Activities</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2046572/2046572_10721526_1705508865636_EAO_likert_5q--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2046572/2046572_10721526_1705508865636_EAO_likert_5q--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="[Figure 1] Trust for the NUG among Ethnic Minorities"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2046572/2046572_10721526_1705508865636_EAO_likert_5q--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="[Figure 1] Trust for the NUG among Ethnic Minorities"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jiwon Lee Kim</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">David&nbsp;D&nbsp;Laitin <div class="imageTitle">[Figure 1] Trust for the NUG among Ethnic Minorities</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2046572/2046572_10721526_1705508889602_EAO_gov_12q--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2046572/2046572_10721526_1705508889602_EAO_gov_12q--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="[Figure 2] Reported Exposure to EAO Governance Activities"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2046572/2046572_10721526_1705508889602_EAO_gov_12q--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="[Figure 2] Reported Exposure to EAO Governance Activities"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jiwon Lee Kim</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">David&nbsp;D&nbsp;Laitin <div class="imageTitle">[Figure 2] Reported Exposure to EAO Governance Activities</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Project Outcome Report for NSF Grant #2046572      PI: David Laitin   PhD trainee: Jiwon Kim      Introduction   Since the 2021 military coup, politics in Myanmar has grown more tumultuous, particularly in the ethnic minority areas. The Myanmar military, ethnic armed organizations (EAOs) seeking self-determination, and the pro-democracy movement led by the National Unity Government (NUG) all vie for control in these areas.   Against this backdrop, some ethnic minority populations have joined the pro-democracy resistance, while others remain neutral. The question arises whether ethnic minorities will support and trust the NUG or perceive it as another Bamar-driven initiative.   A key distinction in the ethnic minority areas is the presence of over twenty EAOs, offering security and social services such as education, healthcare, and dispute resolution. This raises questions about whether exposure to EAO administration influences perceptions of other political actors, particularly the NUG.   To explore this, the project analyzes an original online survey targeting ethnic minority areas in Myanmar. Utilizing Facebook ads for recruitment and providing translations into Burmese and six minority languages, the survey collected responses from 1,113 individuals representing 35 ethnic groups. Participants were asked about their beliefs regarding the NUG's commitment to their ethnic group's interests and their exposure to governance activities by the EAO they are most familiar with.      A High Level of Trust for NUG   Results of the survey shows that in general, trust for the NUG is high among ethnic minority communities. Out of all the respondents, 69% said they trust the NUG and 79% said the NUG will be effective in providing social services to their ethnic groups area.   People were also mostly confident that the NUG will care for the interests of their ethnic group or ethnic minorities in general. 70% said the NUG will care for their ethnic groups interest, while 49% said the NUG will place their ethnic groups people in positions of power. 51% said it will prioritize the interests of Bamar and ethnic minority people equally.      [Figure 1]      EAO Governance and Trust for EAOs   Meanwhile, people in ethnic minority areas have a moderate level of exposure to governance provision by ethnic armed organizations (EAOs). About 33-38% of respondents said they have either directly experienced or know someone who has experienced their EAO providing education and medical care, solving community problems, and dealing with crimes and drugs.   Exposure to negative activities of governancesuch as taxation, forcible recruitment, engaging in business with the Myanmar military (Tatmadaw), and violence against civilianswas much lower in general. Although 30% have directly or indirectly experienced taxation, other activities only had 8-15% respondents who have direct or indirect exposure.   A significant correlation was found between exposure to EAO governance and trust for the EAOs. Individuals who had more exposure to positive governance activities had higher trust for the EAOs, and those with more negative exposure had lower trust for the EAOs. The relationships were true even after taking into account respondents strength of ethnic identity, exposure to violence by Myanmar military, and ethno-political beliefs.      [Figure 2]      EAO Governance and Trust for NUG   The survey shows that EAO governance affects trust not only for the EAOs but also for the NUG. More exposure to positive EAO governance predicts slightly lower trust for the NUG, as long as the EAO is not seen as explicitly supportive of the NUG. If the respondent thinks that their EAO is neutral towards the NUG, then going from an average exposure score of 0 (never heard) to 3 (experienced first hand) moves their average perception of NUG from 5 (somewhat positive) to 4 (neither positive nor negative). This is true even after taking into account respondents exposure to NUG governance, belief in democracy, strength of ethnic identity, and other demographic variables.   This is a significant result considering the near universal popularity of the NUG in Myanmar. This means that those who are more used to receiving social services and governance from EAOs are less likely to trust that the NUG will care for their ethnic groups interest if it gains control of the country.      [Figure 3]      Broader Implications   This study sheds important light into the political implications of ethnic rebel governance. While it has been well known in the literature that rebels can act like a state and perform governance functions, its political implications have not been studied well. This paper is one of the first few to highlight that rebel governance has political influence on the civilians who are exposed to it.   The study also brings significant implications for the future of Myanmar politics. The findings suggest that ethnic armed organizations are important political actors with a high level of trust among the ethnic minority population. Moreover, they imply that the NUG would benefit from directly cooperating with the EAOs in order to build trust among ethnic minority people.     Last Modified: 01/17/2024       Submitted by: DavidDLaitin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
