<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[The Hunter and African School Program to Expand Representation in Economics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299106.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299106</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kwabena Gyimah-Brempong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kgyimahb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927466</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award will provide funding for some specific activities of the Hunter College and African School of Economics Program to Expand Representation in Economics (HASPERE) is to increase the pool of economists from underrepresented backgrounds in academia and prestigious jobs in the private sector. To improve participation rates, economics programs need to create a critical mass of minority students, expand mentorship and financial support, and provide students exposure and access to experiences and networks that provide them with the motive and opportunities to pursue further studies and job opportunities in economics. NSF funding will provide resources for student support and for workshops that will help participating students enhance their skills in key methods used in economics research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To ensure that all incoming students have the mathematics and coding skills that are necessary for success throughout the program, HASPERE will include a two-week quantitatively-oriented summer camp to prepare incoming students for the program. During each semester of study, students in the HASPERE program will participate in workshops to enhance their technical skills in core areas of economics beyond the levels of the masters program. Enrolled students will not only benefit from supportive peers within their cohorts, but will also have personal and group mentors. In addition, in the second year of the program, students will be provided research experience opportunities with faculty at Hunter, ASE and a number of nearby institutions where faculty have pledged to support this program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2049841</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leonard</FirstName>
<LastName>Wantchekon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leonard Wantchekon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lwantchekon@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000700024</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Partha</FirstName>
<LastName>Deb</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Partha Deb</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[partha.deb@hunter.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000193772</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY Hunter College</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100655024</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2127724020</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>695 PARK AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EK93EZLLBSC4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Hunter College]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100655024</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[695 Park Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>146Y</Code>
<Text>Build and Broaden</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~299106</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-42bece5c-7fff-6fe9-318b-c21b6daf2dd2"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The lack of racial and ethnic diversity in economics has major consequences for minority communities, the economics profession, and society as a whole. While evidence suggests that&nbsp; economics degrees can lead to lucrative careers and upward mobility, the current underrepresentation in this field exacerbates economic inequality and leads to wider social implications. Racially diverse groups have been shown to outperform homogenous groups in terms of problem solving and creativity. Furthermore, the lack of representation impoverishes policy discourse with implications for innovation, political representation, and even for public health. Consequently, we designed and implemented an academic program designed to address the crisis of diversity in economics. The program provides substantive analytic education in economics anchored by a Master&rsquo;s degree along with substantial research experience and mentoring typically available to participants in pre-doc programs designed to prepare students for PhD programs in Economics or related Public Policy disciplines.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our program identified talented Black and other underrepresented minority (URM) students with undergraduate backgrounds in economics and related quantitative disciplines and offered financial incentives for students to pursue the program. In addition to taking core quantitative courses taught by Hunter College faculty, students took additional courses (topics in Microeconomic theory, Econometrics, Macroeconomics and games and information) designed to prepare students for the rigors of first year PhD courses. These courses were taught by leading scholars in those areas who volunteered their time for this worthy cause. Each student also worked on one or more independent research projects supervised by faculty at Hunter and other nearby universities. As part of the program, students also participated in an intensive writing workshop and a GRE prep class. In addition, all students regularly attended the economics department seminar where researchers from other academic institutions presented their work. During each of these seminar days, the students had the opportunity to chat with the invited researcher exclusively (without Hunter and other faculty present). <br /></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The program admitted 8 students in the first cohort that began coursework in Fall 2021. Among them, 3 have gone on to PhD programs, each with generous fellowships or assistantships. In addition, 2 students in that cohort have prestigious research assistantship positions which will likely lead to outstanding PhD program placements in a year or careers at the Feds or similar institutions. One student from that cohort is in the process of applying to PhD programs.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Among the second cohort of 6 students, 2 obtained prestigious research assistantships. We expect 2 other students to obtain pre-doc or other research assistantship opportunities in Spring 2024 that will position them well to apply to PhD programs in Fall 2024.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The successes of our early cohorts of students in this pipeline program provide confidence that our combination approach of formal education, work-based skills building, and mentoring produces outstanding outcomes for the participants and for society at large.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><br /></span></p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 01/04/2024<br> Modified by: Partha&nbsp;Deb</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      The lack of racial and ethnic diversity in economics has major consequences for minority communities, the economics profession, and society as a whole. While evidence suggests that economics degrees can lead to lucrative careers and upward mobility, the current underrepresentation in this field exacerbates economic inequality and leads to wider social implications. Racially diverse groups have been shown to outperform homogenous groups in terms of problem solving and creativity. Furthermore, the lack of representation impoverishes policy discourse with implications for innovation, political representation, and even for public health. Consequently, we designed and implemented an academic program designed to address the crisis of diversity in economics. The program provides substantive analytic education in economics anchored by a Masters degree along with substantial research experience and mentoring typically available to participants in pre-doc programs designed to prepare students for PhD programs in Economics or related Public Policy disciplines.   Our program identified talented Black and other underrepresented minority (URM) students with undergraduate backgrounds in economics and related quantitative disciplines and offered financial incentives for students to pursue the program. In addition to taking core quantitative courses taught by Hunter College faculty, students took additional courses (topics in Microeconomic theory, Econometrics, Macroeconomics and games and information) designed to prepare students for the rigors of first year PhD courses. These courses were taught by leading scholars in those areas who volunteered their time for this worthy cause. Each student also worked on one or more independent research projects supervised by faculty at Hunter and other nearby universities. As part of the program, students also participated in an intensive writing workshop and a GRE prep class. In addition, all students regularly attended the economics department seminar where researchers from other academic institutions presented their work. During each of these seminar days, the students had the opportunity to chat with the invited researcher exclusively (without Hunter and other faculty present).     The program admitted 8 students in the first cohort that began coursework in Fall 2021. Among them, 3 have gone on to PhD programs, each with generous fellowships or assistantships. In addition, 2 students in that cohort have prestigious research assistantship positions which will likely lead to outstanding PhD program placements in a year or careers at the Feds or similar institutions. One student from that cohort is in the process of applying to PhD programs.   Among the second cohort of 6 students, 2 obtained prestigious research assistantships. We expect 2 other students to obtain pre-doc or other research assistantship opportunities in Spring 2024 that will position them well to apply to PhD programs in Fall 2024.   The successes of our early cohorts of students in this pipeline program provide confidence that our combination approach of formal education, work-based skills building, and mentoring produces outstanding outcomes for the participants and for society at large.         Last Modified: 01/04/2024       Submitted by: ParthaDeb]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
