<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Long-Lasting Insect Repellent Systems Based on Fatty Acids and Their Derivatives]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>207799.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>207799</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project is to enhance public health by the introduction of safer insect-repelling textiles. The Phase I SBIR effort will lead to the development of textiles embedded with a new long-lasting insect repellent system derived from coconut fatty acids. This project will advance a safer insect repellent to reduce vector-borne diseases and to eliminate the health issues resulting from currently available synthetic products. The insect repellent market is currently valued at $5.64 billion, and the proposed work will address issues generated by synthetic repellents. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to test new coconut fatty acid-based compounds that enable the prolonged release of insect repellent fatty acids via textile impregnation. With growing health concerns over the use of DEET and increasing occurrences of permethrin-resistant strains of mosquitos, active compounds based on coconut fatty acids are a viable option for safe and effective replacement. The proposed research is to develop and to test the release system that will gradually supply insect-repelling fatty acid via the degradation of labile chemical bonds which hold the compound.  These developmental products are envisioned to provide prolonged insect repellency compared to the supposed gold standard synthetic repellents such as DEET and permethrin. The SBIR Phase I research will include proof of concept trials, development of analytical methods for accurate analysis of the active ingredient (chromatographic or spectroscopic), release studies, application trials (using standard methods established in the textile industry), and field performance testing on live insects (via surveys designed for agricultural research).  A technical challenge for this project will be ensuring efficient impregnation of fabrics/textiles with the proposed insect repellent system and obtaining a suitable release timeframe after all steps of the fabric treatment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/26/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051917</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dawn</FirstName>
<LastName>Clarke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dawn M Clarke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dawn@insectapel.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000821178</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/26/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/06/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mazeyar</FirstName>
<LastName>Parvinzadeh Gashti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mazeyar Parvinzadeh Gashti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Maz@insectapel.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000908872</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/02/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Lambert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James D Lambert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dlambert@gtichemsolutions.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000862785</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/06/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/02/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>INSECTAPEL, LLC</Name>
<CityName>WELLFORD</CityName>
<ZipCode>293859528</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8645790112</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10152 GREENVILLE HWY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PNV2LHYCZVB5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INSECTAPEL LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[INSECTAPEL, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>WELLFORD</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>293859528</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10152 GREENVILLE HWY]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~207799</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">The overall goal of InsectaPel and this research effort was to create a human friendly, durable, plant-based insect repellent coating for fabrics as an alternative to petroleum-based permethrin and DEET. The ability to significantly enhance public health through the commercialization of highly effective, cost-effective, bio-based, and safe insect-repelling textiles will substantially benefit society. The growing insect repellent market (currently valued as $5.64 billion) has been largely dominated by synthetic repellents that have been criticized for their health hazards. The technical tasks/concepts proposed for this project led to the development of fatty acid-based systems on textiles with prolonged activity. Coconut oil-based free C10-, C12-fatty acids, and their methyl esters have recently shown significant insect repellent efficacy compared with synthetic repellents against various insects (mosquitoes, stable flies, and bed bugs). These fatty acids, their esters, and derivatives can be applied to textiles and provide long-lasting and safe repellent systems. With support from NSF Phase I, we set out to prove that our initial formulation, licensed from the USDA ARS research center, was able to both bind to clothing materials and repel insects.</p> <p class="Default">For this purpose, several coated fabrics were generated using commercial binder systems in combination with fatty acid derivatives. The Pad-squeeze-curing method was used with different levels of repellant loadings. The team explored the mechanism of efficacy of formulas on textiles using Infrared spectra. Also, High-performance liquid chromatography was utilized to quantify the amount of active ingredients using solvent extraction method. ARS scientists performed lab trials, including bioassays, to evaluate the efficacy and longevity of the treated fabrics. Coated fabrics produced at InsectaPel were tested on 48-hour starved biting flies using modified biting insect feeding assay modules from ARS. Both the activities and longevity were tested for about ten replicates (with each replicate including 5-10 samples). Further toxicity tests against the biting flies and blood-engorged behavior were also observed, in addition to assessing the fly&rsquo;s repellency.</p> <p class="Default">Our Phase I results were able to demonstrate positive results for both objectives. We demonstrated that several developed biobased coatings could achieve 100% repellency against stable flies. &nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">Overall, the introduction of a bio-based repellent agent will be a significant step in the quest to commercialize a safe insect repellent to reduce vector-borne diseases and to minimize the health issues associated with currently available synthetic repellent products. These coconut oil-based free fatty acids and their derivatives represent current state-of-the-art insect repellent textile technology and will create a human friendly, plant-based insect repellent coating for fabrics as an alternative to petroleum-based permethrin and DEET.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/18/2023<br> Modified by: Mazeyar&nbsp; &nbsp;Parvinzadeh Gashti</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The overall goal of InsectaPel and this research effort was to create a human friendly, durable, plant-based insect repellent coating for fabrics as an alternative to petroleum-based permethrin and DEET. The ability to significantly enhance public health through the commercialization of highly effective, cost-effective, bio-based, and safe insect-repelling textiles will substantially benefit society. The growing insect repellent market (currently valued as $5.64 billion) has been largely dominated by synthetic repellents that have been criticized for their health hazards. The technical tasks/concepts proposed for this project led to the development of fatty acid-based systems on textiles with prolonged activity. Coconut oil-based free C10-, C12-fatty acids, and their methyl esters have recently shown significant insect repellent efficacy compared with synthetic repellents against various insects (mosquitoes, stable flies, and bed bugs). These fatty acids, their esters, and derivatives can be applied to textiles and provide long-lasting and safe repellent systems. With support from NSF Phase I, we set out to prove that our initial formulation, licensed from the USDA ARS research center, was able to both bind to clothing materials and repel insects.   For this purpose, several coated fabrics were generated using commercial binder systems in combination with fatty acid derivatives. The Pad-squeeze-curing method was used with different levels of repellant loadings. The team explored the mechanism of efficacy of formulas on textiles using Infrared spectra. Also, High-performance liquid chromatography was utilized to quantify the amount of active ingredients using solvent extraction method. ARS scientists performed lab trials, including bioassays, to evaluate the efficacy and longevity of the treated fabrics. Coated fabrics produced at InsectaPel were tested on 48-hour starved biting flies using modified biting insect feeding assay modules from ARS. Both the activities and longevity were tested for about ten replicates (with each replicate including 5-10 samples). Further toxicity tests against the biting flies and blood-engorged behavior were also observed, in addition to assessing the flys repellency.   Our Phase I results were able to demonstrate positive results for both objectives. We demonstrated that several developed biobased coatings could achieve 100% repellency against stable flies.    Overall, the introduction of a bio-based repellent agent will be a significant step in the quest to commercialize a safe insect repellent to reduce vector-borne diseases and to minimize the health issues associated with currently available synthetic repellent products. These coconut oil-based free fatty acids and their derivatives represent current state-of-the-art insect repellent textile technology and will create a human friendly, plant-based insect repellent coating for fabrics as an alternative to petroleum-based permethrin and DEET.        Last Modified: 12/18/2023       Submitted by: Mazeyar Parvinzadeh Gashti]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
