<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAR-PF: Mammals as sentinels of biotic recovery and the topographic diversity gradient in the aftermath of the Cretaceous–Paleogene mass extinction]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>174000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>174000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aisha Morris</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>armorris@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927081</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is funded in whole or in part under the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (Public Law 117-2). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Lucas N. Weaver has been awarded an NSF EAR Postdoctoral Fellowship to investigate the ecological recovery of mammals during the Cretaceous–Paleogene (K–Pg) mass extinction event.  Insight from other environmental catastrophes in Earth’s past can provide information about the current environmental crisis. Additionally, impacts of environmental disturbances are not equal across time and space; therefore, it is important to see how resilient or susceptible species are to extinction in different temporal and geographic settings. The K-Pg mass extinction event, which occurred 66 million years ago and is famous for leading to the extinction of the dinosaurs, is similar to the kind of extinction seen today. Towards this end, this project aims to study how mammal communities (including the ancient ancestors of the group to which humans belong) recovered from the K–Pg mass extinction over the first 1 million years of the ‘Age of Mammals,’ in the Denver Basin of Colorado. Mammals are often used as ‘canaries in the coal mine’ for ecological health because environmental variables such as temperature and moisture are related to mammals’ ecological health. The work is based on the hypothesis that the Rocky Mountains acted as a buffer during the K–Pg mass extinction and allowed more mammalian species to survive and diversify in a post-dinosaur world. Given that the Earth is likely in the midst of a sixth mass extinction event in its history, this study provides crucial insight into which ecosystems are at greatest risk, and which ecosystems are better able to ‘weather the storm.’ Broader impacts of this work include working with the Denver Museum of Nature and Science to disseminate results to a broad audience through their exhibits; mentoring of undergraduates at University of Michigan and City University of New York, and development of curriculum for high school students.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to investigate the spatial and temporal heterogeneity of mammal recovery after the Cretaceous–Paleogene (K–Pg) mass extinction (66 million years ago) in the Denver Basin of Colorado. Denver Basin fossil localities are highly resolved chronostratigraphically, allowing precise correlation of the pattern and timing of biotic recovery in different paleogeographic regions of the basin during the first ~1 million years of the Paleogene. Since mountainous regions today are biodiversity hotspots, this project is based on the hypothesis that mammal communities close to the emerging Rocky Mountains (1) were more resistant to the K–Pg mass extinction, and (2) recovered more quickly in its aftermath. To explore these hypotheses, the work will quantify and compare the taxonomic (richness, relative abundance), dietary (inferred via tooth shape), and body mass (inferred via tooth size) diversity between two stratigraphic sequences of fossil mammal assemblages: (1) close to and (2) far from the Rocky Mountain front range. This project will involve field and laboratory work and will use new paleoecological methods to infer community-level mammal diversity patterns through time. This study will be the first to (1) look at spatial heterogeneity in post-K–Pg mammalian recovery in high resolution and (2) explore whether mountain habitats were a driver of early mammalian diversity. These results will help identify geospatial features that promote biological community resilience/reassembly after environmental disasters, and will shed light on the tempo and mode of the post-K–Pg radiation of mammals, which ultimately led to the distribution of terrestrial biodiversity we see today. This work will also integrate data from the mammal fossil record with the broader vertebrate and plant fossil record, and with paleoclimate proxies. This novel multidisciplinary approach will allow collaboration with other scientists to track whole-ecosystem recovery in the aftermath of the K–Pg mass extinction.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052992</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lucas</FirstName>
<LastName>Weaver</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lucas N Weaver</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000834566</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Weaver, Lucas N]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981224788</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Museum of Paleontology]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1V21</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA ARP Act DEFC V</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010V2122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA ARP Act DEFC V]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~174000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Biodiversity is unevenly distributed on Earth. Some areas promote biodiversity and are resilient in the face of environmental change, whereas others do not and are susceptible to ecosystem collapse. In this project, I investigated the role that mountainous regions played in promoting and maintaining mammalian biodiversity leading up to and across the Cretaceous-Paleogene (K-Pg) mass extinction event, which is famous for marking the demise of non-avian dinosaurs and the dawn of the Age of Mammals. Mountainous regions today are biodiversity hotspots, and it holds that the same should be true in the geologic past. Using two natural laboratories (the Denver Basin of Colorado, and the Bighorn Basin of Wyoming) I explored the role that mountain proximity played in promoting (1) mammalian speciation and ecological specialization in the Late Cretaceous, and (2) mammalian response to and recovery from the K-Pg mass extinction. Nonetheless, since high-elevation environments do not persist in the rock record due to their propensity for erosion, I had to first establish whether lowland environments close to mountain areas (i.e., mountain-proximal) capture more mountain-derived biodiversity compared to those far from mountain areas (i.e., mountain-distal).</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; I, in collaboration with researchers from the University of Michigan, Denver Museum of Nature &amp; Science, and Brooklyn College, found the following patterns: (1) Mountain-proximal to mountain-distal paleoenvironments can be reliably tracked using clues from sedimentary rocks. Mountain-proximal settings are dominated by coarse-grained sediments, whereas mountain-distal settings are dominated by fine-grained sediments. (2) Vertebrate microfossil bonebeds (VMBs) that form in mountain-proximal settings are distinct from those in mountain-distal settings, and those differences reflect a topographic diversity gradient. Mountain-proximal VMBs are dominated by terrestrial or semi-aquatic taxa (i.e., mammals and crocodiles, respectively), whereas mountain-distal VMBs are dominated by aquatic taxa (i.e., fish and aquatic amphibians). (3) Mountain-proximal VMBs host rare mammalian taxa that are not found in comparable mountain-distal VMBs, suggesting that these taxa were unique to more mountainous regions. For example, we found numerous small mammalian taxa from mountain-proximal sites in the early Paleocene of the Denver Basin that had never-before been found in mountain-distal settings. (4) On a macro-scale, we found that tectonic activity likely stimulated the blooming of modern biodiversity that occurred in the Late Cretaceous; the so-called Cretaceous Terrestrial Revolution. In reviewing biodiversity trends through the Late Cretaceous of North America in comparison with tectonic, climate, and other landscape-proxy records, we found that tectonism and mountain-building, not the diversification of flowering plants (as had been previously assumed), was the major catalyst for biodiversity increases on land leading up to the K&ndash;Pg boundary.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Our findings have several major implications, namely that mountainous regions, throughout Earth&rsquo;s history, have likely been: (1) hubs for biotic innovation, (2) cradles of biodiversity, and (3) shelters from climatic and other environmental perturbations. These findings shed light on our current biodiversity crisis; mountainous areas hold the most promise for shielding ecosystems from the worst predicted outcomes of environmental degradation and should be a top conservation priority.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This project has also provided opportunities for undergraduate students from diverse backgrounds to gain experiences in both field and laboratory research. As documented in the supporting images, I was able to mentor 15 different undergraduate students through the course of this project, providing for them their first primary scientific research experiences. Collectively, these students spent 10 weeks in the field, learning the fundamentals of field geology and paleontology. Eight students were able to conduct laboratory research with me at the University of Michigan, and four of those went on to present their independent research projects at scientific conferences (namely, the 2022 and 2023 Society of Vertebrate Paleontology meetings). Three of those four are now writing their first scientific papers from those studies, and I anticipate they will have their papers submitted for peer review in the coming year. Not only were these experiences transformative for the undergraduates, but their work was transformative for the project, shedding light on many of the key findings listed above.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In sum, this project represents an important step forward in our understanding of how geological and biological processes are linked in the Earth history, and how those links can help us forecast our future. From this project will come numerous continuations, including my own research program as an Assistant Professor in the Department of Earth Sciences at Kent State University. Without the generous support of the NSF, none of this would have been possible.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/21/2023<br> Modified by: Lucas&nbsp;N&nbsp;Weaver</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052992/2052992_10756408_1700581335102_Grace_DMNS--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052992/2052992_10756408_1700581335102_Grace_DMNS--rgov-800width.png" title="Providing laboratory research opportunities"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052992/2052992_10756408_1700581335102_Grace_DMNS--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Providing laboratory research opportunities"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">U. Michigan undergrad, Grace Pizzini, collecting taphonomic data from early Paleocene vertebrate fossils from the Denver Basin</div> <div class="imageCredit">Luke Weaver</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lucas&nbsp;N&nbsp;Weaver <div class="imageTitle">Providing laboratory research opportunities</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052992/2052992_10756408_1700581058753_guzzler--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052992/2052992_10756408_1700581058753_guzzler--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="Undergraduate/graduate training in fossil prospecting"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052992/2052992_10756408_1700581058753_guzzler--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="Undergraduate/graduate training in fossil prospecting"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">U. Michigan undergrads (Abby Waller, Megan Riley) and grad (Tara Lonsdorf) pointing to a sandstone block hosting numerous vertebrate microfossils</div> <div class="imageCredit">Luke Weaver</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lucas&nbsp;N&nbsp;Weaver <div class="imageTitle">Undergraduate/graduate training in fossil prospecting</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052992/2052992_10756408_1700581232704_screenwshing--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052992/2052992_10756408_1700581232704_screenwshing--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="Undergrad training in screenwashing"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052992/2052992_10756408_1700581232704_screenwshing--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="Undergrad training in screenwashing"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">U. Michigan undergrads (Abby Waller, Megan Riley, Blake Briggs, Andrew Colon) screenwashing for mammalian fossils</div> <div class="imageCredit">Luke Weaver</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lucas&nbsp;N&nbsp;Weaver <div class="imageTitle">Undergrad training in screenwashing</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052992/2052992_10756408_1700581128386_IMG_2306_copy--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052992/2052992_10756408_1700581128386_IMG_2306_copy--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="Undergrad training in sedimentology/stratigraphy"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052992/2052992_10756408_1700581128386_IMG_2306_copy--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="Undergrad training in sedimentology/stratigraphy"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">U. Michigan undergrads (Grace Pizzini, Jake Downey) documenting Upper Cretaceous stratigraphy and taking sediment samples</div> <div class="imageCredit">Luke Weaver</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lucas&nbsp;N&nbsp;Weaver <div class="imageTitle">Undergrad training in sedimentology/stratigraphy</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052992/2052992_10756408_1700581435959_abbyjake--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052992/2052992_10756408_1700581435959_abbyjake--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="Documenting mountain-proximal to -distal geology"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052992/2052992_10756408_1700581435959_abbyjake--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="Documenting mountain-proximal to -distal geology"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">U. Michigan undergrad, Abby Waller, logging the sedimentology and stratigraphy of Upper Cretaceous strata</div> <div class="imageCredit">Luke Weaver</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lucas&nbsp;N&nbsp;Weaver <div class="imageTitle">Documenting mountain-proximal to -distal geology</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Biodiversity is unevenly distributed on Earth. Some areas promote biodiversity and are resilient in the face of environmental change, whereas others do not and are susceptible to ecosystem collapse. In this project, I investigated the role that mountainous regions played in promoting and maintaining mammalian biodiversity leading up to and across the Cretaceous-Paleogene (K-Pg) mass extinction event, which is famous for marking the demise of non-avian dinosaurs and the dawn of the Age of Mammals. Mountainous regions today are biodiversity hotspots, and it holds that the same should be true in the geologic past. Using two natural laboratories (the Denver Basin of Colorado, and the Bighorn Basin of Wyoming) I explored the role that mountain proximity played in promoting (1) mammalian speciation and ecological specialization in the Late Cretaceous, and (2) mammalian response to and recovery from the K-Pg mass extinction. Nonetheless, since high-elevation environments do not persist in the rock record due to their propensity for erosion, I had to first establish whether lowland environments close to mountain areas (i.e., mountain-proximal) capture more mountain-derived biodiversity compared to those far from mountain areas (i.e., mountain-distal).    I, in collaboration with researchers from the University of Michigan, Denver Museum of Nature & Science, and Brooklyn College, found the following patterns: (1) Mountain-proximal to mountain-distal paleoenvironments can be reliably tracked using clues from sedimentary rocks. Mountain-proximal settings are dominated by coarse-grained sediments, whereas mountain-distal settings are dominated by fine-grained sediments. (2) Vertebrate microfossil bonebeds (VMBs) that form in mountain-proximal settings are distinct from those in mountain-distal settings, and those differences reflect a topographic diversity gradient. Mountain-proximal VMBs are dominated by terrestrial or semi-aquatic taxa (i.e., mammals and crocodiles, respectively), whereas mountain-distal VMBs are dominated by aquatic taxa (i.e., fish and aquatic amphibians). (3) Mountain-proximal VMBs host rare mammalian taxa that are not found in comparable mountain-distal VMBs, suggesting that these taxa were unique to more mountainous regions. For example, we found numerous small mammalian taxa from mountain-proximal sites in the early Paleocene of the Denver Basin that had never-before been found in mountain-distal settings. (4) On a macro-scale, we found that tectonic activity likely stimulated the blooming of modern biodiversity that occurred in the Late Cretaceous; the so-called Cretaceous Terrestrial Revolution. In reviewing biodiversity trends through the Late Cretaceous of North America in comparison with tectonic, climate, and other landscape-proxy records, we found that tectonism and mountain-building, not the diversification of flowering plants (as had been previously assumed), was the major catalyst for biodiversity increases on land leading up to the KPg boundary.    Our findings have several major implications, namely that mountainous regions, throughout Earths history, have likely been: (1) hubs for biotic innovation, (2) cradles of biodiversity, and (3) shelters from climatic and other environmental perturbations. These findings shed light on our current biodiversity crisis; mountainous areas hold the most promise for shielding ecosystems from the worst predicted outcomes of environmental degradation and should be a top conservation priority.    This project has also provided opportunities for undergraduate students from diverse backgrounds to gain experiences in both field and laboratory research. As documented in the supporting images, I was able to mentor 15 different undergraduate students through the course of this project, providing for them their first primary scientific research experiences. Collectively, these students spent 10 weeks in the field, learning the fundamentals of field geology and paleontology. Eight students were able to conduct laboratory research with me at the University of Michigan, and four of those went on to present their independent research projects at scientific conferences (namely, the 2022 and 2023 Society of Vertebrate Paleontology meetings). Three of those four are now writing their first scientific papers from those studies, and I anticipate they will have their papers submitted for peer review in the coming year. Not only were these experiences transformative for the undergraduates, but their work was transformative for the project, shedding light on many of the key findings listed above.    In sum, this project represents an important step forward in our understanding of how geological and biological processes are linked in the Earth history, and how those links can help us forecast our future. From this project will come numerous continuations, including my own research program as an Assistant Professor in the Department of Earth Sciences at Kent State University. Without the generous support of the NSF, none of this would have been possible.        Last Modified: 11/21/2023       Submitted by: LucasNWeaver]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
