<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Seismic and Hydrostratigraphic Characterization of the Onshore-Offshore Freshwater Systems of Martha’s Vineyard and Nantucket, Massachusetts, USA]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49417.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49417</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Coastal hydrological systems provide significant freshwater resources to coastal communities around the world. These resources are exploited by groundwater wells that produce from aquifers at depths of less than 100 m. Globally, these resources are declining due to overuse, increasing population, and climate change. To improve water supplies and security, new approaches to understanding underused and poorly quantified freshwater resources are needed. One such resource is freshwater that extends from onshore to offshore, potentially extending up to 100km offshore in some regions, such as the northeastern margin of the United States. To better understand the dynamics of these onshore-offshore hydrologic systems, we need dedicated, coordinated onshore and offshore hydrogeological studies. This research project on Martha’s Vineyard and Nantucket, MA, USA will increase our understanding of the coastal freshwater resources by characterizing the sedimentary layering in the coastal environment through geophysical surveys. This work is a critical piece to the integrative, multi-pronged (geophysics, drilling and sampling, modeling) research that is required to understand the dynamics of the onshore-offshore systems and to define their potential as a resource. This study has the potential to establish the protocols for studying global onshore-offshore freshwater resources, to improve understanding of under-developed freshwater resources, and to inform future studies on the maintenance and sustainability of this resource.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Over the last 15 years, there has been growing research on onshore-offshore freshwater systems including geophysical surveys and numerical models that have been motivated by drilling data that were not collected to address freshwater resources. To date, however, no dedicated and integrated onshore-offshore study has been completed to study the dynamics, volumes, and producibility of these offshore freshwater resources. Our proposed study of the hydrostratigraphy on Martha’s Vineyard and Nantucket Island, MA, USA through collection, processing, and interpretation of seismic data is a key portion to the first complete onshore-offshore characterization. The data obtained from this award will be used to support an International Continental Scientific Drilling Program (ICDP) proposal to drill wells to quantify the hydrologic properties and groundwater age for the onshore portion of this coastal aquifer system. This complements an International Ocean Discovery Program (IODP) proposal to drill wells to quantify hydrologic properties and groundwater age for the offshore component of this onshore-offshore aquifer. Combined, this research would be the first dedicated, shoreline-crossing geological, geophysical, and hydrogeological study of onshore-offshore freshwater addressing many questions related to the dynamics, sustainability, and utility of these freshwater systems that exist globally.  This award was co-funded by the Earth Sciences Hydrologic Sciences Program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052794</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brandon</FirstName>
<LastName>Dugan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brandon Dugan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dugan@mines.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000393327</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Shragge</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey C Shragge</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jshragge@mines.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000834807</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado School of Mines</Name>
<CityName>GOLDEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>804011887</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3032733000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1500 ILLINOIS ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JW2NGMP4NMA3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE COLORADO SCHOOL OF MINES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>JW2NGMP4NMA3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado School of Mines]]></Name>
<CityName>Nantucket</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>025543715</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[180 Polpis Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1579</Code>
<Text>Hydrologic Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~49417</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span>Seismic and Hydrostratigraphic Characterization of the Onshore-Offshore Freshwater Systems of Martha&rsquo;s Vineyard and Nantucket, Massachusetts, USA: Project Outcomes Report</span></strong></p> <p><strong><span><strong>NSF Award&nbsp;2052794</strong><br /></span></strong></p> <p>PI: Brandon Dugan, Colorado School of Mines</p> <p>As part of a multi-stage project to understand onshore-offshore freshened groundwater systems, we completed two multi-channel seismic surveys. The first survey was located along Fire Road 11 in Manuel F. Correllus State Forest on Martha&rsquo;s Vineyard, MA, USA. The second survey was located along Milestone Rd one Nantucket, MA, USA. Each survey was conducted with a 750-lb accelerated weight drop as the seismic source and one component wireless nodes to record the data. Two hundred nodes (10 m node spacing) were deployed for each seismic line. Shots (10 m shot spacing, 3 shot stacking) were completed along the length of each seismic line. Initial inspection of data collected on Martha&rsquo;s Vineyard show good quality data from which an initial velocity model was constructed. Initial inspection of data collected on Nantucket are of slightly lower quality. The lower signal-to-noise ratio in the Nantucket data is likely caused by increased environmental noise due to traffic on Milestone Rd. All data are archived and publicly available (https://zenodo.org/records/10407771). Final processing of the data will be correlated with local wells ENW-50 on Martha&rsquo;s Vineyard and USGS 6001 on Nantucket and will be correlated with the offshore seismic data collected using National Science Foundation funding (NSF Award 0824368). Upon completion of the interpretation and correlation, the data will be used to define two drilling targets that will be the focus of a proposal to the International Continental Scientific Drilling Program to understand the onshore component of the onshore-offshore freshened groundwater system along the US Atlantic continental margin. The completion of this work involved the training of three undergraduate students and engagement of the local communities to understand how our science can contribute to the ongoing discussions on water resources in coastal environments.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span><br /></span></strong></p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/19/2023<br> Modified by: Brandon&nbsp;Dugan</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Seismic and Hydrostratigraphic Characterization of the Onshore-Offshore Freshwater Systems of Marthas Vineyard and Nantucket, Massachusetts, USA: Project Outcomes Report   NSF Award2052794    PI: Brandon Dugan, Colorado School of Mines   As part of a multi-stage project to understand onshore-offshore freshened groundwater systems, we completed two multi-channel seismic surveys. The first survey was located along Fire Road 11 in Manuel F. Correllus State Forest on Marthas Vineyard, MA, USA. The second survey was located along Milestone Rd one Nantucket, MA, USA. Each survey was conducted with a 750-lb accelerated weight drop as the seismic source and one component wireless nodes to record the data. Two hundred nodes (10 m node spacing) were deployed for each seismic line. Shots (10 m shot spacing, 3 shot stacking) were completed along the length of each seismic line. Initial inspection of data collected on Marthas Vineyard show good quality data from which an initial velocity model was constructed. Initial inspection of data collected on Nantucket are of slightly lower quality. The lower signal-to-noise ratio in the Nantucket data is likely caused by increased environmental noise due to traffic on Milestone Rd. All data are archived and publicly available (https://zenodo.org/records/10407771). Final processing of the data will be correlated with local wells ENW-50 on Marthas Vineyard and USGS 6001 on Nantucket and will be correlated with the offshore seismic data collected using National Science Foundation funding (NSF Award 0824368). Upon completion of the interpretation and correlation, the data will be used to define two drilling targets that will be the focus of a proposal to the International Continental Scientific Drilling Program to understand the onshore component of the onshore-offshore freshened groundwater system along the US Atlantic continental margin. The completion of this work involved the training of three undergraduate students and engagement of the local communities to understand how our science can contribute to the ongoing discussions on water resources in coastal environments.         Last Modified: 12/19/2023       Submitted by: BrandonDugan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
