<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAR-PF: The optimization of SPC-POU filter and its application of well water treatment within Indigenous lands.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>174000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>174000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aisha Morris</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>armorris@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927081</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[An NSF EAR Postdoctoral fellowship was awarded to Dr. Ranalda Tsosie to carry out a research, teaching and professional development experience at Montana State University under the mentorship of Dr. Ellen Lauchnor and Dr. Mari Eggers. The PI will engage with three communities to address arsenic contamination issues. Two of these communities are located on Indigenous lands, the Navajo and Crow reservations, and the third community is in a rural community in the state of Montana. The proposed research will focus on the ongoing private well arsenic contamination issues in households in Montana and the contamination issues of unregulated water sources located on the Navajo reservation. Specifically, the proposed use-inspired research will determine the species of arsenic and test cost effective and commercially available arsenic removal filters. A second objective is to optimize the design of a current prototype of silica polyamine composite based point of use filter (SPC-POU) developed by Dr. Tsosie during her dissertation research at the University of Montana. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will advance the knowledge of arsenic remediation and develop an innovative method of &lt;br/&gt;addressing arsenic contamination. Arsenic has been studied extensively and much effort has gone into developing more cost-effective methods of remediation. Despite all these efforts, many households throughout the U.S. continue to face issues with arsenic exceedance in their drinking water. This research aims to tackle these issues by working with these households in Montana that do not have access to a publicly monitored water supply. In addition, on the Navajo reservation there are some households that do not have running water in their homes and must rely on unregulated water sources for their household water needs. It is communities/households like these, that this research will be the most impactful.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by the Division of Earth Sciences and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2053016</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ranalda</FirstName>
<LastName>Tsosie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ranalda L Tsosie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000809588</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tsosie, Ranalda L]]></Name>
<CityName>Missoula</CityName>
<ZipCode>59802</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Montana State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bozeman</CityName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>597173820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1579</Code>
<Text>Hydrologic Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~174000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was designed to provide a temporary solution for communities that are impacted by mining and contamination of water sources. The project began as a vision and involved multiple partners from tribal communities to students. Tribal communities like those involved in this project, Navajo and Crow Nations, were involved by bringing forth concerns for their water sources. Past mining efforts and geologic conditions created challenging water insecurities and contamination issues that these communities are continuing to deal with today.</p> <p>The Point Of Use (POU) filter is a tangible solution that can help relieve some of the pressures of these water insecurities. The filter is designed with the user in mind. It is a handheld unit that is meant to travel with the user to unregulated water sources located at times miles apart. In the spring, the availability of water is more widespread but as late fall approaches, the water becomes sparse. Therefore, a handheld unit is ideal. Due to mining and geology of the arid southwest, some water sources are impacted by increased levels of arsenic, uranium, vanadium and other elements of concern. Keeping the well-being of not only human health in mind, but also livestock. The POU filter will filter the water collected at these unregulated water sources (windmill wells) and ensure safe drinking water for livestock, for agricultural and household purposes. However, it is currently advised that these water sources not be used for human consumption or cooking.</p> <p>The project allowed for five mechanical engineering students at Montana State University to work with Dr. Tsosie to pursue a year-long project in design, development and production of the handheld unit. The first semester was focused on planning and design. Students involved in the project explored multiple designs, potential challenges that may arise in the field, and materials to use. In the second semester, students produce the second prototype. An additional unit design feature is the customizable cartridge system. The unit has removable cartridges that allows for different resin types to be changed and customized to site. For example, the same system could be use on the Navajo Nation, where the waters are high in As, U and V, and in Montana where the biggest challenge is nitrates and biological contaminates. Therefore, the ease of exchange the materials used to bind and remove elements of concern or biological contaminates, is what make this system unique.</p> <p>In addition to the mechanical engineering students, the project also recruited two civil engineering students to gain undergraduate research experience. These students assisted Dr. Tsosie (project PI) in determining which commercially available materials to implement in the handheld unit and tested these solid phase extraction (SPE) resins for capacities, breakthrough and pH dependency. They also assisted in understanding and overcoming the flow challenges of the unit. All these conditions were and continue to be tested at bench scale. There are plans to begin in-field testing within the next year.</p> <p>While this project was focused on providing a tangible solution for water haulers and livestock watering, it has the potential to be used for expanding drinking water access for impacted communities in other rural areas. If commercialized, there could be large impacts to access to water for communities that are coping with water insecurities. If the unit is designed in such a way that it could be provided at low cost then the potential public impact could be greater. While there are many water filtration units on the market or in development, the POU filter developed in this project is the first of its kind because it can travel with the user, it can be modified for site specific removal of identified contaminates and it can be used with a wide range of SPE materials on the market including those that are newly designed. The POU filter and the cartridge system has the potential for future commercialization. Currently, a patent application is being considered and plans to file are in discussion with the current institution.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/29/2023<br> Modified by: Ranalda&nbsp;L&nbsp;Tsosie</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This project was designed to provide a temporary solution for communities that are impacted by mining and contamination of water sources. The project began as a vision and involved multiple partners from tribal communities to students. Tribal communities like those involved in this project, Navajo and Crow Nations, were involved by bringing forth concerns for their water sources. Past mining efforts and geologic conditions created challenging water insecurities and contamination issues that these communities are continuing to deal with today.   The Point Of Use (POU) filter is a tangible solution that can help relieve some of the pressures of these water insecurities. The filter is designed with the user in mind. It is a handheld unit that is meant to travel with the user to unregulated water sources located at times miles apart. In the spring, the availability of water is more widespread but as late fall approaches, the water becomes sparse. Therefore, a handheld unit is ideal. Due to mining and geology of the arid southwest, some water sources are impacted by increased levels of arsenic, uranium, vanadium and other elements of concern. Keeping the well-being of not only human health in mind, but also livestock. The POU filter will filter the water collected at these unregulated water sources (windmill wells) and ensure safe drinking water for livestock, for agricultural and household purposes. However, it is currently advised that these water sources not be used for human consumption or cooking.   The project allowed for five mechanical engineering students at Montana State University to work with Dr. Tsosie to pursue a year-long project in design, development and production of the handheld unit. The first semester was focused on planning and design. Students involved in the project explored multiple designs, potential challenges that may arise in the field, and materials to use. In the second semester, students produce the second prototype. An additional unit design feature is the customizable cartridge system. The unit has removable cartridges that allows for different resin types to be changed and customized to site. For example, the same system could be use on the Navajo Nation, where the waters are high in As, U and V, and in Montana where the biggest challenge is nitrates and biological contaminates. Therefore, the ease of exchange the materials used to bind and remove elements of concern or biological contaminates, is what make this system unique.   In addition to the mechanical engineering students, the project also recruited two civil engineering students to gain undergraduate research experience. These students assisted Dr. Tsosie (project PI) in determining which commercially available materials to implement in the handheld unit and tested these solid phase extraction (SPE) resins for capacities, breakthrough and pH dependency. They also assisted in understanding and overcoming the flow challenges of the unit. All these conditions were and continue to be tested at bench scale. There are plans to begin in-field testing within the next year.   While this project was focused on providing a tangible solution for water haulers and livestock watering, it has the potential to be used for expanding drinking water access for impacted communities in other rural areas. If commercialized, there could be large impacts to access to water for communities that are coping with water insecurities. If the unit is designed in such a way that it could be provided at low cost then the potential public impact could be greater. While there are many water filtration units on the market or in development, the POU filter developed in this project is the first of its kind because it can travel with the user, it can be modified for site specific removal of identified contaminates and it can be used with a wide range of SPE materials on the market including those that are newly designed. The POU filter and the cartridge system has the potential for future commercialization. Currently, a patent application is being considered and plans to file are in discussion with the current institution.        Last Modified: 11/29/2023       Submitted by: RanaldaLTsosie]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
