<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Cellular Biomanufacturing Workshop]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/25/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>57792.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>57792</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Peretti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>speretti@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924201</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This workshop was organized to promote interactions between researchers working in the nascent field of biomanufacturing, with a primary focus on therapeutic cell manufacturing. The workshop is also intended to identify significant knowledge gaps in the manufacturing of differentiated cells. This workshop will bring together the EAGER Biomanufacturing awardees from FY15 and FY16, to share results and techniques, and identify challenges and new opportunities. The two funding years cover cell differentiation and large-scale biomanufacturing. It is critical that such upstream and downstream processing research is integrated, and that all researchers in the therapeutic cell area are aware of the constraints faced in the integrated process, as well as the federal regulations surrounding biologics. The small workshop atmosphere enables high-level discussion and participation, and the participation of representatives from CBER, NIIMBL and ARMI is critical to delivering that information to the attendees.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/05/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2055144</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bhavana</FirstName>
<LastName>Singh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bhavana Singh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bsingh@childrensnational.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000928105</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/05/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nitin</FirstName>
<LastName>Agrawal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nitin Agrawal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nagrawal2@cnmc.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000667254</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/05/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Children's Research Institute</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200102916</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3015658483</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>111 MICHIGAN AVE NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[FL 5]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M3KHEEYRM1S6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CHILDREN'S RESEARCH INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Children's Research Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200102970</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[111 Michigan Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1491</Code>
<Text>Cellular &amp; Biochem Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1757</Code>
<Text>Quantitative sys bio and biotech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001718DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~57792</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A series of NSF supported Cellular Biomanufacturing workshops were organized in 2017 and 2023 for Early Concept Grants for Exploratory Research (EAGER) awardees in cellular biomanufacturing to address emerging challenges. These workshops aimed to facilitate collaboration, knowledge sharing, and discussions on critical issues. By connecting academia, industry, and government, the workshops aimed to advance cellular therapies and make immunotherapy more accessible. The workshops aimed to raise NSF leadership awareness, evaluate EAGER awardees' contributions, and plan future meetings for collaborations, career opportunities, and industry engagement in cellular biomanufacturing.</p> <p>The "Cellular Biomanufacturing 2023" workshop, an extension of the 2017 event, played a pivotal role in exploring the current state of therapeutic cell manufacturing. The workshop gathered representatives from various agencies, including NIH, NCI, and FDA, emphasizing collaboration, and acknowledging the evolving landscape of immunotherapies. The event aimed to examine the technological advancements, scientific gaps, and opportunities in therapeutic cell manufacturing since the inception of this NSF initiative.</p> <p>The Cellular Biomanufacturing 2023 workshop featured presentations covering a wide array of topics, ranging from the support for discovery science by NSF to the regulatory considerations presented by representatives from the FDA. These presentations offered a comprehensive overview of the challenges, advancements, and regulatory frameworks shaping the field of cellular biomanufacturing. The presentations also included talks by NSF EAGER awardees, covering topics such as biomanufacturing of thymus organoids, drugs and biomarkers for COVID, and strategies for vascularization of engineered cardiac tissue scaffolds. &nbsp;Discussion sessions were organized to explore critical aspects of the field, with a focus on trajectory, scientific challenges, process optimization, automation, scaling, and emerging technologies like artificial intelligence.</p> <p>The workshop served as a multifaceted platform for training and professional development in cellular biomanufacturing. Attendees gained technical knowledge through expert presentations and talks, fostering awareness of cutting-edge advancements in the field. Networking opportunities facilitated relationship-building among participants, experts, and government officials, expanding professional connections and fostering collaborations.</p> <p>One of the key outcomes of the workshop was its impact on workforce development. The recommendations made during the workshop significantly are likely to influence the development of human resources in cellular bioengineering. Specialized training programs at two-year colleges, retraining initiatives, and apprenticeship programs were proposed to address workforce gaps in the cell biomanufacturing industry. These strategies aimed to align workforce skills with the needs of the industry, ensuring a skilled and diverse workforce. Moreover, the workshop emphasized the importance of workforce diversity and inclusivity. Initiatives to increase the participation of women in biomanufacturing, including programs supporting work-life balance, maternity leave, and retraining grants, were recommended. These efforts aimed to transform the culture within the research and manufacturing sectors, promoting a multidisciplinary approach in science, engineering, and technology.</p> <p>The workshop also evaluated different biomanufacturing approaches, particularly modular versus all-in-one strategies in the context of autologous and allogeneic cell-based therapies. The discussions highlighted the advantages of modular processes, emphasizing flexibility and adaptability in optimizing manufacturing processes.</p> <p>Another focus of the workshop was the exploration of the role of artificial intelligence (AI), predictive biology, and machine learning in biomanufacturing. Acknowledging the transformative potential of AI models, the workshop advocated for data availability and collaboration across diverse scholarly domains, as well as the incorporation of AI into the curriculum and workforce development programs.</p> <p>The workshop's recommendations, encompassing findings, results, and techniques, are anticipated to exert a significant influence that extends beyond the realm of cellular biomanufacturing, resonating across diverse fields. Discussions on AI and modular approaches are likely to find relevance in biomedical engineering, data science, and artificial intelligence. Similarly, insights into regulatory considerations are expected to extend their influence into the domain of regulatory affairs. The strategies outlined for workforce development have the potential to shape educational practices across various disciplines. The workshop's recommendations, with their far-reaching implications, are anticipated to influence and guide developments in physical, institutional, and information resources. Additionally, the proposed technology transfer initiatives are expected to foster collaboration, engage industries, support workforce development, integrate technology, provide education, address regulations, and promote small businesses, ultimately contributing to advancements in cellular biomanufacturing technologies across diverse sectors.</p> <p>The workshop aimed to create a positive societal impact by addressing broader challenges and opportunities beyond the academic and research community. This impact included improved healthcare access, advancements in pediatric cancer treatments, positive contributions to workforce diversity and economic stimulation, ethical considerations in the development and deployment of biomanufactured products, and public awareness and engagement.</p> <p>In conclusion, the "Cellular Biomanufacturing 2023" workshop served as a dynamic platform for advancing knowledge, fostering collaboration, and shaping the trajectory of cellular biomanufacturing. The recommendations made during the workshop were likely to contribute significantly to the ongoing development of the field, impacting various aspects such as workforce development, technology transfer, and societal implications. The workshop's multidisciplinary approach and emphasis on cutting-edge technologies positioned it as a catalyst for future advancements in cellular biomanufacturing.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 01/29/2024<br> Modified by: Bhavana&nbsp; &nbsp;Singh</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055144/2055144_10504299_1706536678647_4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055144/2055144_10504299_1706536678647_4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Session B"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055144/2055144_10504299_1706536678647_4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Session B"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The session discussion, led by Dr. Peter Marks, focused on the complex regulatory landscape, encompassing financial and ethical implications, patient awareness, and healthcare policy coverage.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Diya Jacob</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bhavana&nbsp; &nbsp;Singh <div class="imageTitle">Session B</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055144/2055144_10504299_1706535087810_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055144/2055144_10504299_1706535087810_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="FDA representative Dr. Peter Marks"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055144/2055144_10504299_1706535087810_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="FDA representative Dr. Peter Marks"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">FDA representative Dr. Peter Marks delivering a presentation during the "Cellular Biomanufacturing 2023" workshop.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Diya Jacob</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bhavana&nbsp; &nbsp;Singh <div class="imageTitle">FDA representative Dr. Peter Marks</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055144/2055144_10504299_1706534785058_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055144/2055144_10504299_1706534785058_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Cellular Biomanufacturing 2023"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055144/2055144_10504299_1706534785058_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Cellular Biomanufacturing 2023"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Opening remarks by Dr. Bhavana Singh at the "Cellular Biomanufacturing 2023" workshop sponsored by NSF, held at the Children's National Research and Innovation Campus in Washington, DC, on August 10, 2023.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Diya Jacob</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bhavana&nbsp; &nbsp;Singh <div class="imageTitle">Cellular Biomanufacturing 2023</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055144/2055144_10504299_1706538331397_5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055144/2055144_10504299_1706538331397_5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="networking"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055144/2055144_10504299_1706538331397_5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="networking"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Attendees networking during the evening reception.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Diya Jacob</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bhavana&nbsp; &nbsp;Singh <div class="imageTitle">networking</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055144/2055144_10504299_1706536884767_3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055144/2055144_10504299_1706536884767_3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Session A"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055144/2055144_10504299_1706536884767_3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Session A"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Dr. Sean Palecek led the session discussion on the trajectory of cell therapies, addressing scientific challenges, process optimization, automation, scaling, and emerging technologies like artificial intelligence.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Diya Jacob</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bhavana&nbsp; &nbsp;Singh <div class="imageTitle">Session A</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  A series of NSF supported Cellular Biomanufacturing workshops were organized in 2017 and 2023 for Early Concept Grants for Exploratory Research (EAGER) awardees in cellular biomanufacturing to address emerging challenges. These workshops aimed to facilitate collaboration, knowledge sharing, and discussions on critical issues. By connecting academia, industry, and government, the workshops aimed to advance cellular therapies and make immunotherapy more accessible. The workshops aimed to raise NSF leadership awareness, evaluate EAGER awardees' contributions, and plan future meetings for collaborations, career opportunities, and industry engagement in cellular biomanufacturing.   The "Cellular Biomanufacturing 2023" workshop, an extension of the 2017 event, played a pivotal role in exploring the current state of therapeutic cell manufacturing. The workshop gathered representatives from various agencies, including NIH, NCI, and FDA, emphasizing collaboration, and acknowledging the evolving landscape of immunotherapies. The event aimed to examine the technological advancements, scientific gaps, and opportunities in therapeutic cell manufacturing since the inception of this NSF initiative.   The Cellular Biomanufacturing 2023 workshop featured presentations covering a wide array of topics, ranging from the support for discovery science by NSF to the regulatory considerations presented by representatives from the FDA. These presentations offered a comprehensive overview of the challenges, advancements, and regulatory frameworks shaping the field of cellular biomanufacturing. The presentations also included talks by NSF EAGER awardees, covering topics such as biomanufacturing of thymus organoids, drugs and biomarkers for COVID, and strategies for vascularization of engineered cardiac tissue scaffolds. Discussion sessions were organized to explore critical aspects of the field, with a focus on trajectory, scientific challenges, process optimization, automation, scaling, and emerging technologies like artificial intelligence.   The workshop served as a multifaceted platform for training and professional development in cellular biomanufacturing. Attendees gained technical knowledge through expert presentations and talks, fostering awareness of cutting-edge advancements in the field. Networking opportunities facilitated relationship-building among participants, experts, and government officials, expanding professional connections and fostering collaborations.   One of the key outcomes of the workshop was its impact on workforce development. The recommendations made during the workshop significantly are likely to influence the development of human resources in cellular bioengineering. Specialized training programs at two-year colleges, retraining initiatives, and apprenticeship programs were proposed to address workforce gaps in the cell biomanufacturing industry. These strategies aimed to align workforce skills with the needs of the industry, ensuring a skilled and diverse workforce. Moreover, the workshop emphasized the importance of workforce diversity and inclusivity. Initiatives to increase the participation of women in biomanufacturing, including programs supporting work-life balance, maternity leave, and retraining grants, were recommended. These efforts aimed to transform the culture within the research and manufacturing sectors, promoting a multidisciplinary approach in science, engineering, and technology.   The workshop also evaluated different biomanufacturing approaches, particularly modular versus all-in-one strategies in the context of autologous and allogeneic cell-based therapies. The discussions highlighted the advantages of modular processes, emphasizing flexibility and adaptability in optimizing manufacturing processes.   Another focus of the workshop was the exploration of the role of artificial intelligence (AI), predictive biology, and machine learning in biomanufacturing. Acknowledging the transformative potential of AI models, the workshop advocated for data availability and collaboration across diverse scholarly domains, as well as the incorporation of AI into the curriculum and workforce development programs.   The workshop's recommendations, encompassing findings, results, and techniques, are anticipated to exert a significant influence that extends beyond the realm of cellular biomanufacturing, resonating across diverse fields. Discussions on AI and modular approaches are likely to find relevance in biomedical engineering, data science, and artificial intelligence. Similarly, insights into regulatory considerations are expected to extend their influence into the domain of regulatory affairs. The strategies outlined for workforce development have the potential to shape educational practices across various disciplines. The workshop's recommendations, with their far-reaching implications, are anticipated to influence and guide developments in physical, institutional, and information resources. Additionally, the proposed technology transfer initiatives are expected to foster collaboration, engage industries, support workforce development, integrate technology, provide education, address regulations, and promote small businesses, ultimately contributing to advancements in cellular biomanufacturing technologies across diverse sectors.   The workshop aimed to create a positive societal impact by addressing broader challenges and opportunities beyond the academic and research community. This impact included improved healthcare access, advancements in pediatric cancer treatments, positive contributions to workforce diversity and economic stimulation, ethical considerations in the development and deployment of biomanufactured products, and public awareness and engagement.   In conclusion, the "Cellular Biomanufacturing 2023" workshop served as a dynamic platform for advancing knowledge, fostering collaboration, and shaping the trajectory of cellular biomanufacturing. The recommendations made during the workshop were likely to contribute significantly to the ongoing development of the field, impacting various aspects such as workforce development, technology transfer, and societal implications. The workshop's multidisciplinary approach and emphasis on cutting-edge technologies positioned it as a catalyst for future advancements in cellular biomanufacturing.     Last Modified: 01/29/2024       Submitted by: Bhavana Singh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
